<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The diall of destiny A booke very delectable and pleasaunt: wherein may be seene the continuall and customable course, disposition, qualities, effectes, and influence of the seuen planets ouer all kyndes of creatures here belowe: also the seuerall and sundry situation of countryes and kingdomes. Compiled and discussed briefly, aswell astrologically, as poetically, and philosophically by Iohn Maplet Maister of Arte.</title>
            <author>Maplet, John, d. 1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120741</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855935</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855935</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21445</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21445)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 556:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The diall of destiny A booke very delectable and pleasaunt: wherein may be seene the continuall and customable course, disposition, qualities, effectes, and influence of the seuen planets ouer all kyndes of creatures here belowe: also the seuerall and sundry situation of countryes and kingdomes. Compiled and discussed briefly, aswell astrologically, as poetically, and philosophically by Iohn Maplet Maister of Arte.</title>
                  <author>Maplet, John, d. 1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 73, [3] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fleestreat [sic] neere vnto Sainte Dunstones Church by Thomas Marshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Instead of index at end, the British Library copy has 2 leaves: "A description of such dayes as are most happie and vnhappie" possibly also printed by Marsh.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE <hi>DIALL OF Deſtiny. A BOOKE VERY DELECTABLE AND</hi>
               </hi> PLEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt: wherein may be ſeene the <hi>continuall and customable courſe,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, qualities, effectes, and influence <hi>of the Seuen Planets ouer all kyndes of</hi> Creatures here belowe: alſo the ſeuerall and ſundry ſituation of Countryes <hi>and Kingdomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compiled and diſcuſſed</hi> Briefly, aſwell Aſtrologically, <hi>as Poetically, and Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally <hi>By Iohn Maplet</hi>
               </hi> Maiſter of Arte.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>IMPRINTED AT London in Fleestreat neere</hi> vnto Sainte Dunſtones <hi>Church By Thomas</hi> Marſhe. <hi>1581.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="Psalm">
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:2"/>
            <head>Pſalme 136.</head>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> O Praiſe the Lord of Heauen which by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente wiſedome made the heauens: which made great Lights, the Sun to rule the day: the Moone and the Stars to Gouerne the night.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HONORABLE, SIR</hi> CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOPHER HATTON, Knight,</hi> one of the <hi>Queenes Maieſties</hi> moſt Honourable priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and Captayne of her Graces Garde.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>ENOPIDES</hi> Chius (moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Syr) dedicated at the Tryumphes holde in Greece to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Iupiter Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus (or as others write) to Hercules, a Booke of his owne framing and make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of Braſſe: the Methode and matter whereof was nothing elſe but a ſummary Diſcourſe collected oute of Plato as concerning the continuance, circuite, and courſe of the ſeuen Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets. VVhich buſines ſo carefully, and coſtly perfourmed by the aforeſayd Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, is here peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture in another ſort with other neceſſary ſequell thereof, &amp; with leſſe a doe alſo and leſſe coſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:21445:3"/>&amp; debated. VVhich ſmall treatiſe of myne, neyther crauing Iupiter, nor Hercules, but requireth rather youre honors preſent Patrocynie, and fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable protection: Your Honour being now in theſe dayes to our moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Prince, &amp; the VVeale Publike eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame that PHOCION a moste renowmed Captayne was to the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians: And as EPAMINON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAS was to the Thebanes. Three rare &amp; royall vertues there are which AGESILAVS (ſpeaking it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good tryall and proofe thereof) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth to bee in a Captayne ſet ouer the Prynces Garde: the first hee ſayth, is fidelity to his Soueraygne, whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon hee is moste carefully to ſafegarde and defend: the ſecond (he ſayth) is an hawty heart and valiancy of Mynde, friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y affected towards his friendes, and litle eſteming the force of his foes: and the last he repoſeth in ripeneſſe of Iudgement &amp; dexterity of VViſdome
<pb facs="tcp:21445:3"/>in geuing of common wealth councell. All which three Ormame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; Iewels, and the ſame three (I dare vtter it) thriſe doubled and trebled, shyne and shewe forth in your Honor very reſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dishingly. Inſomuch that if I were (as I am nothing fit thereto) to determyn as the Orator DEMADES did, of Noble Perſonages and moste worthy VVyghtes euen eyes of the Realme, as hee calleth them: the conſideration of your honors ſo Infinite and inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues, euen of very right deſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, required (I shoulde ſay very worthely) your Honors accoumpt (as it alſo hath already) among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Senators and Sages of this Land. And whereas many other Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gouerned onely as it were Cyclopy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, (that is to ſay) wyth myght &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely force, therewith onely defeng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, being wythout theyr wyſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, as it were without their Eyes (as the Poets ſay the great Gyaunte CY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLOPS
<pb facs="tcp:21445:4"/>is) doe yet neuertheleſſe for want of the ſame runne oftentimes to much ruyne, ſubiection, and ſubuerſion. This our Countrey and Nation (the Lord bee hyghly thanked therefore) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuch theyr Eyes and eyſight, as it hath in deede very cleare, perfite, and pretious, whereby aſwell all the whole body of the Realme: as alſo euery parte thereof is most happely dyrected in all kinde of ſafety: howe greatly wee and the ſame is to glorifie GOD therefore, though I ſhould ſay nothing thereof but be ſilent therein, the very force of ſuch a ryche bleſſinge and Benefite, it ſelfe would burst forth and ſpeake it. Now the cauſe that only mooued me at this time, to craue your Honores Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauncinge of this Litle Treatiſe, was chiefly, the heareſay of your Honoures accustomed Clemency, and Curteſy in like behalfe towardes others. VVhich being any thinge accepted at your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors hands, ſhall encourage me hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:21445:4"/>to other Trauayles and endeuours. In the meane tyme I ſhall not ceaſe to pray to the gouernor of all, the Lord of Lordes, for the proſperous &amp; long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of your Honour, and for the continuance of your honors estate &amp; good lyking, to the glory of GOD, the contentation of the Prynce, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of the Countrey.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Northall <date>The laſt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember. 1581.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honors humble and dayly Orator. Iohn Maplet.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>YRESIAS King</hi> the <hi>Thebanes</hi> being in that fooliſhe minde, &amp; ſo perſwaded with him ſelfe that the Stars had no ſuch Pryuiledge or rule in Mans body, or elſe, as the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians did playnely affirme, was (as the Poets Imagine) with the aduiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the all (not ſuffering ſuch ſpeech) ſtriken ſtarke blind and quite bereued of his ſenſe of ſeing. And in deede thoſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men or vnaduiſed ſort which are in a manner come to the ſame paſſe that COTTA the Epicure with CICE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RO, &amp; DEMOCRITVS were at, that all things here belowe come to paſſe by chaunce, meere Caſually, or at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, accordingly as they hap well or ill, they are eyther blinde in knowledge, or elſe are wedded to much to their owne Wits and Willes, dealing with the caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall povvers prepoſterouſly. For PTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOMY plainely proueth an eſpeciall
<pb facs="tcp:21445:5"/>kinde of Influence from them all, vvhich diſpoſeth all bodies here beneath accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to euery ones eſpeciall and naturall propriety. In ſo much that BALBVS the Stoycke is rather to be borne withall, then theſe kynde of Men, which vppon three Principall cauſes, and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was enforced and driuen to graunte ſome ſuperior kindes of fatall prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And the firſte reaſon and cauſe therevnto moouinge him vvas the viewe of ſuch ſundrye Varietyes, and ſuch plentifull ſtoare of Commodities, as which doe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ariſe both in the Earth as in the Sea and Ayre, through the contemperature, and variable diſpoſition of the heauenly powers. The ſecond occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that brought him hereto was, the perceyuinge of the wonderful differences and contrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertyes both of minde as of body in all thinges almoſt, that hee coulde not choſe but thinke and Imagine a ſundrye cauſe for euery one. Thirdly the diſtinct order and placinge of eche thinge to the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuation of the ſame in his kinde, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked and enforced him for to reſt and grounde vpon ſome Superior workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or Authors aboue. Moreouer a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
<pb facs="tcp:21445:6"/>of the Planets, property, and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth in this reſpect offer it ſelfe to be ſeene apparantly, euen in the frame &amp; Workemanſhip of Man kinde, vvhereas euery perſon almoſt hath his ſeuerall and ſundry Inclination: ſome to vertue, ſome agayn to vice: ſome alſo hauing good hap, and other ſome hauing ſiniſter fortune. And whereas vvicked men for the moſte porte ruffle in the vvorld, fortune alwais laughing on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as MARIVS, SYL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LA, DYONISIVS the cruell Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, PYSISTRATVS, POLY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRATES, &amp; PHALARIS, And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwyſe it is here vvith goodme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the moſt parte, as it vvas vvith PAVLVS AEMILIVS a valyaunte Vanquiſher, and a good man, yet through cruell fate murdered &amp; ſlayne vvith his vvhole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at a ſkyrmiſhe fought at <hi>Canna.</hi> It vvas alſo Aphricanus his hap to be bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his countrey and to dye in exile. It vvas CATVLVS his chaunce to bee ſlayne of his mortall enemy MARIVS. The two valiaunte SCYPIOES loſt their liues in <hi>Spayne.</hi> Yea and vvee ſee dayly the ſuddayne ryſing of many men from their lowe Eſtate to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb facs="tcp:21445:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of dignity: as IPHICRATES a Coblers ſonne, aduaunced to bee a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne vnder ARTAXERZES king of <hi>Perſia.</hi> RVMENES CARDIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVS borne in <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> a Carters ſon, aftervvards made Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uſay lor to ALEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANDER the greate. AGATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLES a Potters ſon, aftervvards chiefe of <hi>Syracuſa.</hi> IVLIVS LICINIVS a Huſband mans ſon aftervvards Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Dacia.</hi> Yea, and many contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe being Royally and nobly borne by fatall deſtiny haue fell from aloft: as AL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIBIADES, POMPEYE, yea &amp; PTOLOMEVS the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> king vvhich in hys ruffe and youthfull dayes, banquetted &amp; feaſted dayly a Thowſand Gueſtes ordinarely, ſeruinge them all in their Golden Plate, and yet hee himſelfe aftervvardes as he grevve olde vvas dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to that extremity, that he vvas faine to be ſuſtayned &amp; relieued at other mens handes very barely and courſly. Yea, and beſides this many haue ſuch cruell deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye that as ſoone as they bee borne they are ſubiect to be ſwallowed and ſoopt vp ſtraightwais of ſome one dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger or other:
<pb facs="tcp:21445:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>as was SEMIRAMIS borne of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bloude: and PYRRHVS, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards King of the <hi>Epirotet.</hi> Which both were throwen out &amp; caſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their frends being Sucklings and Infants, and yet by fate of Fortune and by great prouidence preſerued euen at the very dent &amp; brym of preſent and Imminent deſtruction. By ſuch meanes alſo was CYRVS ſo hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of from his friends, ſuſtayned &amp; nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the meanes of a Bitche: ſo was TELEPHVS by a Harte: PELIAS Son to NEPTVNVS by a Mare: PARIS by a ſhe Beare: AEGYSTVS by a ſhe Goate: ROMVLVS, and REMVS by a ſhe Woulfe. In the wonderfull deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery &amp; dealing vvhereof vvhat kinde of Fate and Prouidence this and an Infinite number ſuch lyke was, I referre the ſame (gentle reader) to thine owne determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereof this Treatiſe (if thou vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chſafeſt the thorough Readinge thereof) doth ſhewe forth both in proofe &amp; in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample more aboundantly. The name al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vvhich I haue gieuen to this booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge it the <hi>Dyall</hi> of <hi>Deſtiny,</hi> doth well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough as I thinke agree to the purpoſe. For Dyall vyiſe it goeth from poynte &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21445:7"/>poynte, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Degree to Degree ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubiection of euery eche kinde to his ſundry and ſeuerall Superior Planet. Which labos of mine ſuch as it is, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue thou thankfully: And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue I that Recompence that I doe require.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition">
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:8"/>
            <head>To the ſcornefull ſort <hi>of Scycophantes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>OLLIO</hi> playe not the <hi>PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LYPRAGMON</hi> or Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie body: I wys it becommeth you not. The <hi>Parrat</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniaye</hi> playe ſuch partes for Pray ſake, rather then of property: but the <hi>Corniſh Choughs</hi> and Carrenly <hi>Crovves</hi> haue it of cuſtome. If youre wonte bee ſuch it is worſe then I wyſhe it were. And then I perceiue this Prouerbe is playne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si Coruus poſſet tacitus paſci, haberet plus dapis.</hi> But like Lyps like Lettice. Dayneties ſurely deſire or looke you for none till that your maners be mended.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21445:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>OF THE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord or common felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of the ſeuen Planets, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of their breadefull debate and diſcorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is manyfeſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by argumentes of force, and reaſons of more ſecret and hid phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, likewiſe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Mathematicall, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all Creatures whatſoeuer whych haue their being eſſence, and preſeruation vpon the face of the whole Earth, or els be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned within the Regions or Precinct of the Ayre aboue, and ſubiected vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or Sphere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, haue &amp; receiue their influence of the higher and more Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall hodies or Planets: and after a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſorte (ſayth <hi>Proclus</hi>) they reſi &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of them. And heerem his ſaying ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not to bee amiſſe, for that experience playnly teacheth vs, and we alſo ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is nothinge heere belowe ſo able, ſtronge, or riche of it ſelfe, that being voyde or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb facs="tcp:21445:9"/>of the fauour or furtheraunce of the celeſtiall bodies aboue, can be well pleaſed and contented with it ſelfe. <hi>Agrippa</hi> is in that opinion that at the former conſtitution or firſt breedinge of euery ech thinge, both that which lyueth, as alſo that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde of lyfe (as likewiſe at the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or compoſition of the Clements for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moreaſe of any baſer kindes) the bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of certayne planets is ſuch oftentimes, that beſides the beneficialneſſe of the owne nature of the thinges themſelues (which worketh alwayes liberally) there is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther free gyft beſtowed vpon euery y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd thinges, and kindes by the Planets them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and the ſame more rightly or preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they meete together in more happy ſigne, or be in higher <hi>Horoſcope</hi> or Aſcendent. <hi>Plato</hi> wyth his Conſectaryes doe affyrme, that all theſe Daughters or progeny of Dame Nature, are euery one of them firſt ſealed &amp; (as it were) marked of the ſtarres and Planets aboue, whereby in euery thing they haue to chalenge their owne. And euen as by God the greateſt &amp; mightieſt of all, and the firſt and principall cauſe of all things, all creatures are diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21445:9"/>generally to a like frame and cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order of the ſelfe ſame kinde: ſo in lyke ſorte by the ſeconde cauſes the Planets al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though inferiours yet working cauſes, all things here vnderueath are in more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſorte ſealed and enſampled. Eaſy it is to ſee that there is no one parte in all the whole proportion &amp; workmanſhip of mans body, that is not ruled or diſpoſed by ſome one Planet or other, to affectate that moſt of all other thinges which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperior force doth frame them and enclyne them vnto: ſo that vnto me all the whole body of man, as alſo the bodies of all other creatures here below, ſeeme to be poſſeſſed, buſied, and as it were incenſed and ſet on worke by them. As for example. To begin with <hi>Sol</hi> or the Sunne, it is apparant how he holdeth, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth, and hath in poſſeſſion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Braynes and forepart of the head, the heart, the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the right Eye, the vitall Spirite or breath of life: likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mouth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tongue, and all other the Organes or inſtruments of ſenſe, or feeling: beſides this, he chaleng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hands, the feete, the Synewes, the Imagination, and whole operation of the powre phantaſticall. The Moone likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:21445:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath in her ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ordreth after a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſorte all the whole body, in ſuch wiſe as both the humors and moyſture both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and accidental: doth either abounde in them or dyminiſhe and leſſen, according to her prime and wane. And whereas ſhee thus worketh generally in all ſortes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her owne variation, ſo in the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all members and partes of the body, ſhee eſpecially ruleth in the Lunges, and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alſo with a great portion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Brayne. Hers is alſo the Marrow of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Backbone, as alſo the ſtomacke, the leſt Eye, with all the other partes that yeelde forth &amp; auoyde the excrementes, and ſuperfluities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, with the powre and vertue increaſinge. <hi>Saturne</hi> is lord ouer the Lyuer, and hath to doe with the bottome or loweſt parte of the ſtomacke. <hi>Iupiter</hi> chalengeth a righte in the Belly, as likewiſe in the Nauell: in ſo much that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Temple of <hi>Iupiter Ham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon in Lybia,</hi> the figure or lykeneſſe of a Mans Nauell was hanged vp, to fignifie thereby that the thorough cloſing and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together of the Belly belongeth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelfe. Likewiſe hee hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21445:10"/>the Ribbes, and the place aboute the priuities, as alſo the Bowels, &amp; Entrailes within. Moreouer the beſt and more prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall bloude is his, as alſo both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armes, and both the handes, as well the righte as the left, with all the whole powre &amp; vertue <hi>Nutritiue,</hi> whereby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and maynteyned. To <hi>Mars</hi> apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth and belongeth the ſeconde &amp; more baſe Bloude, as alſo the Vaines, the Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the Celles or placinges of the Cheſt, the Backe, the Buttockes, the Corſe and abundaunce of Seede, as alſo all that full powre of the Stomacke wherein Choler is ingendred. Proper to <hi>Mercury</hi> is the Splene, the Mylte, the Bladder, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, and all thoſe places within the Body which are naturally appoynted to the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe and office of nouriſhing. <hi>Venus</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Secret partes, and ordereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Seede, and alſo cauſeth and proun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the Luſt and Appetite of thinges. It may be perceyued alſo that in ſome one parte of the body, they will all ſeuen beare a ſway.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hermes</hi> ſayth, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of man there
<pb facs="tcp:21445:11"/>are ſeuen Pores or holes, allotted to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and ſundry offices, of the which euery one of them is ſubiect to a ſundry Planet. As that Pore or hole which is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righte Eare apperteineth to <hi>Saturne:</hi> that in the left to <hi>Iupiter: Mars</hi> alſo hath the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that which is in the right ſide of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe: <hi>Venus</hi> the contrary: <hi>Sol</hi> is maiſter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that which holdeth the ſtringes of the Eye: <hi>Luna</hi> ouer the other in the left Eye: and all the whole workmanſhip of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth is proper alone to <hi>Mercury.</hi> Great &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe alſo are all ſuch Benefites of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, as alſo the other baſer kyndes doe eſtſoones receiue of the Planets, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when as thoſe of like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, nature, &amp; quality doe meete together in gracious ſignes of like houſe. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and hearde is their happe, fortune, and chaunce, which haue and obtayne any thing of them as they be in battlement, ſtryfe, &amp; contencion among them ſelues. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not greatly do amyſſe, if in this place I briefly touch, which of them with other are in friendly league and likance, &amp; in like ſorte, which of them with other are at deadly diſcorde, and diſagreement.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21445:11"/>
            <p>Friends to <hi>Saturne</hi> and his welwillers are <hi>Iupiter. Mercury, Sol,</hi> and <hi>Luna:</hi> his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Vonus. Iupiters</hi> friends are all the other, only <hi>Mars</hi> excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Mars</hi> is deſpiſed and deteſted of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, except onely of <hi>Venus. Sol</hi> is in great friendſhip with <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and in greathatred with <hi>Mars, Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Luna. Venus</hi> hath the loue of all the reſt ſaue onely of <hi>Saturne.</hi> In friendſhip with <hi>Mercury,</hi> are <hi>Iupiter, Venus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne:</hi> his enemies are <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mars.</hi> Friends to <hi>Luna,</hi> are <hi>Iupiter, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Saturne:</hi> her enemies are <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury.</hi> Great contencion alſo is amongſt them as they be placed in contrary houſe: as betwene <hi>Saturne,</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> And a much more great debate or ſtrife is betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they bee in Oppoſite, lofte, or degree in Exaltation. Which thing is often ſhewed forth betwene <hi>Saturne,</hi> and <hi>Sol: Iupiter,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mars: Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mercury.</hi> And further their attonement, or agreement is in lyke Nature, Quality, Subſtaunce, might, or powre: as is of <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Sol: Venus,</hi> and <hi>Luna: Iupiter,</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> In ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:21445:12"/>that it was not without iuſte cauſe and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt in that <hi>Heraclitus</hi> ſayd, that al things were perſited and made by a proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip and diſcord. By theſe Planets alſo happeneth better chaunce &amp; fortune, as alſo miſchaunce &amp; miſfortune. Inſomuch that ſome of them are tearmed the Gods of grace and fortune: as is <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> whom they name <hi>Fortuna maior,</hi> the greater or more gracious. Likewiſe <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who in the rules of Aſtrologie is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Fortuna minor,</hi> as if you woulde ſay leſſe gracious, and yet a Lady of grace. The other are called the Gods of miſhap or caſuall chaunce, of the which ſort is <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> whom they name <hi>Infortuna ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior:</hi> As alſo <hi>Mars</hi> which is called <hi>Infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na minor.</hi> And <hi>Mercury,</hi> which is called the God of indifferency, who is for al com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, for with the good, he is good, and with the bad, he is as bad. <hi>Sol</hi> by his ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sunne beames, and amiable aſpecte or countenaunce, is cheareful to al things: but being in coniunction with other or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clypſed, both hindreth much for the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time, &amp; prognoſticateth, &amp; threatneth more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21445:12"/>for the future time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. The moone is ſent in meſſage from one to another, and hath hir recourſe and paſſage by them all: ſo that ſhe hurteth or benefiteth as occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerueth by them, &amp; from them. By <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> alſo they haue all theyr determynate kinde: As <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> are feminyne or of the woman kinde: And all the other are accompted Maſculine, or after men. They are alſo deuided into Planets of the day, and Planets of the nighte. The day Planets are <hi>Saturne, Iupiter, Sol,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie.</hi> The night Planets are <hi>Mars, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Luna.</hi> Againe they be ſo deuyded as that certaine of them be holden for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and Maſſie, of the which ſorte are <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iupiter,</hi> and <hi>Mars:</hi> other are as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and light, as are <hi>Venus, Mercury,</hi> &amp; <hi>Luna.</hi> But <hi>Sol</hi> or the ſunne is partaker of neither of both theſe properties. Amongſt the elementes theſe do alſo contend for the ſuperiority. For <hi>Iupiter</hi> dealeth with that commixture whych partely is of the ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and partely of the Water. <hi>Luna</hi> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone exacteth that which conſyſteth and commeth of the Water alone.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol</hi> alſo helpeth forwardes the meanes, or maner in doing or acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhing of things. <hi>Luna</hi> or the Moone, as it were miniſtreth matter in ſuch behalfes. <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> labour their proceeding &amp; going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and doe geue them ſpeedy and quick expedition: the firſte by the meanes of his force, and might, and the other by his apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Dexterity in deliueraunce. The plenty and ſtore of matter commeth from <hi>Venus,</hi> and the continuation or wayght of any buſineſſe whatſoeuer, is proper alone to <hi>Saturne.</hi> Moreouer all the <hi>Sygnes</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Zodiacall</hi> Circle doe participate, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the qualities of the ſeuen Planets. As <hi>Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Capricornus,</hi> bee <hi>Saturnine: Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Libra,</hi> are after <hi>Iupiter: Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> and <hi>Scorpio,</hi> be after <hi>Mars: Cancer,</hi> &amp; <hi>Leo,</hi> be after <hi>Sol</hi> or the Sunne: <hi>Gemini,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> be after <hi>Venus: Aquari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> bee after the Moone. And accordinge to the courſe of the Sunne, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Gemini,</hi> doe procure a warme and moyſt Spring time, very good for the <hi>Sanguine</hi> Complexion, and for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age. <hi>Cancer, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Virgo,</hi> likewiſe cauſe a hoat Summer &amp; a dry: very good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21445:13"/>for the Cholericke complexion and men of middle age. Likewiſe <hi>Libra, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> cauſe a colde and moyſt <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne,</hi> agreable to the Phlegmaticke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and younge age. And <hi>Capricor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, A quarius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> cauſe the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter naturally to be cold and dry, aunſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Melancholicke complexion, and to olde Age. But of theſe thinges we are to ſpeake of, as Occaſion ſhall ſerue more particulerly, as hereafter followeth.</p>
            <div n="moon" type="part">
               <head>Of LVNA, or the Moone,</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Sol</hi> or the Sunne is the Beauty, Grace, and Countenaunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day: ſo in like ſorte is <hi>Luna,</hi> or the Moone the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, light geuer, and glory of the night. And they both haue for this ſuch their Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and goodnes, the greateſt prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and accoumpte of all other Planets. Whereupon it was not wont good cauſe, and conſideration that in olde and auncient time, both of theſe when at any tyme they
<pb facs="tcp:21445:14"/>were Depictures or drawen forth by any Artificer, Engrauer, or Paynter, they were then chiefly ſet out in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſhion, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe or Habite of a Virgin: and in both their handes were placed and put fine and feate Arrowes, or dartes, to ſignifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that the light which proceeded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe two, was onely cleare, vndefiled, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ſpot: and that theſe were the onely Planets which threwe as it were, and caſt from them the gliſtering beames of cleare and comfortable lighte, as Arrowes or Dartes: whereby all things cheared, and continued the better in their Eſtate, wyth well lyking.<note place="margin">LVNA hovv cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> This ſame <hi>Luna</hi> therefore is with the Poets called <hi>Lucina</hi> the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Goddeſſe of the nyghte. And for that ſhe doth not onely appeare or ſhyne in the night time, but is ſeene oftentimes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our heade in our <hi>Horizon</hi> in the day time. It is growne to a cuſtome, and brought nowe amonge vs to this paſſe &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhee is alſo of ſome called <hi>Diana</hi> (as if you woulde ſay <hi>Duana</hi>) for her thorow preſence both in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day &amp; night: or as <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> better reaſoneth, for that ſhee with her bright looke oftentimes cauſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night to appeare as though it were day. This of al
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21445:14"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other planets is placed loweſt, &amp; is nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earth, for which cauſe ſhe ſheweth forth &amp; ſeemeth vnto our eyeſight to bee ſo great: her figure or faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of body is rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; of her own nature ſhe is fiery, although caſually intermedling w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vapors, water, &amp; ſo forth, ſhe appeareth to be in colour wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which much troubleth her: whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is reported y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (were it not for ſuch lettes, &amp; hinderaunces, as by this meanes it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto) ſhe would ſhyne forth as fully as doth the Sunne, The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> call it. <hi>TSAR,</hi> or <hi>LECANNATH:</hi> the Greekes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. She geueth her chiefeſt light on y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſide or part which is oppoſite againſt the Sun, &amp; is euer darkned on y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſide which is turned away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sun. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone be <hi>3.</hi> ſtates or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions to be obſerued &amp; wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay,<note place="margin">Three ſtares in the Moo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> either as ſhe is in coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Sun: or els as ſhe is on ſome of his ſides, or els as ſhee departeth &amp; goeth backe furder of from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the is in this laſt of <hi>3.</hi> point, ſhe will appeare end wiſe, with her hornes reaching towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly as ſhe is in oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſun and draweth nighe to that pointe, ſhee appeareth all ouer a like rounde with the
<pb facs="tcp:21445:15"/>Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, but her reuolution then is moſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Weſt. And laſtly as on eyther ſide ſhee turneth more or leſſe towardes the Sunne, ſo is ſhee the more obſcured or lightned. <hi>Marcianus</hi> ſayth that there is a certayne Stayne or Spot euer ſeene in the Moone, which blemiſheth her brightneſſe greatly: eſpecially the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when as ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Myſtes, or of any other <hi>Metecre</hi> is troubleſome vnto her. Her houſe is onely in <hi>Cancer,</hi> Her exaltacion is in the fourth of <hi>Taurus,</hi> Her qualies are cold &amp; moiſte. As likewiſe her effectes or workinge is to make colde and moyſte. Where ſhe colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſhe geueth a ſaffron colour: &amp; in taſtes or ſauoures ſhe worketh &amp; maketh the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Her courſe or race is of all other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets moſt ſwift:<note place="margin">her courſe</note> for in <hi>28.</hi> dayes ſhe paſſeth through all and ſinguler <hi>Signes</hi> of the <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacke.</hi> And for ſuch her ſwiftnes or haſte it happeneth ſomewhiles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhee is vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne, another while aboue: one while ſhe is before, another while behinde. And when as the Sunne is in his courſe or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite by the nethermoſt circles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouth, and the Moone contrariwiſe in the higheſt circle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> North, then the top of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21445:15"/>appeareth like a Cockbote or ſmall ſhip, and her hornes are vpwarde. But when as ſhe is vnder the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, her hornes giue downewarde towardes the earth. From y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone are gathered and coniectured cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine probable ſignes,<note place="margin">Certayne prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations from the Moone.</note> whereby we prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate and foreſhewe of the alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of times &amp; mutability of the weather to come. As when the Moone by and by after her chaunge doth appeare red, ſhee prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cateth wyndes and tempeſtuous weather, the moſt parte of the ſayde Moones conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. Agayne if vpon her chaunge ſhee incontinently at her Top or higheſt parte looketh blacke, or be there darckened ſhee foreſheweth rayne, and a wet &amp; moyſte firſt quarter. But if ſhee bee onely obſcured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middle of her, ſhee prognoſticateth a fayre full Moone and laſt quarter of the ſame. The Eclypſe of the Moone is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally cauſed through the interpoſition of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth betwene the Moone &amp; our eyeſight:<note place="margin">The Moones Eclypſe.</note> but then eſpecially is ſhe Eclipſed when as the bodies both of the Sunne, Moone, and Earth are right oppoſitly ſet one ouer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in one &amp; the ſelfe ſame contrary line: ſo that by ſuch occaſion, one darckeneth and
<pb facs="tcp:21445:16"/>obſcureth another. Her chaunge, increaſe, and decreaſe, hath much troubled the wits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Aſtronomers.</hi> As hardly alſo can they render a reaſon &amp; geue forth the cauſe why one while ſhee croketh in to hornes, why another while ſhe wexeth all rounde, why one while ſhe ſhyneth in one parte of her, why another ſhe geueth light al ouer why now ſhe is ſeene all night, why now but a piece of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night: why now leauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nighte time, ſhee ſheweth her ſelfe onely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day time: why now ſhee is cleare and radiant, why anon blotted and blemiſhed: why now caried Northwarde, why anon mooninge directly Southward. Which al and other ſuch like meruaylons and ſtraunge effects and properties (are reported by <hi>Plinie</hi> in his ſecond booke and eight chapter to haue bene beſt obſerued by <hi>Endymion</hi> being as is there ſayde, rauiſhed &amp; in great loue for ſuch her aſtoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, fel ſo to affectionate her, that accomptinge more of her then of all the other <hi>Supercoeleſtiall</hi> powres, ſhee to requite him like loue agayne, is ſayd to haue diſcended on a time and to haue kiſſed the ſayd <hi>Endymion</hi> as he lay a ſleepe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Latmus,</hi> &amp; Mountayne in <hi>Caria, Plinie</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21445:16"/>in his fourtenth chapter of the aforeſayde boke doth report, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alwaies at the Moones increaſe, her hornes are turned from the Sunne: as contrariwiſe as ſhe decreaſeth ſhee turneth her hornes toward the Sun.<note place="margin">Many Moones at once.</note> There haue appeared Many Moones at once, but neuer more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three at one time. And three appeared at one tyme manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d booke of the ſayd <hi>Plinie</hi> and xxxii. chapter is recorded: that is to ſay, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of the prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Cneius Domitius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Three moones ſeene at one tyme.</note> and <hi>Lucius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius:</hi> which were called of ſome then, the night Suns. Likewyſe it hath bene ſeene &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Author doth affirm it to be true,<note place="margin">lib. 2. cap. 32.</note> that there hath appeared ſuch lightes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, as that it hath bene in a manner all one with the day light. As for example: In the tyme of <hi>Caius Cecilius</hi> and <hi>Cneius Papirius,</hi> they beyng conſuls,<note place="margin">Lights in the Night like the day, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</note> ſuch lights were ſeene in the night, as that the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes thereof could not be diſcerned from the brightnes of the noone day. And at diuers other tymes in ages and yeares ſynce, ſuch ſtraunge ſights ther haue bene ſeene, ſuch ſightes in the Night, as men haue ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to haue bene day. There haue bene
<pb facs="tcp:21445:17"/>alſo Bucklers of fyre ſene gliſteryng from the Weſt to the Eaſte,<note place="margin">Bucklers of fier.</note> and of all theſe the moſt greuous of others to behold, &amp; which bred greateſt wonder hapned in the tyme of the <hi>Conſulſhip</hi> of <hi>Lucius Valerius</hi> and <hi>Cneius Marius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fiery flames</note> There hath alſo ben ſeene and be often as yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, fiery flames or burninges in the element or ayre, which haue ſhewed forth diuers and ſundry like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: ſo that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought to haue reſembled and to bee like vnto a Candle or Torch burning:<note place="margin">Torches. Fiery bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Fiery ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res. Svvordes. Fery darts</note> ſome like vnto fiery beames: ſome like vnto pillers ſet on fire: ſome are after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſpeares: ſom ſhewing forth the likenes of ſwords: ſome not much vnlike horſes manes: ſome ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing forth the likenes of hornes: ſome as it were fiery darts. And al theſe &amp; ſuch other like apparitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre which in Greeke by a general and more common name are called <hi>Eupicaumata,</hi> do appear for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte in the calme &amp; cleare night, although ſomewhile ſome of theſe are ſeene in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day time. And all theſe aryſe euer vnder the globe or circle of the Moone. The proofe whereof herein is manifeſte, for that they continue not in one and the ſelf ſame place
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21445:17"/>long, but moue with a ſwift paſſage, &amp; are caryed away with the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moones motion. Wee ſhall not therefore greatlye go aſtray if we gieue forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of theſe apparitions and ſights, and do declare the maner and matter of theyr engendring.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cauſes hereof.</note>The efficient cauſe of theſe fiery impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions bred and ingendred through heat, is the ſunne, and the reſt of the bodies celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: which in theyr motions as they labour in their courſe, caſte from them exceſſyue heate vpon theſe bodies, and places below here ſubiected: Which heat catcheth and carieth vp into the ayre all ſuch exhalatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues alſo be hoat and dry) as are ready for ſuch receipt. Then the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall cauſe is nothing els but ſuch kynd of Exhalation: euen as wodde is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fyre, &amp; oyle of the flame. Now theyr generation is after this ſorte: The Earth being throughly warmed through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne and the other ſtarres, doth thereupon caſt from her and ſend forth, a double kind of ſpiration of breathyng: one kynd very dry accordynge as the places from whych it is ſente forthe, bee drye: and this kynd of exhalation being naturally hoate and
<pb facs="tcp:21445:18"/>drye is much like vnto that fume or ſmoke which proceedeth from ſtickes or wood ſet on fyre and kyndled. Secondly by ſuch heat rayſed from the Sunne and Starres, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, there is fetched from ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as be moyſt, an other more groſſe, kind of fume, hot and moyſt, which is called a vapour like vnto that maner of euaporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeething water. Theſe two caught vp into the ayre, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng there diuerſly placed and ſet on worke, by the element of the ſire (vnto which, the firſt ſort called exhalations do eftſones ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and come neere) do cauſe ſtraunge ſightes in the Regions of the Ayre, for the exhalations beinge both ayry &amp; fyery, are ſone kyndled and ſet on fyre, &amp; become flames, and fierye impreſſions: euen as the drie ſnaſt of a candel, or as the fare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lunge ſticke is ſoone ſet on flame. For the flame of any thing is nothinge els, but the fume of the ſame already kindled: and it is ſo ſoone kindled becauſe it is of a drye and fyery nature. Now the faſhion and forme of the fiery flames ſeene often tymes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the element, do vary and differ one from another, as they haue more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſuch matter of exhalation or leſſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21445:18"/>as they are placed alſo in other &amp; contrary order.<note place="margin">Burning lampes.</note> For when ſuch exhalation is diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in breadth, and diſcontinued, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as it were burning lampes: &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame is fy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red round, and caſteth from it ſparcles, then ſuch impreſſion is after a goate, and is ſo called: when that doth not ſparcle, but burneth greate aboue &amp; ſmal below, it is called a fyrebrande.<note place="margin">Firebrand</note> And that kynd of exhalation which burneth both in breadth and length, and moueth apace in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre, leauing after it ſom ſteps of his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and as it were marking the way as it goeth, is called a flying ſtarre,<note place="margin">Flying ſtarres.</note> which is wont to appeare on a ſodaine: &amp; forthwith to vaniſh out of ſighte. Theſe exhalations as they come nigh to the Elemente of the fyre, or as they bee in the higheſt region of the ayre, which is next to the fire, bee as it were gunpowder nighe the match, or as brymſtone, or towgh put hard to the fyre: which, what expedition is in them, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume all along, it is euident by experience and common ſenſe. But theſe and al other impreſſions haue theire names of thoſe thinges which they moſt figurate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent. And as in the cleere night by ſuch matter of exhalation hot and drye, caryed
<pb facs="tcp:21445:19"/>vp to the higheſt region of the ayre, &amp; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kindled, ſuch burning flames do eftſoones appeare: ſo ſomewhile through the lyghte onely of the ſunne and ſtarres, the element onely appeareth coloured: And theſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours there ſeene are called <hi>Phantaſmata.</hi> For when the light ſtayed in any myſt ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go forth abroade,<note place="margin">Coloures ſeene in the ayre.</note> or proceede directly, but is fayne to harbour there onely, and to diſperſe it ſelfe into the ſides, and nexte partes thereof: then doth there ſhew forth colours of all ſortes: ſomewhiles white, ſomewhiles blacke: but moſt often a ſaffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colour, and next to that a ſanguine or blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy colour. For theſe colours for this cauſe cauſeth ſuch diuerſity, as white nighe and next vnto blacke or intermedled therwith: or as the flame ſeemeth oftentimes moſte ſtraunge through the ſtraungenes of the fumes thereof.<note place="margin">Gaſpings &amp; gapings in the aire</note> So the cauſe of gaſpynges gapynges and gulphes ſene oftentimes in the ayre riſeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame occaſion, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the fiery impreſſions or flames of fyre afore rehearſed do, and partly vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſion of the colours ſeene in the ayre, &amp; laſt ſpoken of. There is ſeene oftentymes alſo in the ſtarlight nights vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21445:19"/>(as ſomewhiles alſo vnder the ſunne and ſtarres) as it were a garland called of the <hi>Greekes Halon,</hi> in Latine <hi>Corona,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Halon or garland of the moone</note> whych is engendred through a refraction of the ſight in watery Cloudes, as diuerſe other apparitions are. But then ſpecially doth this garland ſhew about the Moone,<note place="margin">When it shevveth chiefely</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome vniforme cloude be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow which is on all ſides alike thicke or thin, is placed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly vnder the moone: ſo that her beames coueting to perſe and go through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, are there ſtil kept and retayned, or els are beaten backe by the force of the cloude: and ſo ſhee being letted therein to go any further directly, diſperſeth her beames a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe by the outmoſt ſides of the clowde: by which refractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there appeareth either right vnder her or vnder ſom ſtar, a great circle, greately illumined or lightned in a maner of a white garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d This ſighte alſo is ſomtimes vnder the ſun, &amp; the other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets: but moſt ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the Moone. For the ſun through his extream &amp; ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heat doth diſperſe &amp; ſunder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter of ſuch a cloud, &amp; doth not ſuffer it long to abide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone hath not ſuch force of diſperſing, &amp; therfore this appartio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the more eaſely vnder her.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:20"/>
               <p>So like wiſe ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>whyles wee ſhal ſee this halon or garlande about ſame ſtarres<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Halo, or garland of the ſtars.</note> but that is, when betweene thoſe ſtarres &amp; vs, ther is oppoſitely ſet ſome harren &amp; weake clowde, which is vnfytt to the generation of wynd or rayne. For if the clowdes were thicke and warry, it were not poſſible for vs (as daylye experience approueth it) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to haue ſighte of, or to beholde the ſtarres themſelues.</p>
               <p>Now as the poets alſo make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, ther is beſydes all theſe ſtraunge ſightes in the element which do appeare moſt in the night tyme, a peece or parte of the Skye, keeping away all a longe in colour mylke whyte, of the <hi>Gretians</hi> called <hi>Galaxia,</hi> and latined <hi>via lactea.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galaxia, or milky vvay.</note> Which part of the Skye (as they ſay) was once burnt by the vndiſcrete dealinge of <hi>Phaeton:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paethon.</note> who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to take vpon him an enter priſe which was very vnfit for him, and wherof he had no ſkill, that is, to rule hie father <hi>Phoebus</hi> charyots and horſes, by not keeping y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due order and way in dryuing of them, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and went vp ſo hie, nigh to the pallaice of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee had like to haue ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame on fyre with the Sun: but as it happened
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21445:20"/>(ſay they) that matter beyng eſpyed &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented in tyme, the moſt miſfortune y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then befel, was that this <hi>Phaeton</hi> burnt a peece of the Skye, which appeareth vnto vs, to he as it were a whole ſtreete. But what this ymaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the poet herein purpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that I paſſe and pretermit: onely the truth of this whyte coloured, milkye, and ſtreetlyke ſight of the ayre, is through this occaſion. There is vndonbtedly a certayne part or portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in which the light of many ſtarres ioyntly lodged, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by a refraction from them all do cauſe this whyte coloured appearaunce. <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſayth, that it proceedeth, or rather ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth forth by the meanes of ſome receyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of light, happening vpon an exhalation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is hot, and drye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d thinne withall. The cauſe why theſe nightly ſights, as alſo why the ſtarres themſelues are not ſeene of vs to ſkyne in the day tyme, is for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun letteth the ſame, by whoſe great light, the leſſer light of the ſtarres and other ayriall ſightes are obſcured and darkened, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the quicke cole be it neuer ſo litle, yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night tyme is ſeene of vs in his full ſhyne, but beyng greace, and ſhyping out withall
<pb facs="tcp:21445:21"/>&amp; thorowly quicke, &amp; aliue yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broade day light beyng put in an open place, doth rather ſeme dead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliue, &amp; doth neither geue light norſhine vnto vs, &amp; al is becauſe it lyeth as it were &amp; yeeldeth it ſelfe to the Sunsmore noble light, and moſt gloryous ſhyne: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doth the ſtarres and al other impreſſions in the ayer, abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; kepe them ſelues from our ſight, all the tyme that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun is here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant among vs in her ſuch ſuperexcelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t glory. But let vs returne to the effect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mone in the other creatures here below: and firſt let vs begin to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider a little vnto what diſpoſition ſhee frameth thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be ſubiected &amp; borne vnder her conſtellatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">The Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts hovv diſpoſed.</note> Touching the inclination of all ſuch parties which bee borne vnder <hi>Luna,</hi> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, they be naturally mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table &amp; mouable, without fidelity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, geuen to prouoke much anger and &amp; diſcord betwene friends: they be alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry enuyous, agreeued with the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and good fortune of others: they bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ful of hatred, and in their conuerſation and manner of lyfe they be verye childiſh. The colbure of theſe commonlye is a pale or whyte colour, althoughe now and then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21445:21"/>they haue therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al a little red intermedled Their face is rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, their ſtature indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their eies black, &amp; their browes wrinkled. And as in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefeſt creature, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone hath this ſcope or ſway: ſo likewyſe it hath as greate force in the bodyes of bruite Beaſtes, and in them woorketh at her owne wil ſuch ſtraunge effectes as bee no leſſe to be meruayled at. The profe wherof the <hi>Panther</hi> geueth forth, whoſe body is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather ordered by the Moones dyrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">Panther</note> for (as <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſayth) he caryeth, or weareth the very badge or patterne of the moone vppon his ſhoulder: which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth and vaniſheth euerye moone accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as the Moone her ſelfe doth eyther encreaſe or decreaſe.</p>
               <p>The lyke argument is of <hi>Cynocephalus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cynoce. phalus.</note> (whom ſome make one of the kyndes of Apes) other ſome Engliſh ye the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Of this <hi>Horus APOLLO</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that hee piſſeth twelue tymes in the Day, and twelue tymes urthe night. And that in the wane of the Moone (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge all the tyme that ſhee is darkened) hee coutinually lamenteth neuer eatynge
<pb facs="tcp:21445:22"/>any thing at all: Whereby he playnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth what parte and rule the Moone hath in him, ouer his whole hodye: vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Moone is alſo the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable <hi>Cameleon,</hi> which turneth her ſelfe into what colour ſhee lyſteth:<note place="margin">Cameleo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Vnder her are alſo the Badger, the Otter, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer kindes which liue and doe engender monſtruouſly.<note place="margin">Cat.</note> The Catte alſo whoſe eyes do wexe either greater or leſſe at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and chaunge of the Moone, doth manifeſtly declare what right the Moone hath in the ſame. Likewiſe waſpes which ariſe of the deade carcaſes of horſes: and Bees which do breede of the deade bodies of beaſtes or Kyne:<note place="margin">Betell.</note> Betels which come of the fleſh of Aſſes, do al in their being and continuance depend vpon the Moone: And eſpecially that kinde of Betſe which hath as it were two Hornes, and which is alſo made and proportioned in the eucke like a bull: whoſe propertie is ſuch that at the be ginng of euery new moone in the ſommer and ſprynge time chiefly, ſhee ſeeketh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and getteth certayne ſhels wherin ſhe beſtoweth ſome of her ſeede, which done, ſhe hydeth and burieth the ſame in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21445:22"/>and ſo leaueth the ſame there <hi>28.</hi> dayes (in which time the Moone goeth throughe the whole zodiacke, &amp; finiſheth her ful courſe) and the <hi>29.</hi> day which is the pryme of the Moone againe, ſhee retourneth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where thoſe ſhels were buried, and taketh them forth: and carieth them to the water, where they afterwardes take and receyue life, &amp; come to the perfection of their kind. The Harte alſo and the Swine, the Dog and the Goate, bee all ſeruiable vnto the Moone. Amongeſt fowles ſubiected to the Moone, are the Crane, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſe, the Duck,<note place="margin">Cormorat</note> the Cormorant, whoſe property is to diue vnder the water to take fiſh, and by ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing perceiuing Signes of Tempeſtes to come, ſhe ſodainly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a gret noiſe &amp; cry get<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth her away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water, &amp; ſeketh where to hide her. Belonging alſo to the Moone amongſt fiſhes are, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Creuis or Crabſiſh: The fyſh <hi>Torpedo</hi> or the <hi>Torpede</hi> which maketh the takers hands num or dead for a time: Likewiſe Oyſters,<note place="margin">Torpede</note> and all ſhaled fyſh: Moreouer the fiſhe <hi>Echeneis</hi> whych hath prickels in ſtead of ſins and feete, and neither ſwimmeth nor goeth, but rubleth. Likewyſe <hi>Aelurus</hi> whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yen alter after
<pb facs="tcp:21445:23"/>the alteration of the Moone amongeſt Plantes. And fyrſt of Trees, in her holde is the Palme tree, which at euery chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſhooteth forth a new ſlippe: lykewyſe roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marye, the Oliue tree, and ſuch lyke.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a certayne Plant, or Herbe called of the Greekes <hi>Selenotropion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Selenotro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pion.</note> that turneth rounde with the Moone, as <hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otropion,</hi> lykewyſe turneth rounde with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne. <hi>Chinoſtares</hi> an Herbe alſo, doth not onelye varye in her taſt, goodnes, and virtue, according to the diſpoſitione of the Moone, but getteth &amp; loſeth more or leſſe, of her ſubſtance and number of leaues, as the moone getteth, or looſeth of her lighte. Proper to her alſo amongeſt Pretious ſtones or gemmes, is the Chriſtal, the ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Marcaſite, and all thoſe whoſe colour is white or greene. Moreouer the precious <hi>Selenite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Selenite.</note> which for like qualities with the Mooue, hath with her almoſt one, and the ſelfe ſame name: whoſe colour is much like hony, and which leſſeneth and waxeth byg, accordinge to the pryme, and wane of the Moone. Hers is alſo the Magaryte, and all other perles, which engender by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21445:23"/>heauenly dewe, within the encloſure of certayne ſhelfiſhes. In this ſtate alſo is the Berill: and amongeſt metalles, onely Syluer: and amongeſt taſtes and ſauours that which is ſalteſt or moſt fulſome: amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the ſuperfluities, or excrements of the body, ſweate, fleume,<note place="margin">Countries ſubiect to Luna.</note> and groſnes or fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Amongeſt the Elementes the water with all fountaynes, floods and ſuch like. prouinces alſo and kyngdomes vnder her dominion and rule are <hi>Bythinia, Phrigia, Colchos, Numidia, Aphrick,</hi> and all <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Mercury" type="part">
               <head>OF MERCVRY. the ſecond Planet</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext aboue <hi>Luna</hi> or the Moone is <hi>Mercury,</hi> which alwaies go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the ſun, and is neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the ſun more then <hi>30.</hi> degrees. This planet is accompted the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, workeman, or procurer of eloquence and good wit: &amp; cauſeth the ſenſes of thoſe bodies which are ſubiected to him to bee dextere and pregnaunt. So that thoſe whych bee borne under hys conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:21445:24"/>as hee gouerneth alone: are lightly &amp; for the moſt part rethoricall, well ſpoken, and very wiſe,<note place="margin">Mercury his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> applying their wiſedom to good and honeſt endes. But as he is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>Saturne</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> hee procureth an abuſe of the ſame good and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble giftes, and conuerteth them to beſtow both their eloquence and wits to the hurt and harme of others: as alſo to ſtirre vp ſtryfes, diſcorde, quareling, tumultes, ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, hereſies, and ſuch like. Of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe natured men, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world (alas) in theſe dayes is to full of, almoſt euery where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding: which as they are endued with right excellent giftes both of eloquence, &amp; wiſedome, do nothing els therewith (but as the Poet ſaith well) make thinges that be ſtraight crooked: ſuch as be perfite, and whole, crackte, and broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: darkening that which is manifeſt, and thruſting truth out of place: wexe &amp; becom ſhameles ſcholema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of errors. Contrariwiſe if this <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> be ioined w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> he cauſeth in the <hi>Mercuriſts</hi> a clean co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary effect. As who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to apply &amp; refer the aforeſated precious gifts to the inquiſition and finding forth of truth, &amp; to the defence of the ſame: as alſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21445:24"/>to contend in nothing ſo much as in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Religion and vertue. The Poets faygne that this <hi>Mercury</hi> nowe a Planet in heauen, was ſometimes Neauy to <hi>Atlas,</hi> who (as they ſay) vnderproppeth heauen: and ſomtimes he is named of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Hermes,</hi> that is an Interpretour, which both geueth plenty of words, as alſo liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſpeach: whereby we vtter the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and conceipt of our mindes. Againe he is called <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> for that hee firſt found out the knowledge or vſe of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Sciences. Marchaunts vſe to haue this Planet in high price, of whom many haue ſuppoſed them ſelues to haue obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a thorough knowledge and great dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity in accoumpting and numbring: vpon him therefore they were wonte to call in their affayres and buſineſſe of Marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize. And as <hi>Mercury</hi> when hee was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paynted or drawen forth in any kynde of ſorte, hee was chiefly paynted oute wyth Wynges, and with a Cocke ſet hard by him, ſignifying thereby both his celerity and ſwyftnes in all his buſines, as alſo his Uigilancy and watchfulneſſe: So many painefull Marchants in their daungerous
<pb facs="tcp:21445:25"/>&amp; painefull paſſages doe continew ſtill this property and practiſe. <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſayth that his houſe or manſton is in <hi>Gemini,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go:</hi> and his exaltation or aſcendent is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>15.</hi> of <hi>Virgo.</hi> The qualities which he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth vnto are dyuerſe, accordinge to the firſte and principall qualities of the other Planets, with whom he is in coniunction. The colors which he worketh are browne, and a darke or duſky colour. He alſo fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all ſharpe ſauoures.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that be borne vnder <hi>Mercury</hi> are Luſty, and lyking, and valiant of body: but of ſlippery and chaungeable mindes.<note place="margin">Mercury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts.</note> The colour of their Face is after a browne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene white and blacke: their Face is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſomewhat long: they are alſo of a highe and broade foreheade: their eyes comely, and rowling: their Noſe flat: their Beard, thinne, and their Fyngers long.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Mercury</hi> (for ſeeming to ſtriue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Venus</hi> his next neyghbour in place, aboue him, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate in certaine qualities of righte belonging vnto her) is imagined of the Poets to haue forced and rauyſhed her. The Hebrewes calleth him <hi>MACID:</hi> The Greekes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He runneth ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21445:25"/>zodiack in <hi>336.</hi> dayes. Subiected to <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cury</hi> are all thoſe kindes of Beaſts which be of ſharp ſenſe, &amp; which be witty, ſtrong, and luſty: and which be alſo of a chaunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able nature and of ſwifte pace, and which couet to be conuerſant among men: as the Ape, the Foxe, the Scurrell, the Weaſel, the ſheepe, the Cony, &amp; the Hart: likewiſe all ſuch as be of a confuſed nature &amp; kinde: Among Byrdes and Foweles of the ayre. He hath in his Domynion all ſuch as bee moſt ſubtile and wily, as alſo thoſe that be of ſhyrll voyce and of pleaſaunt note, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Larke, the Lynnet, the Birde <hi>Ficedula</hi> which lyueth &amp; feedeth cheifly vpon Figs and grapes: alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Blackmacke, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys or Thruſt, the Parret, the Popiniay, and the Bird <hi>Ibis:</hi> among fiſhes he chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the fiſhe called <hi>Trochus</hi> which is of one onely kinde,<note place="margin">Troch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and conceyueth and enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of it ſelfe alone, through which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is called <hi>Maſculofaeminina,</hi> that is, both Male, and Female: likewiſe the wyly and crafty <hi>Polypus</hi> which is ſo crafty that it is ſeldome taken.</p>
               <p>Amonge Planets, and chiefly amonge Trees, the Haſell, &amp; Filburd tree be his:
<pb facs="tcp:21445:26"/>And among hearbes, <hi>Cinkfoyl</hi> or fiue lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hearve: as alſo the hearbe <hi>Mercury, Fumitory, Pimpernell, Maioram, Parce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and all ſuch hearbes as beare a ſmall &amp; fine leaſe, and which be alſo delectably and diuerſly colored. Among Precious ſtones his is the Emeralde, the Smaragde, the Achate, the Porphyrite, the Topaze, and al thoſe which be of a chaungable colour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Mettalls is his principally Siluer, &amp; Tinne. Among Humors the thickeſt and moſt mixt. Laſtly among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Elements hee claymeth the water in dyuerſe poyntes of ſeruice to be his owne proper. This <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> with <hi>Gemini</hi> (one of the <hi>Sygnes</hi> or houſen wherein he is placed) doth holde &amp; poſſeſſe <hi>Hircania,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Countries ſubiect to Mercury.</note> &amp; <hi>Armenia,</hi> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions and Prouinces of <hi>Marmaricke,</hi> and <hi>Cyrenaica,</hi> as alſo the lowermoſt <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And with <hi>Virgo</hi> (his other <hi>Sygne</hi>) he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth theſe Kingdomes and Countreyes, <hi>Aſſyria, Babylon, Meſopotamia, Achaia, Greec, Creet,</hi> or <hi>Candy,</hi> and <hi>Elam,</hi> of whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are called <hi>Elamytes.</hi> In euery attempt or buſines of waight he both haſteneth &amp; ſetteth forward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes thereof: as alſo helpeth forth to a good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21445:26"/>or ſucceſſe of the ſame. <hi>Volateranus</hi> ſayth, that he was begotten of <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae. lib. 3</note> and <hi>Maia,</hi> whoſe Nephewe <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth was <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> which hath writte ſo Profoundly, and deepely of Philoſophy. Which <hi>Mercury</hi> as he is the God of Marchaunts and Rethoritians: ſo is he alſo of Theeues and Iuglers, which worke vpon deceipt &amp; ſleights: he is alſo a Meſſenger of the heauenly powres aboue: his Sonnes were <hi>Eudorus,</hi> whom he had by <hi>Polymia</hi> as <hi>Homer</hi> witneſſeth: &amp; <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilus,</hi> which draue the Horſſiter, or Coche of <hi>Oenomaus</hi> the King: <hi>Hermaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> whych was both Man and Woman: <hi>Daphnis</hi> the Sheephearde,<note place="margin">Aethalis.</note> and <hi>Aethalis</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cryar, or Beadell, which when hee was deade coulde reuiue himſelfe agayne as they ſay:<note place="margin">Argon.</note> which is alſo Iuſtified of <hi>Apollonius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Venus" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:27"/>
               <head>Of VENVS the thirde Planet.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>ENVS is a faeminin Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> very placable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt: a pacifier of <hi>Mars</hi> in his great fury, and malice, &amp; fiery feruency, quieting him with friendly and amiable Aſpect, in ſuch wiſe, as a beautifull and louinge Woman doth appeaſe and ſtill the rage, and anger of her Huſband being incenſed. Shee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accompanieth the Sunne: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhee goeth before him, and ſheweth in our <hi>Horizon</hi> before the Sun ſhe is called <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi> the bright morning light or day ſtar:<note place="margin">Venus hir names.</note> but when ſhe followeth the Sunne, and is ſeene of vs after the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſet ſhe is called <hi>Heſperus</hi> the ſtar of the night: and ſo how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer ſhe doth appeare ſhee is the Sunnes Meſſenger, either that hee is already comming, or that hee is already gone. Whereof this verſe of <hi>Virgil</hi> well witneſſeth, whereas hee ſayth:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Ite domum ſaturae venit Heſperus, Ite capellae.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21445:27"/>
                  <p>Yee Goates I ſay with Bellies full that long haue harbored here,</p>
                  <p>Goe get yee home for Heſper now beginneth to appere.</p>
               </q>
               <p>THis <hi>VENVS</hi> is of a bright ſhyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing colour, being therein of al other ſtarres moſt acceptable &amp; pleaſaunt to the eyeſight: and ſhee is called <hi>Venus</hi> for <hi>venuſtie</hi> and beautifull countenaunce: or (as ſome ymagine) for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through thoſe qualities and contemperature, which ſhee naturally planteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body (that is to ſay) heate and moyſture, ſhee cauſeth burninge Loue, and prouoketh to tickling Luſt.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> call her <hi>NEGAH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOTH:</hi> The <hi>Greekes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifieth the Fat or Fome of fleſhe: for that (as the Poets imagine) ſhe breedeth the Fatneſſe of fleſhe and Maſſyneſſe, or groſeneſſe of bloude. And they haue it alſo in opinion that this <hi>Venus</hi> was bred firſt and came of the froth or bloude that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Priuities of <hi>Coelus</hi> whom <hi>Saturne</hi> gelt, and cut of, and threwe them into the ſea.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:28"/>
               <p>They alſo maryed her to <hi>Vulcane</hi> and made her his Wyfe, ſignifying thereby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſure &amp; delighte is as it were wrought and kindled by fire and heare. <hi>Martianus</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Her coler.</note> that her colour glittereth after the maner of ſiluer: and that ſhe onely ſheweth her ſelfe vnto vs in the Winter tyme, for in the Summer ſhe is conuerſaunt &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pole <hi>Antarticke.</hi> Her Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or place of abode is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Sygnes Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Libra,</hi> her Exaltation or Aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is in the <hi>26.</hi> of <hi>Piſces.</hi> Thoſe that be borne vnder <hi>Venus</hi> are amiable,<note place="margin">Borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Venus hovve af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</note> and of merry &amp; ſinylinge Looke or countenaunce, greate laughters, very wanton, &amp; ſuch as do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delight in Muſicke: they haue alſo a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perfect ſmell and taſte, and their voyce is very ſweete or defectable. They are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo geuen much to the compoſing and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſweete Oyntments and Odoures: Their bodies are wel ſet, and be of proper features: their Faces &amp; vyſages are rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: their hayre yealow, their Eyes glittering and rowling. In conditions they be gentle. curteous, fayre ſpoken, milde, and modeſt, meete for all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies: whereupon for ſuch her deſeruing towards Mankinde, they of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21445:28"/>olde time pictured <hi>Venus</hi> after theſe ſorts following. Firſt they drewe her out in the ſimilitude or lykeneſſe of a Woman, vpon whoſe heade ſtoode a Byrd, which purpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Loue his force: and her Feete were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Aegles</hi> feete, ſignifying the ſwyftnes of the ſame: and this woman held in her hand an Arrowe or Darte, noting forth the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible ſtroke or perſifenes thereof. Another Image of her they were wont to engraue in the Precious ſtone Lazulus, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented a fayre and beautifull mayde all vncouered and naked, whoſe hayre hunge downe a long all ouer her body, who alſo had a lookinge Glaſſe in her hande, and a Chayne tyed or faſtened to her Necke, by whom ſtoode a fayre, younge ſtripling and beautifull, who with his left hand held her faſt by the ſayd chayne, and with his right hand held her by the hayre: herein perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture noting forth the circumſtaunce of Suiters and Wooers, and ſo forth. Shee had alſo another manner of Image other wheres: for there were that drew her forth in the habite of an Handmayden or Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, whoſe hayre lay ſcattering aboute her necke, and whoſe garment hung downe to
<pb facs="tcp:21445:29"/>her ſhooe, which were all white and milky coloured: who helde in her right hande a Lawrell braunch, &amp; ſometimes an Apple, or els a Poſie of ſweete and freſh flowers, in her lefthand ſhe held a Combe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is ſignified that al ſuch as are borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her, are naturally geuen to bee louers of ciuilueſſe and cleanlineſſe, and to delight much in pleaſant ſmells &amp; ſmeete Odours. Vnder her gouernment or rule are al ſuch bruite beaſtes which are delicate &amp; leache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, &amp; which are geuen to exceſſe of luſt: as the Cony, the leſſer kinde of Dogs, the Goate &amp; Goatebucke, the bull and al other which are of like ſet and diſpoſition. Ouer birds of fowles ſhe hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Swan, the Wagtayle, the Swallowe, the Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the Partrich, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bergander, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crow, all kindes of Doues, likewiſe the ſhe Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, which is of ſuch immoderate luſt that being trod xiii. times in a day,<note place="margin">Eagle.</note> yet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> call of her Mate is ready to take it agayne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge fiſhes <hi>Venus</hi> ruleth ouer the gylt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head or Goldeney, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Merling, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Whiting, &amp; the fiſhe <hi>Cancharus</hi> which is Ielous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer her Mate,<note place="margin">Cancha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; ſtriueth often for him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Plants or Hearbs ſubiect to her is the Violet, the Malow, the hearbe <hi>Venus</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21445:29"/>hayre or goldy lockes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lylly, likewiſe the hearbe <hi>Lada</hi> or <hi>Ledum</hi> whoſe Gum is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ladanum</hi> &amp; moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly <hi>Labdanum</hi> and is vſed in Pomanders: furthermore al &amp; euery odoriferous thing as is <hi>Ambra,</hi> which is engliſhed <hi>Ambergriſe:</hi> it is found on the ſea ſhore by a countrey called <hi>Zingi</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, &amp; is for his gray colour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called of the Apothecaries <hi>Ambergriſia,</hi> hereof are made very preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; Cordiall medicines: hetherto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth alſo the ſweete ſmelling Time, &amp; the ſpice <hi>Saunders:</hi> furdermore all ſuch fruits as are pleaſant, &amp; of good taſte, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apple the Hare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fig, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> currant, the date, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granet, &amp;c. Amonge Precious ſtones ſhee chalengeth the Beril, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chruſolyte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyr, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iaſper, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cornellys, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pretious <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites</hi> the ſtone Lazulus, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corall &amp; al ſuch as be beautifull, &amp; of mylke white or graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy greene colour: among Mettalls ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth a right in Copper &amp; braſſe, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſiluer: and among ſauours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is ſweeteſt, delicious, &amp; vuctuous is hers: &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong humors a part of bloude, as alſo the whole courſe of naturall ſeede is at her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicion: among the Elements ſhe holdeth a porcion in the ayre and alſo in the water.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:30"/>
               <p>Ouer Prouinces, and Kingdomes. Firſt ſhee rayghneth (as ſhee is coupled) with <hi>Taurus,</hi> ouer <hi>Cyprus, Parthia, Mede,</hi> and <hi>Perſis,</hi> the <hi>Cyclades</hi> or the fifty Iles in the Sea called <hi>Aegeum:</hi> And ſecondly as ſhe is ioyned with <hi>Libra,</hi> ſhe ruleth ouer <hi>Bactri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> wherein were ſometimes very many cities: likewiſe ouer the People <hi>Caſpij</hi> a people in <hi>Tartaria</hi> dwelling next unto the ſea <hi>Caſpium:</hi> likewiſe ouer <hi>Serica, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bais, Oaſis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Troglodytis, Agrippa</hi> ſaith that <hi>Venus,</hi> in all kindes of Creatures purchaſeth and procureth Loue betwixte Mate &amp; Mate: and that ſhe laboureth chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the multiplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and increaſe of ſeede, to the continuance, and preſeruation of the whole kinde, coueting alwayes as nigh as ſhe can, and thereto with mighte &amp; mayne labouringe, to abandon and remooue Barraynneſſe out of the way, which coueteth to cut of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Race &amp; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of all. This <hi>Venus</hi> paſſeth through the <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacke</hi> in <hi>348.</hi> dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Sun" type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21445:30"/>
               <head>Of SOL, or the Sunne, the fourth Planet.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>OL, or the Sunne</hi> is the fourth in place and preheminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge theſe ſeuen, &amp; is among them as it were a Ringe in the midſt of his Throne, Trayne, and Garde. For vnder him he hath <hi>Luna</hi> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, <hi>Mercurius,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> of whom we haue already ſpoken: and aboue him in poſition and place he hath as many, that is toweete <hi>Mars, Iupiter,</hi> &amp; <hi>Saturne.</hi> And as it ſhould ſeeme it was not without great cauſe and conſideration that the Mighty <hi>IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH,</hi> the Maker of Heauen and Earth placed the Sunne in ſuch a proportioned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality among them all:<note place="margin">Sun plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the middeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the 7. Planets Wherfore</note> notwithſtanding through his excellency he deſerueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt roome of prerogatiue and dignity. For if the Sunne which is the moſt vniuerſall cauſe, and the very beginning &amp; fountayne of light and influence, &amp; alſo of vitall heat,
<pb facs="tcp:21445:31"/>to his intemperate heate of heart, maketh them in ſtomacke to be rather wylde &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage, rather then properly Puiſſant: and more venturouſe raſhe, and bolde, then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and Polliticke. For it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exceſſe of heate, which burning and boyling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a man that bringeth boldneſſe and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when as the bloude about the heart is immoderately and to much ſet on fire.</p>
               <p>There is nothing almoſt gloriouſly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the ſacred Scriptures, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory thereof is likened &amp; reſembled to the Sun:<note place="margin">Cap. 17. Apoc. 1.</note> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Tranſfiguration of <hi>Chriſte,</hi> in which <hi>Mathew</hi> ſayth, his Face did ſhyne as the Sunne.<note place="margin">Sun chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note> So <hi>Ihon</hi> in his Reuelation ſayth that he ſawe the Face of the Sonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhyning as the Sunne in his greateſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. (But to ende with theſe:) This <hi>Sol</hi> was fabled of the Poets to haue bene <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and <hi>Latonaes</hi> Sonne, who for that he is as it were euery day newly borne, is paynted out in likenes of a younge childe, noting forth thereby that hee is euery day newly ryſinge. His property is neuer to ſhewe vs all the day longe, one and the ſelf ſame looke: for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he riſeth he ſheweth red, at noone hee ſheweth more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21445:31"/>white, at his going downe or ſett, he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſheweth wan and pale, but often he appeareth alſo red. Wheruppon for ſuch diuerſity the Poets imagine that hee hath foure horſes, which do daylye at theyr ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted tymes and ſeaſons, one after an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, helpe to draw the Sunne about the zodiacke. And the fyrſt of theſe they name <hi>Pyrois,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Eous,</hi> the third <hi>Aetho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and the fourth <hi>Phlegon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sunne, if ſo be he ſhew at his ryſing and ſeeme clowdye or darke, and looketh wan, he cauſeth vpon this more then won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted warmth: hee foreſheweth rayne, if he looketh red: hee betokeneth tempeſtes to be at hand, if hee ſhyneth forth cleere: or caſteth his beames towardes the South, hee prognoſticateth more moderate &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable weather.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martianus</hi> ſayth, that the Sunne as he is in the midedeſt of the zodiacke, beateth backe from him twelue ſeueral lightes, or more broad Sunbeams: which reflectate themſelues and remayne vpon the twelue ſignes. The ſame Author alſo affyrmeth that there is nothing ſo occult or deeply co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned within the entrayls and body of the
<pb facs="tcp:21445:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21445:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21445:33"/>earth but that it is manifeſtly ſeene of ye. It is ſayde that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Indians,</hi> or men of <hi>Inde</hi> had <hi>Sol</hi> or the Sun to a banquet, and the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quetting place was in the Ocean Sea: Wherupon now they ſay, that before any fore rayne, or ſhowers diſcending, we feele a terrayne heat going before. His houſe or manſion is onely in <hi>Leo:</hi> his exaltation or aſcendent in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>19</hi> of <hi>Aries Agrippa</hi> ſayth, that the Sun is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, the ſame that the hart is in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith, in his <hi>2</hi> booke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord and prince of tyme: and as <hi>Prolome</hi> ſayth, the verye ſpirite or wel of lyfe in all liuing thinges. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes call him <hi>IPHNATH,</hi> the Greeks <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. To vtter forth his exceeding bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, they vſed in olde tyme to draw him forth after diuers likeneſſes: as ſomwhiles after the attyre &amp; ryal robes of a king, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a crowne of gold on his head, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his chayre of ſtate, hauinge vnder his footea round globe or bowle meaning to vtter forth thee by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Sol</hi> made many ſuch partyes as were vnder hym, honorable, tryumphant and inuincible. <hi>Orpheus</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Sun, the glory and face of heauen, and the ſufferaygne ey ſight or right eye of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21445:33"/>the world. It fortuneth oftentymes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys Sun notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandinge his great &amp; wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful light is obſcured, darkned,<note place="margin">Eclips of the Sun.</note> &amp; as it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reued therof, which is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eclipſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun, Which ſo often as he is in coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Moone, eſpecially if ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be Diameter wyſe vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eclipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal lyne, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head or tayle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dragon, by ſome interpoſition of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone betweene the Sun &amp; our eyſight:<note place="margin">Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eclipſe of the Sun</note> &amp; this neuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth that the Sun is whollye eclipſed, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ther is ſuch Diameterlyke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Moone &amp; Sun vnder the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptical line in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head or tayl of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they both meete together, eyther in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head or tayle, ſo diametewiſe oppoſite, as that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame diameter paſſeth by the center of them both.<note place="margin">A particu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> eclipſe of the Sun.</note> But there may be a particular eclipſe of the Sun, then, when as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone is in Coniunetion almoſt vnder the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall lyne verye nigh within the heade or tayle of the Dragon, and within the bonds &amp; borders of the general eclipſe, of whiche wee haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue. Betweene the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral &amp; particular eclipſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun ther is this differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the firſt al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is directly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head or tayl of
<pb facs="tcp:21445:34"/>the Dragon all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of the Sun, is ſhadowed &amp; darkened, wherby ther hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth ſuch an eclipſe, as that a man can ſee nothing of the globe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne. But in the particular eclipſe, when the coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is onely nigh to one of the foreſayde poyntes, then is not the whole body of the Sun darkened, but onelye ſome part: and ther, where it happeneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced betwixt the Sunne and our eyeſight. And this kynd of Eclipſe is oftentymes ſo ſmal, as that it is ſcant perceyued, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be (as it were) ſome ſpotte in the bodye of the Sunne. it is therefore mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that there can he no Eclipſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun but in the tyme of ſuch Coniunction, as is aboue ſayde: as likewyſe in the new of the Moone: as there cannot neyther bee any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Moone, but in the time of Op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſition and ful Moone: becauſe that other wyſe the Moone can not bee obiected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Sun and our eyeſight.</p>
               <p>Now a litle to ſpeak of both their differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces (which is much) I recke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yt to be right neceſſary.<note place="margin">Sun and Moones eclipſe. hovv they differ.</note> Fyrſt they differ in this, that the Eclipſe of the Sunne requireth Coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſame poynt, or very nigh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21445:34"/>poynt: but the Eclipſe of the Mone requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Oppoſition in oppoſite poyntes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the Sun muſt be eclipſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the new Moone: but the Moone in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the ful Moone. In the firſt the Moone is interplaced betweene the Sun, and the Earth: In this laſt the earth is obieceed betweene the Sun and Moone. In the firſt the ſhadow of the Moone doth darken the earth: in the ſecond the ſhadow of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth doth obfuſcate the bodye of the Moone. In the firſt there is onely a ſubſtraction of the light from our eyeſight. In the laſt there is a depriuation of reall light. There are beſydes theſe more eſpeciall differences, moſt worthy to be noted: whereof the fyrſt is this, that the eclipſe of the Moone (whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be to tall, or in part) is euer vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall in all places of the Earth: but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Sunne is neuer ſo generall, which is thus proued: becauſe that the Sun is not at any tyme euery where eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but whyles here we lacke therby the Sunnes light for a tyme, euen in the ſelfe ſame inſtant, others a far of enioy the light of the ſame: yea and ſometymes thoſe, that he not ſo farre of, and the reaſon is, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21445:35"/>the Sunne doth but onely ſuffer ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umbration for a tyme, throughe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of the Mone, which cannot but in a part of the Sun, hinder hys light, and not totally nor whollye. Agayne there is this other difference, as that the Sun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to be Eclipſed on the Weſt, part of his body, becauſe that the Moones pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per motion is from the Eaſt. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moon is eclipſed chiefly on the eaſt ſyde of her bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye. But now a litle let vs tary to reporte what kynd of Ecliſpe happened in the time of the paſſion and ſufferyng of our ſauiour Chriſt, which befell at noone dayes, and continued all the whole tyme that Chriſt hanged vpon the croſſe: which was ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ſtraunge, that beſydes the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and witnes that the Euangeliſtes geue forth thereof,<note place="margin">Whatkind of eclipſe vvas at Chriſtes death.</note> it is alſo regiſtred and remembred in the hyſtoryes of <hi>Pagans</hi> and Heathen men. Beſydes that <hi>Dioniſius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riopagita</hi> an eye witnes therof: &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the vniuerſity of <hi>Heliopolis</hi> in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, in his epiſtle to <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> maketh mention, that hee together with <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> a noble Philoſoper did both ſe and behold the ſame: and alſo with exceedinge
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21445:35"/>much aſtoniſhment, and admiration therof conſidered of the ſame moſt deeplye and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently. It is manifeſt that this Eclipſe, was not natural, but rather ſupernatural. For the naturall Eclipſe muſt bee as wee ſayd before, onely in the tyme of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the Sun and Moone, and in the new of the Moone: but when Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it was full moone, and the ſame oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Sun as both witneſſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſame <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> which ſaith he ſaw the ſame as alſo <hi>Apollophane.</hi> Beſydes holye wrytte doth very cleerelye ſet downe the tyme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Chryſt agaynſt the feaſt of Eaſter after he had taken the Paſſouer with his Diſciples incontinently almoſt to haue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; ſuffred vppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. And this feaſt of Eaſter muſt alwayes of neceſſity by the preſcript of Moſes lawe bee obſerued, and kept in the ful Moone, &amp; ſo did the Iewes obſerue the ſame moſt diligentlye: ſo that this Eclipſe, happeninge then at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and tyme, could not be as other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſes of the Sunne bee natural, through the vnfitnes and incommodiouſnes of that tyme: for there is no tyme ſo vnpoſſyble to worke ſuch an effecte, as in the tyme of
<pb facs="tcp:21445:36"/>Oppoſition: for then the Sun and Moone which require coniunction in that behalf, are neuer more remote, or farder diſtance from coniunncion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that preſent time. In fyue propertyes therefore I fynde this miraculous eclipſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo happened at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſauiour Chriſt, to differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other eclipſes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be only natural. The firſte which wee laſte touched was in the time therof, which hapned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the full of the Mone, a tyme moſt vnfit to the generation of my natural Eclipſe. The ſecond appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the corſe of the Moone, which, wher as naturally of her owne proper motion, ſhe goeth from the Eaſt to the Weſt. In this ſtraunge eclipſe then ſeene, <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> ſayth, he ſaw her with a moſt ſwift pace returne very ſtranngely from the Eaſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the South, vntil ſhee ſtood directlye vnder the Sun, wheras ſhee ſtayed by the ſpace of whole three howers, and by that meanes cauſed darkenes ouer al the whole face of the earth. And after the third hour about which time our ſauiour Chriſt was deade, ſhee returned agayne to her owne place in the Eaſt, with a moſt ſwift courſe appearing there agayne as it had bene in a tryce. And ſo in the ſixte and nynth hower,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21445:36"/>ſhee was ſeene vnder the Sun: but in the euening, and at the Sunnes going down ſhe appeared new agayn in the Eaſt, right oppoſite to the Sunne. The thyrd poynte wherin this miracle differeth from other vſuall Eclipſes, was vpon the ſtrange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynning of the ſame: for this began on the Eaſt ſyde of the Sunn, wheras all other wonted eclipſes of the Sun vſe to begin to be eclipſed after their naturall order, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weſt part of the Sun. The fourth poynt of difference was herein, which was verye ſtraunge: For that part of the Sun which was firſt darkened &amp; obſcured of his light by the interpoſition of the moone, did laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew forth reſtitucion of his light which is otherwyſe in other Eclipſes: which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of the Sunne that ſeemeth fyrſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured dother agayne fyrſt and formoſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the ſame to be reſtored. And then the Moone paſſed not aſyde from the Sun as ſhe is wont in his naturall eclipſe, but ſtode right vnder him for the ſpace of thre whole howers: and ſo ſhee not after that, goyng on beyond the Sun, but returning to the Eaſt her place from whence ſhe fyrſt came, gaue great occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of admiration &amp; wonder. The fyrſt eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et all difference ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:21445:37"/>alſo was vpon the perduratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: taryance and ſtaye of the ſame ſtrange eclipſe. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunnes ordinarye Eclipſes cannot conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, as which are very ſpedely perfour med, by reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body of the Sun doth infinitely exceede in bignes &amp; quantity the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone: as alſo for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of the Moone is very ſwift. For which two cauſes, fyrſt becauſe the Moone is ſo little in reſpect of the other, &amp; therefore not able any tyme to obſcure &amp; hyde away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Suns light, neither totally nor in part from our aſpect. And agayne for the ſwiftnes &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locity of the Moones courſe, ſhee cannot hyde away the Sun beyng ſo huge and big any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tyme: but he muſt needes ſhyne out on one ſyde or other. Beſydes, this wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eclipſe procured of God to ſhew forth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt haynous fact of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, in abuſyng his Son ſo, as it greatly grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars &amp; Sun aboue not onely amaſed many men, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many ſtroke their breaſtes and returned from <hi>Caluary</hi> where he was crucifyed:<note place="margin">Math. 27</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing and ſaying, verely this was the ſon of God: as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Centurion</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but alſo ther was a general &amp; great darknes ouer al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 2 hower vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21445:37"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 9. for els it could not be true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Dyoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>Heliopolis</hi> in Aegipt gaue forth to be true vndoutedly in one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> either y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maker of al thinges then fuffered, or elſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> domes day &amp; the end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world was then come: if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this eclipſe had bene onely in <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> which is ſo far of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegipt. Beſides this a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time after by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſight ſtroke into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hartes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Athens ſuperſtitious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Paul</hi> being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them awhyle, and vewinge their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yngs narrowly, chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth to eſpye there an Aulter wherin was writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>vnto the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen God</hi> erected as is ſayd preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this eclipſe caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> which is very far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Iudea,</hi> proueth it to be more vniuerſal: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſcant it to narrowly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeme to bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it onely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the borders of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place, where y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> villanous fact was committed. For ſhal we thinke that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miraculous going backe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun, which happened in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayss of <hi>Ezechias</hi> kynge of <hi>Iuda,</hi> witneſſing his recouery of helth was alone the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perceyued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitants ther, &amp; not aſwel alſo among nations furder of: for if we ſhould ſo think, we ſhould be dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iued. Na y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> K. of <hi>Babilon,</hi> which was a far
<pb facs="tcp:21445:38"/>of, ſent afterwardes letters vnto the ſayd <hi>Ezechias</hi> by Ambaſſadours and Princes of Babilon, to enquire of the wonder. And ſhal not we vndoubtedly bee reſolued that this teſtimony that God gaue in this order of the abuſe of his ſon, reached furder then <hi>Iudea,</hi> na euen ouer all the whole world? for euen the very horror of that fact, cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun (as it were to kepe backe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of illumination of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had ſo yll deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued at the hands of his Maker, &amp; Creator. But now I hauing ſufficiently ſpoken of Eclipſes, aad of theyr kyndes and cauſes, I am to proceede to other viſions &amp; ſights, cauſed oftentymes by meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Suns working, which are no leſſe meruaylous. Of the which ſorte is the ſhew and ſighte of many Sunnes at once in the fyrmament called of the <hi>Gretians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: which are ingendred through this occaſion. When as ſome cloude of good thicknes and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and which is alſo regular &amp; vniforme is placed ſo,<note place="margin">Many Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſeene at once.</note> as that it is neither vnder the Sun, nor directly agaynſt it but as it wer on his ſyde, and ſo nigh as it may be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into rayne, and beyng not yet reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the Sunne by the refractions of hys
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21445:38"/>beams doth imprynte and forme his owne Image there, as hee doth oftentymes in braſſe that is well and finely polliſhed. And this ymage of the Sun ſo conſiſting on his ſyde is called <hi>Parahelius,</hi> of the Greeke prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifyeth next, &amp; the Greeke nowne <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſygnifyeth the Sun: ſo that <hi>Parahelius</hi> is another im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in all poyntes moſtlike to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun. Wee ſayd before that, that Cloude which muſt be the mater hereof, muſt be conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or thickt, that it may the better cauſe forth refraction. And that it muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuate, that it maye receaue a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Image of the Sunne: likewyſe that it muſt be regular and altogeather vniforme that it may receaue a more true and perfit image therof: and alſo that it muſt beready to be reſolued into rayne, that the Sunne may the better repreſent his lykenes in the ſame: and yet not conuerted, or reſolued, for that if it were already reſolued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parts therof beyng diſcontinued, the ſayd clowd were not fyt neither to receyue the ymage of the Sun, nor to ſhew forth the ſame. And theſe impreſſions be called Suns, through the likenes that they haue of the Sun: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:21445:39"/>that at their appearance we are to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that there is but one of them the true Sun indeed, and the other to bee but likeneſſes of the Sun.<note place="margin">3 Sunnes ſeenevvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> There haue bene three Sunnes appeared at once in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of our Forefathers and Auncientes,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 2 cap. 31.</note> as when <hi>Spurius Poſthumius</hi> and <hi>Quintus Minutius,</hi> were Conſuls, and when <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus Minutius, &amp; Marcus Partius</hi> wer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office: and alſo when <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> &amp; <hi>Publius Dolobella</hi> had the ſame rome: &amp; beſydes when <hi>Marcus Lepidus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lucius Plancus</hi> enioyed the ſame ſuperioritye: &amp; more then three Sunnes at one tyme hath neuer bene ſeene. There appeared alſo <hi>3.</hi> Sunnes at the tyme of the byrth of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, which at length com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming together into one gaue forth therby ſome ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the miſtery of the holy Trinity to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tanied in vnity which now by the comming of Chriſt was to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in all the worlde: and that the ſame Child which was then born, the Sunne of righteouſnes, hadd, and contayned in him completely the fulnes of the Godhead, and that together with Chriſt, now neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe incarnated, the Father and the holy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21445:39"/>Ghoſt were al one in ſubſtaunce, and all of them diſtinct in perſonne and all of them but one God, one vncreate and euerlaſting power, which is to bleſſed for euermore, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. This <hi>Parahelius,</hi> or appearaunce of diuers Suns at one tyme, differeth from that Impreſſion, whiche is called <hi>Halo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Halo of the Sun.</note> which ſheweth forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude of a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land about the Sun: and lykewyſe from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raynbow, in many poyntes, but chieflye in the ſituaſion of place, for that the garlande is euer directly vnder the Sun: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe is euer ouer agaynſte hym oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitlye: but this <hi>Parahelius</hi> is ſituated in none of theſe orders: for if this ſhould bee in place of the firſt, the Sunne muſt needs diſperſe the matter therof with his heate, and if it were in place of the laſt, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great diſtance therof the diſtraction ſhould be to feeble to cauſe forth the image of the Sun. Therfore it is placed on the ſyde of the Sun, that the matter thereof cannot through ſuch nighnes be eaſily diſſolued, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Sun beams may occaſionate a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t refractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better faſhioning of the Suns likenes: &amp; whereas this <hi>Halo</hi> doth ſeme to be as it were vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun, as alſo
<pb facs="tcp:21445:40"/>about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, euen ryght vnder her, yet notwithſtanding it is but engendred in the midle region of the ayre, &amp; often beneath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, and cauſed onely by ſuch directe ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and placing: but it is through the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſility of our eyeſight, that wee therein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng deceyued, do thinke amiſſe, the ſayd garland to be neere the Sunne and Mone. Vnder which this <hi>Halo</hi> ſheweth and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more often by a greate deale, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun: for the Sun with his adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heat doth more eaſily diſpach, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſuch vapours, as go to the originall thereof, then the Moone, who hath a more moyſt light and feeble heate.</p>
               <p>There hath appeared alſo a garlande of bloudy coloure,<note place="margin">Garlande of bloudy colour.</note> and cyrcled by reaſon of the condenſity, or thicknes of the clowde, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſyng aboute the Sun beams, as it had bene a circle of bloud. And this ſight was ſeene (as <hi>Plinie</hi> reporteth it) in the tyme of the Conſulſhip of <hi>Lucius Iulius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">li. 2. ca. 30</note> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Rutilius.</hi> There hath bene alſo verye prodigious, and very long lacke and want of the Sunnes ſhyning forth,<note place="margin">Long lack of the Sun thyne.</note> as was after that tyme, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> the Dictator was ſlayne: and in the tyme of the warres of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21445:40"/>
                  <hi>Antony,</hi> the ſun almoſt for a whole yeres ſpace neuer a whit ſhyning forth.<note place="margin">Bloudy bovves.</note> There hath bene alſo ſeene a bloudy bow aboute the Sun, as when <hi>Lucius Opimius</hi> the thyrd time, and <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond time, were made <hi>Conſuls:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stars ſene in the day time. Plinie. li. 2 cap 28.</note> as alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of the ſelfe ſame ſupertority impoſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Lucius Portius,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Acilius.</hi> So there were ſeene ſtarres in the day tyme following, and accompanying the Sunne all the day longe, and they ſhewed aboute the circle of the Sunne, as they had bene a kind of garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or a diuerſe coloured kind of circle, as in the beginning of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi> If this garland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like impreſſion called <hi>Halo</hi> whether it be of the Sun of Moone vaniſheth away ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly of by little and little lyke ſmoake,<note place="margin">Halo vvhat it prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cateth,</note> it ſignifieth and prognoſticateth fayre wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to enſue: for that thoſe vapours which otherwyſe are to bee reſolued into rayne, are now vaniſhed and gone. The nexte im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I haue to ſpeake of, (which is alſo one of the Sunnes effecte) is the Raynebowe, whych is thus engendred in a watry cloud,<note place="margin">Rainbovv novv en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred.</note> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ready to reſolue into a ſhower right oppoſite againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun,
<pb facs="tcp:21445:41"/>as the beames of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne are beaten backe agayne, it cauſeth the ſame Cloude, albeit obſcurely, and imperfectly to expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the ſame, which neuertheleſſe for the far diſtance and interiection of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours being betwene the ſunne and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Cloude, expreſſe it very weakely. Which inbecillity cauſeth the figure of a bowe in the ſame cloude, beautified &amp; diſtinguiſhed with <hi>3.</hi> ſeuerall colours: toweete yealow,<note place="margin">Three co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loures in the ſame vvherev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon,</note> Greene, and purple, and ſometimes red, &amp; in ſteade of Greene, a colour more blacke then Greene: which diuerſity of coloures come hereof, as the beames of the ſun are drawen out longer or ſhorter in the cloude: for the longer they be reached out, ſo much the weaker and feebler are the colours of the Raynbowe: as which alſo geue forth a greater obſcurity and blacknes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the yealow colour altreth to a greene, the greene to a more blacke. And agayne, the ſame Beames beinge become weaker geue forth in the Rainbowe a more weake colour. And contrarywyſe ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe as theſe Beames be ſtretched out, ſo much the more freſh and floriſhing colours doth the Raynebowe geue out.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21445:41"/>
               <p>Now the figure of the Raynebowe why it is croked, or halfe circled after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manner of a Bowe, it would be conſidered.<note place="margin">Why it is croked or halfe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled.</note> When there is a Cloude regular &amp; right ſet, and the ſame in a parte thereof as it were ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in one horizon, ſo as the other part of the cloude going and declininge beneath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame horizon is taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſight, hereupon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Raynbowe appeareth croked: and the nearer the ſunne commeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, ſo much the greater is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raynbowe. So that the rainbowe doth neuer appeare after a whole circle, or bigger then halfe a circle, but either as a <hi>ſemicircle,</hi> at one end touching one parte of our horizon, and at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ende the contrary parte of the ſame: or els it is ſometimes leſſe then a <hi>ſemicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</hi> There are oftentimes ſeene <hi>2.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tvvo and 3. bovves at once.</note> Rayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes at once, and ſometimes althoughe (very ſeldome) three. When there doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare but two at once they haue doth the ſelfe ſame colours: but a contrary placing of the ſame: ſo that whereas the principall hath yealowiſhe, greene, and red: the other hath in his ſituation firſt red, then greene, and laſtly yealowiſhe. And that Raynbow which ſheweth weakeſt, is the Paterne or
<pb facs="tcp:21445:42"/>Image of the pryncipaler, and ſtrongeſt. Alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there doth appeare three at once the third is ſo weake as it can ſcantly bee perceiued. For the thyrde commeth of the refractions of the Beames of the ſecond, which muſt needes be but very weak. And this thirde being of ſuch weakenes wyll haue notwithſtanding alwaies the colours of the firſt and ſtrongeſt, and wil be lightly after a yelow, greene and purple colour. Further this is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the higher the Sunne is exalted aboue our horrizon, ſo much the leſſe doth the Rainebow appear. as when any ſheweth aboute the mid day, they ſhew very ſmal. But thoſe which ſhew either ſhortly after the Sonne ryſinge, or not longe before the ſunne ſet: they bee the greateſt. So likewyſe in the midſt of ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, whe the Sun is in the chiefeſt Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer pointes and Signes: as when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies bee longeſt wée ſee no Rainebowes ſhewe forth at any time, aboute noone or the mid day, But after the <hi>Aequinoctium</hi> of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne following, when the ſun entreth in to <hi>Libra:</hi> we ſee about the ſame time many Rainbowes almoſt at al houres of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day, Now come wee to Comettes or blaſing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21445:42"/>ſtarres being of the kinds of fiery Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions alſo,<note place="margin">Comets or blaſing ſtarres. Hovv en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred.</note> and occaſioned by the ſuns ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration chiefely, and the other ſtarres. For the Comet is thus engendred. Whereas by the force of the ſun and the other ſtarres there is eleuated and drawen vp on hye, ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry much viſcous matter hoate &amp; dry, groſſe and fat, and ſuch as will be commodiouſly kyndled and ſet on fyre, from theſe earthly places to the higheſt region of the Ayre, where it being turned aboute round, wyth the motion of the ayre, and being nighe the fire is kindled and ſet on fyre equally and on euery ſide, and ſo other exhalatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing and comming on doth both nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and encreaſe the burning thereof: ſuch kinde of impreſſion is called a comet.<note place="margin">Kyndes thereof.</note> The matter whereof if it be groſſer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt, and thinner on the furthermore and oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſides, it appeareth after the manner of hayre, or as the Horſes mane: &amp; is called <hi>Stella Comata.</hi> But if the ſides &amp; outward parts therof be be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding downward in le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth tailewiſe it is called <hi>Cometa caudata:</hi> but if thoſe ſides &amp; parts being very ſubtile be thinly layed downe or ſcattered belowe beardewiſe, it is called <hi>Stella Barbata.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21445:43"/>The matter of a Comet muſt needes bee much and great, and very plentifull or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popious, or els otherwiſe it ſhoulde ſoone be conſumed away throughe the Adurant heate of the ſunne. And the ſhorteſt time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer any Comet continueth and is ſeene, is at the leaſt the ſpace of ſeuen whole dayes,<note place="margin">Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> &amp; for the moſt parte it is <hi>40.</hi> dayes or more yea <hi>80.</hi> dayes ere it vaniſheth away, neuer geuing ouer his fiery ſhewe and looke, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till all ſuch viſcouſe matter be quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med away in burninge out. The chiefeſt time of a Comet is chiefly in and about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of Autumne,<note place="margin">Chiefeſt time there of.</note> becauſe that then there is ſufficient heate to eleuate ſuch viſcouſe matter, and then there is alſo temperate heate, which eaſily ſuffereth ſuch matter without any hinder aunce of the ſame to be ſoundly compact together: which in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cannot bee well done, as at what time ſuch groſſe matter of exhalation throughe the Sunnes heate diſperſing the ſame, &amp; alſo for the extreame coldneſſe of the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Region of the Ayre, doth not permit the ſame to paſſe vp into the higheſt Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So in the Springe tyme there is not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more parte ſufficient heate to eleuate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21445:43"/>ſo great matter: in Winter the extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Moyſture, and colde is vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant thereto. And yet <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his firſt booke of his <hi>Meteores</hi> maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Comet very horrible, great, and greeuous, which was ſeene in the dayes of <hi>Aſius</hi> the Prynce of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> euen in a very froſty and colde winter, but as he ſaith, very fayre, and cleare, which at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt appeared ſo litle that in the firſt day of his ſhewe it was as it had ben vaniſhed away and gone, a litle before the Sunne ſet: but afterwardes it ſhewed agayne ſo grat that it caſt out his lighte to the thirde parte of Heauen, and ſhyned forth in manner of the ſinne: ſo that it went as it were a way of light: and this aſcendinge at the laſt to the Horizon did there aboutes weare away. Whenſoeuer there be any Comets there followeth ſhortly after great tempeſts and wyndes and continuance of dry weather, &amp; great drouthes.<note place="margin">Comets vvhat thei prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate.</note> Theſe Comets doe prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate Warre, Commotions, ſturres, ſtryfes, Treaſons, and ſuch like, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the tyme of their Generation and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, exceding heate ruleth and boyleth in men, which Incenſeth and ſturreth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="tcp:21445:44"/>thereto, the bodyes and myndes of men. And beſides this, it ſignifieth more eſpecially the death of Princes and Noble Perſonages, for that the Ayre which then is more groſſe and viſcouſe through the cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted matter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Comet, is not ſo whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for delicate and deliciouſe Perſons, as for the luſty and courſe Conſtitution of the bodyes &amp; appetites of Labourers and Huſbandmen. But now to returne to the proper poſſeſſion of the ſunne in all kindes of Bodies here belowe.</p>
               <p>Such as be borne vnder <hi>Sol,</hi> are for the moſt parte of a browne colour, and of ſmal ſtature, yet well and comely knit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porcioned: they be alſo of a very thin haire and curled Head, Gray eyed: they be alſo hawty ſtomacked, and they are aduaunced often to great honours and dignities. And the Diſpoſition of their minde is ſuch that they be ſtudious of difficult and hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, very deſirous of glory and ronowne. They bee alſo faſt and faythfull in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and conſtant in Fact and worde. They bee likewiſe, Wiſe, and Polliticke touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing common wealth affayres, and are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much to procure the profit of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21445:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>Vnder his gouernment among the kindes of Beaſtes are alſo all ſuch as be of bigge ſtature, and of hawty ſtomacke: likewyſe ſuch as are deſierous of ſuperiority, and haue naturally a pryde in themſelues: Of which ſorte is the Lyon, the Crocodile, the wilde and vntamed Lynx, the Ramme, the Oliphant, the Tyger, likewiſe the Wolfe whom the aunciente Gentils dedicated to <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Latona:</hi> amonge Fowles hee hath as his owne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Phaenix,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 10. Cap. 2.</note> which chiefly keepeth about the Coaſtes of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and is in bigneſſe about the greatneſſe of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agle,<note place="margin">Phęnix.</note> which ſhyneth like Golde aboute her necke, and in other partes of her ſhe is pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple coloured, ſauing that her Tayle being blewe is diſtinguiſhed with roſe coloured feathers. She lyueth a long time, euen <hi>6.</hi> hundred and three ſcore yeares: and when ſhe waxeth olde and is weary of her lyfe, ſhee getteth ſlippes of <hi>Caſia,</hi> and Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, &amp; maketh her Neſt on hygh as nigh the ſun as ſhe can, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhe dieth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brunt &amp; conſumed into Aſhes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuns heate: out of whoſe bones &amp; aſhes there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>greth firſt as it were a litle ſmal worme, which in ſhorte time after proueth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a younge <hi>Phaenix.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>There is no man that euer ſeeth the <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> eating: likewiſe to <hi>Sol</hi> appertayneth the Eagle which keepeth moſt in Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes,<note place="margin">Eagle.</note> and which almoſt of all Fowles is without her cry, &amp; is alſo very rauenous, ſo that whatſoeuer pray it catcheth, it cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it away ſwiftly. But one good proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it is not without herein, for that it ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after his pray a far of alwayes, neuer ſpoyling about the place where ſhe abideth and breedeth. They neuer commonly dye vpon death, nor ſickneſſe, but vpon famine: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when they were old, their bill grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out at length in the vpper part thereof onely, and the neather parte of the ſame ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſhrynking then ſtill continuing at his olde ſtay, doth cauſe that ſhe cannot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly receiue her Foode. Her flight and trauaylinge is onely in the after Noone, ſitting ſtill idle all the foore Noone eying the aſſemblies of men, &amp; will not remooue till that ſhe haue had wearineſſe therein. In her Neaſt is onely found the Precious ſtone <hi>Aetites</hi> which is very Medicinable and which no fyre can doe harme vnto.<note place="margin">Aetites.</note> Her feathers being put amonge other Brides Feathers will eate and conſume vp the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21445:45"/>this hath a great and mortall hatred to the Dragon, which very greedely hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after the Eagles Egges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOL</hi> alſo or the Sunne, ruleth ouer the <hi>Vultures</hi> whych are of ſuch ſmell,<note place="margin">Vulture</note> as that they can thereby finde out any dead Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe whereſoeuer it be hidden: lykewiſe ouer all ſuch Fowles as which with very pleaſaunt Note and Ditty or Songe, doe as it were welcome the Sunne at his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing: Of which fortes are the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale,<note place="margin">Nightin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gale.</note> which oftentimes ſo ſtriueth to excell in her ſinging as that in ſtrayning herſelfe ſhe falleth a bleeding oftentimes: yea, and the continuance of her ſinginge is ſuch as <hi>Plynie</hi> reporteth,<note place="margin">Lib. 10. Cap. 29.</note> that fiftene whole dayes and nyghts together ſhee neuer leaueth of therein. Of all byrdes for her Song moſt maruaylous: firſt that there ſhould bee in ſo ſmall a body, ſo forcible a Breath or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite: ſecondly, that in the ſame beinge but one body, all the whole perfection of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, as it were, ſhould be vttered forth &amp; and ſounded, nowe in playne Note, nowe deſcantinge, anon recording, and anon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canting all: one while diſpleaſed with her Note ſhe is in her Baſe, and by and by in
<pb facs="tcp:21445:46"/>her Treable, ſhortly after in the meane: ſo that it is a mater euen almoſt of aſtoniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſee and heare ſuch variety of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody to iſſue and proceede from ſo ſmall a breaſt: which emulateth in a maner all the melodious, and harmonycall Inſtruments that euer mans arte or wit coulde deuyſe. The Male, &amp; Female hereof doth ſtriue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, which of them may moſt excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Song, ſo long that now &amp; then one of them killeth themſelues thereby. And their younge liſten to them both, framinge themſelues to imitate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Note y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they moſt delight in, in as attentiue ſorte as the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Scholer geeueth good heede to the wholſome inſtruction of his Maiſter. The beſt note they haue is <hi>15.</hi> whole dayes and nightes together chiefly in the ſpring time: then being ſo wearied they reſt a while, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing ſo earneſt to ſing as before: in Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer after, they ſing other whiles, but nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo artificially or variouſly: in which time with their note they alſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their colour. Laſtly in winter they be ſeldome or neuer heard or ſeene. Her breedinge onely is in the ſpringtime and ſhe layeth <hi>6</hi> Egs. Vnder the ſunnes gouernment alſo is the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21445:46"/>Larke, as alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cocke which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nights watchman, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornings Embaſſadour:<note place="margin">Cocke.</note> and the Artificers, wayfaringmen, &amp; huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handmens Clocke to awake them oute of ſleape, to ſettle them forwardes towardes their next dayes buſines. The Cocke go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to rouſt about the ſunſet, and afore his ryſinge agayne hee commonly croweth in the morning three ſeuerall times: in which crowing he beateth himſelfe with his win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. He is very Emperious ouer all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fowles where he abydeth, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth right well the force of his Spurres: if he getteth the victory in fight he triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in crowing: but if he be beaten he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and hydeth himſelfe. Vnder <hi>Sol</hi> is alſo the Crowe, the Pye, the Goſhawkes which be of diuerſe ſorts:<note place="margin">Goſhaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</note> for ſome of them flye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly after Fowles belowe: other ſome as the fowles flyeth about the trees: other as they ſit on high: other as they flys in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> open ayre. In a part of <hi>Thracia</hi> which lyeth vpon <hi>Amphipolis</hi> the Men and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haukes there, are of ſuch mutual ſociety &amp; fellowſhip as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly hawke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſuch order y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the men there doe but onely beate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byrdes vp out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thickets &amp; woods, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſhawks tarying on hie meet
<pb facs="tcp:21445:47"/>them and ſtrike them downe aſſone as they haue flowen vp. And therefore for this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceablens of theirs, they ordinarily looke for ſome parte of the pray, and haue it. It is not ſeene at any time that the Goſhauke eateth the heart of Fowles. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder <hi>Sol</hi> is alſo the Peacocke, which gloryeth in him ſelfe in beholding his Golden,<note place="margin">Peacock</note> Glorious, &amp; Glittering colours, which chiefly ſhewe moſt beautifull and Radiant, as hee ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth right ouer agaynſt the Sunne: This after hee hath once caſt his Feathers and loſt his tayle, (which he doth euery yeare) hydeth him ſelfe and is as it were ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a time, vntill the ſame be growen agayne. He lyueth <hi>25.</hi> yeares: and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſhew in his gay coloures after hee is once three yeares olde. The firſt that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cauſed the Peacocke to bee ſerued in the courſe of Seruice at any Feaſte, was <hi>Hortenſius</hi> the Orator.</p>
               <p>Among Fyſhes in <hi>Sols</hi> ſubiection is the Fyſhe <hi>Dactylus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dactyl.</note> which is like to a Mans Nayle, which is of ſuch glittering colour that it ſhineth wonderfully in the day time, and ſheweth alſo ſhyningly in the nyght: lykewiſe in the ſame order vnder <hi>Sol</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21445:47"/>Starfiſhe, and alſo <hi>Strombus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stromb.</note> which is of all kindes of Fyſhes moſt cyuill, <hi>Aelianns</hi> ſayth that they haue their King vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they alwayes waite. They hadde in olde time ſuch an opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer coulde ſee any of theſe being vpon the Seas hee ſhould haue proſperous ſucceſſe and good lucke in all his affayres. Heather to alſo be longeth the fiſhe <hi>Scolopendra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Scolope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> which hath as it were an hundred feete, and which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnder the bayte receiued in the hooke into her Belly, doth perbrake and caſt out all her Bowels within her, vntill ſhee be deliuered of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, and then afterwardes ſhe ſoopeth and receyueth them in againe: hetherto pertayneth the Seafoxe,<note place="margin">Seafox.</note> whych contrarywiſe as ſhee perceyueth her ſelfe caught, doth not caſt vp as the other, but doth deuour and receiue the Hooke &amp; Line downe into her Belly more and more, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſhe commeth to the weakeſt parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lyne, and then the ſhame ſhe byteth a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Hetherto likewiſe ſerueth the Fyſhe <hi>Glanis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Glanis,</note> which never deuoureth the Hooke or byteth at the bayte a right or forth on as the other doth, but contrariwiſe eateth and gnaweth on the ſides thereof ſo ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:21445:48"/>as that by ſnatches got away nowe and then. Hee repaſſeth himſelfe, and is neuer taken with the hooke.<note place="margin">Crabfish</note> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto <hi>Sol</hi> belongeth alſo the Crabuſh which delighteth in roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky places, which alſo were fat in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprynge time, and Autumne: and ſpecially then at the full of the Moone. They liue a longe time, and haue eight feete bending croked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in one towards another. The Females firſt foote is doubled or parted, the males is al alyke. Theſe being in fear wil creepe as faſt backeward as forward. They fight betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as it were with hornes which they ſeeme to haue after the maner of Rammes. They are ſufferaigne reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt the byting of ſerpentes.<note place="margin">Plinie lib. 9. cap. 31.</note> They ſay that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Sol</hi> entreth into <hi>Cancer</hi> that the bodies of theſe which being deade and caſt forth into dry places do reuiue againe there, and doe degenerate into a kinde of <hi>Scorpions.</hi> Amongeſt <hi>Plantes,</hi> and firſte, &amp; formoſt amongeſt Trees, theſe are in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to <hi>Sol:</hi> firſt the Olyue tree, whoſe iuice is the oyle Oliue. Alſo the <hi>Cyprouſe</hi> treee which chiefely proſpereth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yland <hi>Creta:</hi> alſo the <hi>Cedar</hi> tree, the <hi>Balme</hi> tree which in preciouſnes of ſmell, far excedeth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21445:48"/>all other woods: and is only to be had as it groweth in the land of <hi>Iury:</hi> This tree ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer groweth higher then two cubits hye: Likewiſe the pepper tree which groweth chiefely in <hi>Arabia,</hi> although now in <hi>Italy</hi> there is a kind of pepper tree not much vn like the Myrt tree. This pepper tree, hath a certaine cod as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuniper hath, but this is more ſmall,<note place="margin">Pepper tree.</note> in which lyeth the Pepper ſeede: which cods pluckte of before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin togape or breake out and dryed againſt the ſun and rowled out at length, cauſeth the longe Pepper: and contrarywiſe thoſe Coddes ſuffered and let alone tyll they are ready to fal forth out of the huſke themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, grow round and ſhew fyrſt white, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they being dryed, and as it were roſted in the Sun, doe thereby both change theyr colour to black, &amp; become wrinckled. With theſe pepper berries there are often Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per berries intermedled whych are taken for the other. The blackeſt Pepper is accompted the chiefeſt. Hetherto likewyſe belongth the Cinamon tree which chyefely groweth in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tree.</note> whoſe ſtickes is beſt at the top of the tree aboute the bignes of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hand: then next towardes and at the body of the ſame: but worſt of al towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roote thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:49"/>
               <p>And the tree is neuer aboue the heyghte of two cubits:<note place="margin">Lote tree.</note> likewiſe vnder <hi>Sol</hi> is the <hi>Lote</hi> tree which is a noble tree in <hi>Arabia,</hi> ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious that they ſay a man ſhall neuer feele ache or haue diſeaſe of body ſo longe as he vſeth to eate thereof. The fruite thereof is ſaffron coloured, and is in quantity as byg as a beane. The fruite hereof is of ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt taſt, as is wine: &amp; hereof is confecte &amp; made a kinde of wine, but it laſteth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the ſpace of ten Dayes. Wyth thys whole armies haue bene ſuſtained ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for lacke of other neceſſaries alonge tyme, and haue done very well. It is called of ſome <hi>Arbor ſolaris,</hi> the Sunnes tree, for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of his fruite and leafe is after the Sunne. There is (as <hi>Ruellius</hi> witneſſeth) a notable tree in <hi>Affricke</hi> of thys kynde &amp; name: of whoſe fruite if any ſtraunger doth taſte or eate of, he incontinently doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get himſelfe of what place and countrey he is of. Amongſt hearbes theſe appertayn to <hi>Sol.</hi> Fyrſt the herbe <hi>Helyotropium</hi> which turneth round with the Sunne, both ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, encreaſing and cloſing as the Sunne ryſeth, aſcendeth, or goeth downe. Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe the herbe <hi>Pyonie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bugloſſe</hi> which is ſo ſayde becauſe it is like a bullockes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21445:49"/>tongue: and <hi>Cynogloſſe</hi> whych is lyke a dogges tongue. Likewiſe the herbe <hi>Scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie</hi> whoſe leaues are like Iuye but ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more Tryanglewiſe, his flower is white. Thys is very hoate &amp; purgeth chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and layd to any ſwellinges doth helpe the ſame.<note place="margin">Dictamus</note> Likewyſe the hearbe <hi>Dictamus</hi> which is lyke <hi>Sorrel,</hi> yet very bitter as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oſcorides</hi> ſaith. It is chiefely founde gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing in <hi>Creet,</hi> and with the ſame Hartes being wounded or ſhot in with any arrow or darte do herewith cure themſelues, and diſcharge theyr bodyes of the weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer: Likewyſe the hearbe <hi>Celidonye</hi> which is vſed of Swallowes as a Mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine to helpe the ſorenes of theyr eyes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt gemmes or precions ſtones, theſe are chiefly ſubiected to <hi>Sol.</hi> Fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Chru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolyte</hi> whych being held againſt the ſunne doth gieue forth beames in color like gold. Hetherto alſo belongeth the precious <hi>Iris</hi> whoſe colour is after a chryſtall. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes found in his faſhion ſixe cornered or ſixe ſquare. This being held in any couert place doth manifeſtly ſhew forth the reflexi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of the Sunne vpon the contrary parte or ſide of the wal. There is alſo a precious
<pb facs="tcp:21445:50"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21445:50"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21445:51"/>ſtone called <hi>Heliotropius,</hi> which is after a Iaſper, which being held vp betwixte the ſunne and our eyes, doth make the Sunne to apeare bloudy, and repreſenteth to vs a likenes of the ſunnes Eclypſe. With this, (as alſo with the Hearb of like name) the <hi>Magicians</hi> playnely profeſſed that a man may goe inuiſible. Hereupon this laſt is called <hi>Solſequium,</hi> as alſo <hi>Heliotropium.</hi> for that it followeth and turneth rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with the ſunne. In like condicion is the hearbe <hi>Hyacinth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hyacinth.</note> which is made effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous by the ſunne to helpe agaynſt Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: which alſo maketh the bearer ſaufe, &amp; getteth him fauour, winneth him riches, and diſpoſeth him to a quicke &amp; ſharp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: and being held or reſerued in the Mouth, comforteth and cheareth the heart or minde, and next after that, all the whole partes of the body. Hetherto lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe belongeth the Precious Pyrophyte, which is of a mixed red:<note place="margin">Pantaure.</note> as alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taure which draweth all other ſtones to it, after ſuch wiſe as the Lodeſtone draweth yron: of other ſome it is called Pantherus, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is diuerſly ſpotted after the maner of the Panther: and it is called Pantochras, for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21445:51"/>that it is of all coloures. Alſo the Topaze, the Chruſopaſſe, the Rubine, the Gem cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>Solis Oculus,</hi> as alſo the Carbuncle, which of the ſunne receiueth his hoat bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning colour. Among Mettals <hi>Sol</hi> hath in in his regiment golde beautifying it wyth ſo excellent a colour as that it ſhyneth like the ſunne: as alſo gieuing it that force and powre confortatiue that it hath, as alſo the powre reſtauritiue: likewiſe his is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mettall, and the more puerer Braſſe. Humoures which bee his is the pure Life bloud, as alſo he chalengeth the life breath. And finally among the Elements, he hath to doe with the fier and fiery flame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Countryes ſubiect to Sol.</note>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> with <hi>Leo</hi> hath ſpeciall gouernment ouer <hi>Italy, Apulia, Spayne, Cicilia, Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicea, Caldaea,</hi> &amp; other ſuch like Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Kyngdomes.</p>
               <p>The Sunne finiſheth and endeth his Courſe aboute the Zodiacke in <hi>365.</hi> dayes, and ſixe howres.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Mars" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:52"/>
               <head>Of MARS the fifth Planet.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARS in Greeke is</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee is fierce and fiery hoat: ſo is he alſo dry, and worketh the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke Complexion, which is alſo hoat &amp; dry: as <hi>Saturne</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Melancholicke complexion which is colde &amp; dry. This <hi>Mars</hi> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the God of battayle, for that he ſtyrreth vp mens myndes to debate and ſtryfe, and letteth the league of Tranquillity &amp; peace. He is alſo called <hi>Mars, <hi>quaſi mors,</hi>
                  </hi> for that he is a heauy, hard, and deadly Planet: or for that hee procureth the death &amp; decay of many Inferior bodyes. <hi>Ouid</hi> ſayth that he was Sonne to <hi>Iuno,</hi> without Father, but conceyued of her through a certayne hearb which <hi>Flora</hi> on a time ſhewed vnto ber.<note place="margin">Philolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia. lib. 33</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sons to this <hi>Mars</hi> (as <hi>Volateranus</hi> ſaith) were firſt <hi>Oenomaus</hi> which raygned in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys,</hi> which obtayned the Daughter of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21445:52"/>called <hi>Hyppodamia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus. Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damia. The ſvvif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vvas. Mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippus.</note> which was the ſwyfteſt Runner that euer was, &amp; had her to his wyfe, by out runninge her. And by <hi>Meroe, Mars</hi> had alſo another Son called <hi>Parthaon:</hi> and a third called <hi>Oeneus</hi> king of <hi>Calidonia,</hi> of whom came <hi>Dianira,</hi> which was wife to <hi>Hercules,</hi> and <hi>Melea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Tydeus,</hi> and <hi>Menalippus.</hi> This <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalippus</hi> whileſt hee in hunting the wylde Bore in a Woode earneſtly followed his Game, was vnwares &amp; by euell hap ſlaine of his brother <hi>Tydeus,</hi> who afterwardes fled and came into <hi>Argos</hi> by night, and hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pening into the court of <hi>Adraſtus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, and katched in a grieuous Rayne ſought further, and anon hit into a ſhelter where <hi>Polynices</hi> baniſhed his countrey abode, &amp; was ſcanted, ſo that that roome would not ſerue them both, for the which cauſe they fell together by the Eares, and wounded ech other grieuouſly.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Mars</hi> is paynted &amp; drawen forth hee reſembleth a tall and luſty Stripling ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with open breaſt, and his feete ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth as though he ſtryded, noting there by that warres are to be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted of haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty heartes, and to bee followed &amp; purſued
<pb facs="tcp:21445:53"/>buſily. His colour is ſomewhat red, hys houſe or place of abode is in <hi>Aries</hi> &amp; <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio,</hi> his exaltation or aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is in the <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>Capricornus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Martlaliſts hovv affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note> Such as are borne vnder <hi>Mars</hi> are cruell, dreadfull, deſpitefull, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, quickely moued and ſtyrred vp to wrath and anger: theyr countenaunce and looke alſo is ſowre, grim &amp; fearful. Theyr colour for the moſt part is after a fiery red theyr hayre cole blacke, theyr face rounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, theyr eies yellowiſh. In conuerſation and demeanure or maner of life they he im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pudent, and ſhameles, very aduentrous &amp; bold, hardy, hie minded, proude, crafty and ſubtill. Wherevpon in token of ſuch diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitions that the Martialiſtes were ſo encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, they were wont in old time to ſet out <hi>Mars</hi> theyr gouernour like a ſouldyer hauing a ſallet on his head, and in his lefte hand was put a Sword, and in his ryghte hand he had a Iauelin or ſpeare, whereby was ſignified his daily practiſe and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rement towards wars and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention. The ſtone which they vſed in time paſte to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue <hi>Mars</hi> in, was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly the Adamant ſtone, wherin they drewout a harneſſed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riding vpon an <hi>Aegle</hi> in whoſe righte ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21445:53"/>was a naked ſword, and in his left hand a mans head which turned round about. By this was vttered forth how mighty, ſwift, and fierce <hi>Mars</hi> is in battayle, ſo that hys power is a terrour to all the whole fielde. <hi>Mars</hi> maketh thoſe bodies ouer whome he hath preheminence hardy and aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous, and diſpoſeth them by a certaine naturall inclination to aptnes and dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the quicke and expedite obtayning of ſuch artes and crafts as be manual or don by ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <hi>Mars</hi> likewiſe amongſt ſuch beaſts as be brutiſh exceedingly, &amp; ſauage or wild is altogether ruler. Likewiſe amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be fierce ſtomaked or warlik of which ſort is the horſe,<note place="margin">Horſe by vvhome firſt found out &amp; rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den on.</note> which was firſt found out by <hi>Neptunus,</hi> &amp; by him firſt made acquain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with men, after that, he was firſte rode vpon by the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> of whom <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phon</hi> reporteth as followeth, how we ſhal haue an vndoubted &amp; perfec trial of a good horſe: Fyrſt he requireth that he be broade breſted,<note place="margin">A perfect triall of a good horſe.</note> which tendeth both to comelines &amp; importeth main &amp; great ſtrength, &amp; beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, he ſhal ſo bew<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out danger beneath in his feete of ſmiting one againſt another in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing which we cal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly enterfering.
<pb facs="tcp:21445:54"/>And ſecondly, his necke he would not haue hang downe prone, in manner of a boare, nor yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be too erect or ſtrayt vp, in maner of a Cocke, but to be indifferent betwene both: his head hee would haue to be bony, his Iawbones ſmall, and his eyes in his Iourneying bendinge downe to the beholding of his feete: for the holding out of his necke at length is a ſigne of weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and weakenes in a horſe, and bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Iade. It is alſo to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his eyes be eyther hollowe and deepe within, or whether he be ful eyed and often fiery coloured in the ſame, which onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth great valiancy in a horſe, as alſo that he is of exceeding ſharpe eyeſight: his Noſthrils alſo the more open they appeare and withall bending right downe, do both demonſtrate great eaſe &amp; liberty of breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a horſe, as alſo very great fiercenes: his eares muſt not bee longe, his Foretop ſomewhat longer then his Mane: his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt be ſomwhat gaunt grayhou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlike: his Loynes how much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broader &amp; ſhorter they be, ſo much the more eaſy is his pace: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more that his buttockes be deuided &amp; parted with a broader ſtrike, ſeame, or line
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21445:54"/>ryght downe toward his Tayle, the more ſwifter hee is in his runninge, his hinder feete getting an aduantage thereby of hys forefeete in euery ſtep and pace: if a man will frame and make his horſe fit for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like exerciſes,<note place="margin">Hovv to make a Horſe Warlike</note> he hath (as <hi>Zenophon</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celleth (to try Maiſteries with him in this order: he muſt not ſpare to make him take hedge and dytches: yea, nor to leape ouer walles ſomtimes: he muſt often alſo exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe himſelfe both to ſkip of, and to ſkip on at his pleaſure: and to put him forth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles right on, ſometimes to reuert and turne him backwards, and ſomewhiles to ride him ſidelong. Somewhiles the Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is to bringe him out from his pryuate courſing at home or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fieldes, into thro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; frequented places, that with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight, noyſe, and hearing of ſo populous a multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude he may acquaint him ſelfe, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tractability of the Ryder to be fit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for euery aſſay. <hi>Columella</hi> ſayth of horſes,<note place="margin">Hovve Horſes markes vveare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay.</note> that their Markes of age weare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly as they grow one in yeres: for when they become two yeares olde and an halfe, he ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then their middle teeth both aboue and belowe doe fall away: and
<pb facs="tcp:21445:55"/>when they bee foure yeares olde they caſt thoſe teeth of theirs which he called <hi>Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> which bee ſharp after Dogges teeth, &amp; haue new agayne by and by grow in their roome: and afterwards when they growe to be about ſixe yeares old, their Wange teeth or great Grynders aboue fall away. And when they bee ſeuen yeares olde they caſt diuerſe belowe, &amp; the remnant become all of a like ſiſe, &amp; begin in the vpper parte to waxe hollow: after which time it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard to affirme truely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of any horſe when they come to be ten yeares old their teeth then remayning are very hollowe, &amp; their Eyebrowes wax hoary oftentymes and ſome of their teeth ſticke out: but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Horſe wee haue ſpoken ſufficient. Vnder <hi>Mars</hi> alſo is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greedy &amp; rauening Wolfe,<note place="margin">Wolfe.</note> which being bent vpon his pray as he is in his way thitherward, he vſeth al the while to ſmell out extremely in euery part of his body.<note place="margin">Lib. 8. cap. 12.</note> (<hi>Plynie</hi> ſayth) that in tymes paſt euen the very ſight of wolfes in <hi>Italy</hi> was thought to preſage or foreſhewe no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Country. His Tayle the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians</hi> vſed in their loue Medicines. He vſeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> extremity of hunger oftentimes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21445:55"/>to Eate earth. And neuer beſtoweth more time in conioyning with his mate then xii. dayes in the yeare. Vnder the iuriſdiction of <hi>Mars</hi> alſo is the Oxe of both fortes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the wylde Oxe as the Tame. Theſe were firſt yoked and prepared to the vſe of Huſbandry in <hi>Italy,</hi> in ſo much that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians through certayne contempt,<note place="margin">Oxen of vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſte yoked.</note> called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Italians</hi> the Oxes of <hi>Italy.</hi> There are (as <hi>Aelianus</hi> ſayth) ſome of this kinde in <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are without hornes. In <hi>India</hi> there be Oxen ſo ſwift as that they will out run a Horſe. In <hi>Eubaea</hi> all their breede of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en are for the moſt parte white. There be wilde Oxen in <hi>Aethyopia</hi> that moue their hornes to and fro, as our Oxen heere doe their Eares. <hi>Columella</hi> ſayth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt labourers &amp; workmen (as they call them) of theſe, are chiefly bred about <hi>Hetruria,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> which are well knit and ſtronge to laboure.<note place="margin">8ignes of good Oxe</note> And the ſignes of good Oxen be theſe as hee ſayth: a broade and curled forehead, rough and heary Eares, great &amp; black eyes, long hornes, broade &amp; wyde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrells, a broade &amp; wreathed necke, a plenti full and ſofte hyde, a righte out and playne backe, great Hoofes, a long tayle, and of a red, browne, or blacke colour.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:56"/>
               <p>Vnder <hi>Mars</hi> is alſo the wilde Bul which (as <hi>Aelianus</hi> ſaith) be he neuer ſo curſte, fierce or mad he is to be bridled. If a man tyeth or byndeth his right teſticle or ſtone with a lyne to one of his hornes. The firſte that is red to haue cauſed the Bul to haue bene bayted was <hi>Caeſar</hi> the dictator.<note place="margin">Who firſte baited the Bull.</note> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto belongeth alſo the foming Boare, whoſe armory in fighte conſiſteth chyefely in his Tuſkes: as alſo the cruell Beare which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth <hi>Animal omni vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beare.</note> a deuourer of all. And yet is the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male more wood and ſtronger then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> male of this kinde.<note place="margin">Whyte Beare.</note> There is a kynde of whyte beares in <hi>Myſia</hi> ſo infectiue, as that they kyll the dogs put on them, euen only wyth theyr venemous breath. The ſhe beare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth her yonge by little and little with her onely lycking, and hath young at three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes end, at which time ſhe creeping on her backe and ſides, ſtealeth to ſome priuy den that ſhee choſe before to that purpoſe, being very wary leaſt he ſhoulde be ſpyde, and there continueth fourteene dayes lyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge her younge. Then ſhee goeth abroade for fleſhe, and ſuch lyke to ſuſtaine them &amp; her withall. If in this tyme ſhe be found,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21445:56"/>to ſaue her younge ſhe taketh ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on her back, and ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in her mouth and away ſhe getteth her vp into the next Tree. Amongeſt all ſuch Fowles as fly vnto <hi>Mars</hi> belongeth the <hi>Griffron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffon.</note> whych is bred in <hi>India</hi> and hath onely amongſt al other fowles foure feete. It is very bygge and mighty, and hath crooked nayles and clawes after the lyon: he is blacke on hys backe, purple coloured on his forepart, and white winged: his mouth is like the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles</hi> and his eyes fiery, very hard to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but onely when he is younge. He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his Neſt in the highe Mountaines, and encountreth with all kynde of beaſtes except onely the <hi>Lion</hi> and <hi>Elephant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe to <hi>Mars</hi> pertaineth the <hi>Puttock</hi> of al fowles the moſte ſnatching.<note place="margin">Puttock or Kyte.</note> The firſte chaſing of her was by <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the king of <hi>Neapolis,</hi> which put vp a Goſhauke and a Faucon alſo of his at once after her in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apre.<note place="margin">Pye.</note> Alſo the Pye which euery day chatte reth eftſoones chaunging her note, whych was dedicated to <hi>Mars:</hi> Alſo ſuch fowles as are fierce and earneſt of pray, and be of ſhryll voice, as the Kiſtrell or Kaſtell, and the ſhricke owle,<note place="margin">Ovvle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which cryeth or ſhrycketh
<pb facs="tcp:21445:57"/>in ſted of ſonge, as alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other owle which howleth in ſted thereof.<note place="margin">Lapvving.</note> Likewiſe the Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing which maketh her neſt in deſertes in marſhes, and vpon mountaines, buildinge the ſame with mans dunge, to the entent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any man come nigh the ſame he may bee dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> backe by the ſtinke of the ſame. And amonges ſerpents the Dragon holdeth on <hi>Mars</hi> which is of a very ſharpe &amp; fiery eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight:<note place="margin">Dragon.</note> which hath alſo three things in her ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry much deſyred after (ſhe is killed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephant which is alwayes at mortall ſtryfe with her, and ſhe with him) That is to ſay her eyen, her ſkin, &amp; her teeth. Her cies whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhee is ſlayn become precious ſtones called <hi>Draconites,</hi> and are like the fier: her ſkyn is very medecinable: and her teeth are like vnto Boares teeth, but that they be ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and ſerue alſo for ſundry and diuers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, Likewiſe the <hi>Cockatrice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice.</note> whych ſpeedeth ſo wyth her enuenoming, that ſhee beinge in bigneſſe but as much as a mannes hande doth yet not wythſtanding kill all other Serpentes wyth her onely infected &amp; poiſonous breath. And if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmite at her but with a ſticke or ſtaffe, ſhee ſpeedeth him ſo with poyſon as that he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21445:57"/>very ſhortly after. Amonge fiſhes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to <hi>Mars</hi> is <hi>Cephalus</hi> whych breedeth onely in <hi>Ionium</hi> an Iland, and liue moſte vpon mud. So is the fiſhe <hi>Arcanus</hi> a caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. So is the woolfiſh a great deſtroyer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which euer ſwimmeth alone. So is the Mullet fiſh which is called <hi>Trygle</hi> whych breedeth but onely three times in the yere: Of al fiſhes in the ſea a great deuourer, &amp; lyueth much by the fome or froth of the ſea and by the dead bodies and carcaſſes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuch other thinges. So is alſo the pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerell, ſubiected to <hi>Mars.</hi> Among plantes &amp; herbes are pertinent alſo to <hi>Mars,</hi> Ling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Radiſh, Onions, Scammony, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> roote is of a ſtronge ſmell, and his leaſe is three cornered. So is Spurge which clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſtomacke,<note place="margin">Spurge.</note> helpeth to make wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet hurtful to the eyes and raines. So is garlicke which (as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith) is good to gieue ſuch as haue abundance of flegme It being ſtampt with ſalt and rue,<note place="margin">Garlike.</note> or herb grace, and receiued, doth remedy the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of mad dogs: or els layde plaſter wyſe to the ſore place is therefore likewiſe effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. In <hi>Aegypte</hi> there is a kynde of Garlicke which hath but one onely heade,
<pb facs="tcp:21445:58"/>and without cloue as our onions here are, which head is alſo red, ſweete and ſmall. So is alſo Rue, Turnepps, longe rape in ſubiection to <hi>Mars.</hi> And all ſuch as haue their ſtinge or be pryckely or ſharpe-after the manner of a dart, hurting, byting and feſtring with the onely touching of them, as the Thiſtle, Nettle, Quick thorne, and ſuch like. Amonge precions ſtones, <hi>Mars</hi> ruleth ouer the Adamant,<note place="margin">Adam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>at</note> which is ſo ſayd for that he is inuincible and not to be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght vnder wich any force to be made plya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to any vſe of the Lapidary, but onely with Goates blond very warmely applyed vnto it.<note place="margin">Lode ſtone.</note> So is alſo the <hi>Lodeſtone</hi> which as <hi>The ophraſte</hi> ſayth, is of a ſiluer colour. It is digged out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground in <hi>Syphnus</hi> which is aboute three furlonges of from the red ſea. It is eaſy to bee engraued in. This ſtone draweth Iron to it whereſoeuer it be placed, whether on hye or belowe. So is alſo the touchſtone which is of no great quantity and is found in the greate ryuer <hi>Tmolus</hi> in <hi>Armenia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</note> The property of this is to try the fynes of gold and liluer. So is the <hi>Pomesſtone</hi> alſo which commeth of a kinde of fome in the ſea hardened and caſte<note place="margin">Pomes ſtone.</note>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21445:58"/>vp vpon the ſhoare. So is the <hi>Sanguinary</hi> and a certaine kinde of <hi>Ametiſte.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Li. 34. cap. 15.</note> Amongſt Mettals he poſſeſſeth and hath rule in Iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith that it will conſume anone and ruſt away if it bee once put into the fyre,<note place="margin">Iron,</note> &amp; be not already hardened a good with laborous ſtrokes and wel wroughte. There is alſo force of medcine in Iron as it may be vſed: his property is to bind, dry vp and ſtaunche. It ſtaucheth bloude, and helpeth other excrements and is good for the gowt. So hath he alſo the redder braſſe and all other thinges mettal like, whych haue moſt ſtore of the Brimſtone in them. His ſauours are al ſuch as be bitter, ſharp and ſuch as burne and bite the tongue, and which make a man to weepe. Amonge the Elementes he hath moſt right to the fire. His prouinces &amp; dominions are firſt as he is ioyned with <hi>Aries</hi>) <hi>Brittany,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Comuries ſubiected to Mars.</note> 
                  <hi>Fraunce Germany, Barſtany,</hi> the lower moſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Syria, Idumed</hi> and <hi>Iudea</hi> or <hi>Ievvry</hi> And as hee is partaker with <hi>Scorpio</hi> hee holdeth the hyer <hi>Syria, Cappadocia, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritania,</hi> &amp; <hi>Getulia.</hi> He runneth his courſe about the zodiacke in twoo yeres.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Jupiter" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:59"/>
               <head>Of IVPITER the ſixt Planet.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext in place aboue Mars</hi> is <hi>Iupiter,</hi> which te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pereth &amp; allaieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malice of <hi>Mars</hi> &amp; ſiniſter conditions of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</hi> For this <hi>Iupiter</hi> is in his qualities very te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay) hoate &amp; moyſte, &amp; cauſing heate &amp; moyſture. Wherupon he is ſayd to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; worker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sanguine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. For it is proper to bloude to bee hoate and moyſt. Hereupon for ſuch bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite wrought by him, he hath often ben cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Originall Lyfe Planet. And they were wont to draw him forth in the Royal likeneſſe of a Kyng, holding a Scepter or golden Mace in his hande: gieuinge to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande thereby his rule and Empyre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all Creatures lyuing. The Poets af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme him to bee Sonne to <hi>Saturnus,</hi> and <hi>Rhea,</hi> which <hi>Saturne</hi> vnderſtandinge by a Propheſie that it ſhould come to paſſe that his owne Sonnes ſhould thruſt him out of his Kingdome, prouided with him ſelfe to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21445:59"/>ſlea them all as ſoone as euer they ſhoulde be borne. So hee began to deale heerein, firſte wyth <hi>Ceres;</hi> then with <hi>Neptunus</hi> whom he had by the aforeſayd <hi>Rhea.</hi> Who when ſhe perceiued his purpoſe herein, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing great with childe of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of him, ſent him forthwith very pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily into <hi>Lycton</hi> a place of <hi>Creet,</hi> where he was hidden in a Denne: and when <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> came to haue deuoured him alſo, ſhe caſt him a ſtone in ſteede of her childe.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Iupiter</hi> in proceſſe of yeares gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing both into mighte and wealth, expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Father, &amp; deliuered his other Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren from ſuch Thraldome. The Stone which <hi>Saturne</hi> catched in his mouth think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to haue bene his owne Chylde, was deceyued therein, and hee euomitinge the ſame, is yet a Monument ſtill remayning to bee ſeene at this day vpon the high Hill <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Iupiter</hi> by <hi>Proſerpina</hi> had <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> who was called the God of Wynes. And by <hi>Alcumena</hi> hee had <hi>Hercules,</hi> who by <hi>Augaea</hi> Daughter to <hi>Aleus</hi> Kinge of <hi>Arcady</hi> had <hi>Telephus,</hi> which was hid in a wood and nouriſhed vp of a Hart.<note place="margin">Vulcan.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:60"/>
               <p>This <hi>Iupiter</hi> by <hi>Iuno</hi> had <hi>Vulcanus</hi> which for his deformity and ill fauoredneſſe was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrowen of them both into the Iland <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus,</hi> whereas he ſhould make lightninges for <hi>Iupiter:</hi> which <hi>Vulcanus</hi> aſceuding vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on high, and couetinge to ſee the Palace of his Father, going vp higher then he was able to hold on &amp; continue forth, fell downe and brake hys Lymves &amp; Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he halted euer after. So had <hi>Iuditer</hi> by <hi>Minerua</hi> (whom he forced or rauiſhed) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sonne called <hi>Ericthonius,</hi> which was the firſt that inuented and founde oute Carting: of whom <hi>Virgil</hi> ſayth thus:</p>
               <q>Primus Ericthonius currus &amp; quatuor auſus jungere equos.</q>
               <p>and may be Englyſhed thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The firſt that Cart and horſes droue, and drawing did inuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was <hi>Erycthon,</hi> who Ioyned them in Teame for that intent.</l>
               </q>
               <p>THis <hi>Erycthonius</hi> had one <hi>Pandio</hi> to his Sonne which was Kinge of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> who had two Daughters one caſted <hi>Progne</hi> and the other <hi>Philomena:</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21445:60"/>the firſt was maried to <hi>Tereus</hi> Kynge of <hi>Thracia,</hi> who being on a time in his ſiſter <hi>Philon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>aes</hi> company, and entiſing her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide as he though good, forced her agaynſt her will and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent this matter ſhould not be knowen he cut out her tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: which thing neuertheleſſe comming to his wiues Eare, and ſhe takinge greate diſpleaſure the neat, againſt his returne and comming home ſhe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewe his beloued Sonne <hi>Ithys,</hi> and dreſſed him in Meates Banketwiſe, &amp; ſo ſet the ſame before him: whereof he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares of his Sonne, yea of his beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne did feede hungerly. At which ſo great wickedneſſes perpetrated on euery ſide, <hi>Iupiter</hi> being highly offended did firſt chaunge the man into a Lapwing, &amp; <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> his wife he chaunged into a ſwallowe: and <hi>Philomena</hi> into a Nightingale.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Iupiter</hi> alſo and <hi>Taygeta</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Agenor</hi> came <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> who built the City <hi>Lacedemonia:</hi> of him alſo came <hi>Orion</hi> which was a valiaunt champion to <hi>Diana,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orion.</note> and which was ſo huge of body &amp; great. Giantlike, and of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> arrogancy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that he boaſted &amp; craked that he would ſlea all kindes of beaſtes &amp; others, and yet
<pb facs="tcp:21445:61"/>to ſee, he being but ſtinge of a <hi>Scorpion,</hi> &amp; ſerpent of no great hignes, dyed preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And the ſame <hi>Orion</hi> being now tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and ſet vp for a ſigne in heauen by <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter,</hi> doth at this day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer he ſheweth forth to ſaylers and ſhipmen prognoſtycate vnto them litle good to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſue. <hi>Iupiter</hi> alſo by <hi>Europa</hi> had <hi>Mynos,</hi> which raygned in <hi>Creta,</hi> and who had firſt the rule ouer the <hi>Cyclade</hi> Ilandes:<note place="margin">Mynos firſt caugh pyrates.</note> he firſt ſcoured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sea of Pyrates, which in that time abounded ſore. This <hi>Mynos</hi> ſettinge before him the vertuous and commendable lyfe of <hi>Rhada manthus</hi> a moſt iuſt Kynge, to ſhewe that he likewiſe would doe nothinge in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amiſſe, is ſayd to goe and diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into a deepe Den at <hi>Gnoſus</hi> an Ilande of the <hi>Cyclades,</hi> where he receyued whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes at his Father <hi>Iupiters</hi> owne hands. So likewiſe of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Aegina</hi> came <hi>Aeacus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aeacus.</note> which raygned in the Ilande <hi>Oenon,</hi> which afterwards he called <hi>Aegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> after his mothers name: where wiſen as all men died generally of a certayne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame contagion or peſtilence, inſomuch that there was not one man left alius, this <hi>Aeacus</hi> deſired &amp; prayed his father inſtant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that he would turne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Antes or Emets
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21445:61"/>which hee ſawe there into men: which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt being graunted, he afterwardes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them <hi>Myrmidonę:</hi> this <hi>Aeacus</hi> hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third place &amp; accoumpt among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudges. So another ſon of <hi>Iupiter</hi> was <hi>Aeolus,</hi> which raygned in <hi>Sicilia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aeolus.</note> and was lord ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ilands called <hi>Aeoliae:</hi> this <hi>Aeolus</hi> is called the God of Winds, which is alſo ſaid to haue firſt taught &amp; inſtructed the Maryners &amp; ſeafaringe men to knowe and vnderſtand the ſignes &amp; tokens of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts enſuing, as alſo the diſpoſition &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winds: this <hi>Aeolus</hi> begot <hi>Syſiph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who raygned at <hi>Ephora,</hi> which as is ſaid,<note place="margin">Siſiphus</note> being made priuy of the ſecrecy &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of the Gods, playd the parte of a Blab &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed the ſame vnto men, whereat they taking great indignation to puniſhe hym therefore perpetually, haue ſet him in hell to rowle aſtone aſmuch as euer he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wag or moue with al the endeuor he hath, &amp; the ſame moſt laborious buſines of his neuer to ecaſe. So was alſo <hi>Tantalus</hi> ſon to <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> which raygned in <hi>Phrigia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>talus.</note> who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Gods on a time to a feaſt or ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had prepared for them, he in the ſame, hauing ſlaine his ſon <hi>Pelops,</hi> dreſſed and ſod him piecemeale &amp; ſerued him in ſo
<pb facs="tcp:21445:62"/>for an eſpeciall ſeruice: and this hee did to tempt and try their curteſies: at which fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fact they being highly diſpleaſed, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt reſtored <hi>Pelops</hi> agayne to lyfe, &amp; ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together agayne his pieces or ſeuered members, ſauing that his ſhoulders they could not reſtore, for that <hi>Ceres</hi> had eaten it vp: therefore in ſteade of the ſame they made him one of Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry: and <hi>Tantalus</hi> they threwe downe into Hell, &amp; appoynted him an eſpecial place of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for euer, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſtanding vpright in Floudes and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vp to the Chin and aboue and hauing there pleſaunte Apples hanginge ouer his head reaching downe to his vpper Lippe, ſtriueth continually to catche of them into his mouth, to ſuſtayne and relieue hys ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme hunger, &amp; is yet neuer able to come by one byte of them,<note place="margin">Vlyſſes.</note> 
                  <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> alſo is ſayde to diſcend &amp; come of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> vaunting him ſelfe therein: and reckening vp his nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; Progeny ſo againſt <hi>Aiax,</hi> He to keepe him ſelfe ſafe at home, and not to goe with the Grecian Army to lay ſiege to <hi>Troye,</hi> craftely deuiſed with himſelfe to faine him ſelfe mad:<note place="margin">His ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> and to vtter forth ſome ſhewe thereof, he went and ſue ſalt, and went and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21445:62"/>ioyned together at Plough, hee cared not what croſſe kyndes of Cattell, and all to make the Greekes belieue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſtark mad: but deepe diſſemblinge doth by one meanes or other euer bruſt forth, as in this matter: for <hi>Pallamedes</hi> by and by bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame, who layde his ſonne <hi>Telema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> in his way as hee ſhould come w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his Ploughe, to ſee whither he were in deede as hee pretended: but hee percyuing anon his ſonne to lye in his way ſhunned and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chued ſuch a daunger, and ſo diſcloſed his owne counterfayting. But wee are nowe to returne agayne to the Hiſtory of <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> from which by occaſion we haue a litle and yet not very much declined. The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gentils were wont to depicture hym oute in likeneſſe of a Bull, for that as the Poets write,<note place="margin">Europa.</note> when as he rauiſhed <hi>Europa</hi> daughter to <hi>Agenae</hi> King of <hi>Phenicia</hi> hee tranſformed him ſelfe into the likenes of a Bull.<note place="margin">Danae</note> Some alſo vſed to call him <hi>Danaés</hi> for that he broke in by the roofe or top of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe vnto <hi>Danáe,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Acryſius</hi> king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Argyues,</hi> who was cloſe ſhut vp and locked faſt in a ſtrong towre, &amp; hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo vnto her in likenes of a
<pb facs="tcp:21445:63"/>ſhowre of golden Rayne forced her, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat on her <hi>Perſeus,</hi> who was hee that firſt gaue name to the Country and kingdome of <hi>Perſia.</hi> See herein what aſſaultes and what meanes inordinate Loue aſſayeth in oppugning of chaſtity. The <hi>Panims</hi> gaue this <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſoueraygnty in all things: and to purchaſe &amp; obtaine through his meanes as they ſiniſterly thought therein, helpe, &amp; remedy in their calamities and diſtreſſes: they ioyned with his proper name another as it were a ſurname, accordingely as the wayght and nececeſſity of their cauſe driue them vnto: as for example, when they were preiudiced by any man of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe, or by any gueſt,<note place="margin">Iupiter Zenius.</note> they ſtraight wayes ſought to <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Zenius</hi> for remedy. When all truſt &amp; confidence in friendſhip fayled,<note place="margin">Iupiter Philius.</note> they called vpon <hi>Iupiter Philius</hi> to take vengeaunce. When familiars or Companyons betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one another,<note place="margin">Iupiter Heterius.</note> they ſoughte after <hi>Iupiter Heterius.</hi> When kinſfolke and Kinſmen fell to contention, and were together by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eares among themſelues,<note place="margin">Iupiter Homog.</note> to <hi>Iupiter Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moginus:</hi> When thoſe which had taken truce with others, or which were in league brake Truce, and deceyued ech other,<note place="margin">Iupiter Enhorcius.</note> then they had their recourſe to <hi>Iupiter Enhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius.</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21445:63"/>His ſtar is called in Greek <hi>Phaéthon.</hi> And the ſame ſtar of his is ſomewhat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſiluer colour. His houſe is in <hi>Sagita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> &amp; <hi>Piſces:</hi> his Exaltacion or aſcending is in the <hi>15.</hi> of <hi>Cancer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ionyſtes hovv diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</note>Such as are vnder the gouernment of <hi>Iupiter</hi> are outwardely of merry Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and of comely &amp; ſeemely behauiour &amp; geſture: they be alſo louers of clenlineſſe, &amp; ſuch as be fayre ſpeached. Their colour is commonly white, yet ſtayned here &amp; there with ſome red among: their body is well ſet and proportioned, and their ſtature and height is indefferent: they be alſo of thyn haire, of great eyes, and the pupill or ball of their eye exceedeth and is after a black: they bee moreouer of ſhorte Noſe, curled Bearde, and their fore teeth are great and long. And inwardly concerning the frame or qualities of their minde, they be ſtudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, quiet, &amp; well affected towards all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but their loue is ſodaynely got &amp; quickly loſt againe. Moreouer as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly benefits <hi>Iupiter</hi> aduanceth his to great Proſperity, good ſucceſſe, much Riches, high Honoure, and getteth them Fauour and friendſhip in the Worlde, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſaults of their enemies.
<pb facs="tcp:21445:64"/>Amonge bruite beaſtes all ſuch kynds are his whych in pryde of ſtomacke, contende and ſtriue one with another for and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the prerogatiue of their kynde: as the Elephant and Dragon betweene whome there is continuall and deadly diſcorde as they that trauaile the wilderneſſes of <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Elephant &amp; Dragon</note> and <hi>Mauritania</hi> can witneſſe. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dragon and the Elephant in their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting purpoſe the death and deſtruction of ech other. And in theyr firſt ſighte they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice one anothers being. In ſo much that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerpent twyning about the other with the greate length of his body and tayle ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him round aboute, at which deadely ſtrokes, the other extreamely payned doth fall downe to the ground preſently, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waight or force of which fall he both killeth himſelfe or at leaſte wiſe hurteth hymſelfe very grieuouſly, and is thereby in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of dying himſelfe, as alſo he preſently kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Dragon which is ſo wounde and twynde aboute his body, and cruſheth hym all to pieces.<note place="margin">Tyger.</note> So is the <hi>Tyger</hi> alſo ſubiecte to <hi>Iupiter</hi> in that reſpecte that he likewiſe beareth a naturall grudge and moſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall malice to the Horſe. And his ſwiftnes
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21445:64"/>alſo in running is nothing inferiour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others. This kinde is bred moſt often in <hi>Hyrcania</hi> and <hi>India,</hi> a wylde beaſt of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uallous ſwiftenes in running, as alſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with all in the ſame. And the ſmel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> females of this kynde is alſo exceding wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull: For ſo often as ſhee being forth at purueying for her younge, and for her owne pray (for the Male kynd thereof doth neuer a whit regard either her or her yong all this whyle) and in the meane time (as it cannot otherwiſe be) it falleth ſo forth as that if ſhe be robbed of any of her whelpes at her returne home againe to her Den, when ſhe perceiueth that ſhe hath loſt any of her littour; ſhe goeth forth out of her de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by and by, and ſmelleth about which wais theſe ſhould be taken, and after ſhee purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that waies haſtely. And to auoyde the daunger of her which is but preſent death the partye that hath robbed her, being on horſebacke (for one foote he may not be, for he wil then be quickly ouertaken of her) turning one of them downe, muſt yet make away as faſt as euer he can, and not ſtay til he be got on the other ſyde of ſome greate Water, vnto whych place ſhee can not
<pb facs="tcp:21445:65"/>approach, and ſhe in this time makyng af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at the finding of that one ſo caſte in her way, ſeemeth to be ſo glad thereof, as that ſhe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly returneth again with al home and there hauing beſtowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, taketh againe after the other that ſhe miſſeth, and neuer ſtaying till ſhee come at the Water where the robber in paſſing through eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped her fury and reuenge, ſhee ſtandeth at the brym or bankes of the ſame and roreth out very ſtraungely. So is the <hi>Vnicorne</hi> in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vnicor.</note> which is alſo a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and ſore enemy to the Elephant, whych with her one horne whetted and filed vpon ſome flinte, prepareth her ſelfe to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter with him. And alwayes in her fighte ſhee ſtriueth and laboureth very buſily to puſhe at the belly of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Elephant, which ſhe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be the moſt tender place. And as con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning fowles all ſuch kyndes be hys, as are of tender and ſofte meate, and of moſte temperate bodies, As is the Pheaſaunt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Partriche,<note place="margin">Partrich</note> which was ſometimes dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Latona:</hi> Of all fowles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt lecherous: For the cocke Partrirhe doth often deſtroy his mates neſt and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Egges in the ſame, and letteth her of ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21445:65"/>to the intent, ſhee ſhould ſerue him at his lyſte in the acte of Venery. This kynde lightly breedeth and bringeth forth fifteene Egges. And ſitteth but ſeuen dayes &amp; then hatcheth. There is alſo great wylineſſe in in the olde Partryches, for a man ſhall ſee them at ſuch time as any Fawkener or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approacheth nighe vnto their Neſt or place where their younge (not yet rype y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in flight) be contayned and kept to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, the olde Partryches as it were yeelding themſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fawkener &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering him to come nigh vpon him, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by ſuch pollicy they may auert &amp; turne away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parties far of from happening or chauncing vpon their younge, which they knowe are yet inſufficent &amp; vnable to ſhift and prouide for themſelues.<note place="margin">Doues.</note> So is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Doue in ſubiection to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> whoſe kindnes to eche other as they bee matched or Mated together, (as it were in a certaine forme of Wedlocke) euery dayes experience doth teache vs. They aſſiſt buſily and help one another carefully in ſitting: They breede onely two Egs for the moſt parte, firſt the Male, ſecondely the Female. There is no fowle more profitable, or that breedeth oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.
<pb facs="tcp:21445:66"/>For euery ſpringe, ſommer and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumnes Monethes (ſauing the moneth of <hi>Iune</hi> onely excepted, whych is commonly called <hi>Carlocke</hi> moneth at which time they be moſt vnapte and leaſt myndfull of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) they miſſe not in a maner ſo to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in breeding. They do lightly return and repayre home agayne (how far ſoeuer now &amp; then notwithſtanding they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; fly) vnto theyr accuſtomed breeding pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. As experience hereof was tried at the ſiege of <hi>Mutina,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brutus ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a letter by a Doue to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> whereas <hi>Brutus</hi> catching one of them (which vſed and kept about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtell) a good way of, wheras then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of the <hi>Romayne</hi> armie lay, afore he let her goe: he wrot an Epiſtle to them, &amp; faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame about her feet, after ſhe was let goe, ſhe made haſte home againe to the ſayd caſtle her old abyding place, &amp; withal by this ſtraunge meanes and meſſage, the other were made priuy of <hi>Brutus</hi> his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſucceſſe and Affayres. Vnder <hi>Iupiter</hi> alſo are the Plouer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quaile, the Larke, the hen, the Capon. Amonge fiſhes hee cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth great a do in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Dolphin</hi> called <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liotechnos</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe loueth her youg deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">Dolphyn.</note> The female of this kynd hath both milk
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21445:66"/>and breaſtes and geueth her younge ſucke with the ſame. As their younge beginne to learne to ſwim, they ſet them in a ranck or rowe one afore another, and the elder Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins aſwell hee as ſhee, to keepe them in theyr ray or order, do ſwym by them on ech ſide, the other on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide: But as her younge waxe great, this ranke is broken.<note place="margin">Whales.</note> The Whalefiſh is alſo pertinent to <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> This kinde bryngeth forth no ſpawne but a younge fiſh at the firſt, &amp; gieueth her younge mylke. This is very heauy &amp; ſlowe in ſwimminge. The <hi>Indian</hi> Sea is full of theſe which are in quantity and bignes fiue times as big againe as the <hi>Dolphin.</hi> Ouer Trees hee ruleth ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popular tree, the Oke, the wyllow tree, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beeche, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Darnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> tree, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pare &amp; Ipple trees. Likewiſe he requireth the fruite of the Almond tree Date tree: and amonge ſweete leaues and rootes <hi>Mirabolanum, Rheubarbaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</hi> Among herbes he hath Mynt, <hi>Iupiters</hi> beard Sage, Time, He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>locke, <hi>Helica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pane.</hi> Amonge gems or precious ſtones he retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the <hi>Iacinct,</hi> the <hi>Berill,</hi> the <hi>Saphy,</hi> the <hi>Turkys,</hi> the <hi>Emerald,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more duſky kind of <hi>Iaſper,</hi> and all other ſortes whych declyne
<pb facs="tcp:21445:67"/>Among Gemmes or Precious ſtones hee retayneth the Iacinct, the Berill, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir, the Turkys, the Emeralde, the more duſky kinde of Iaſper, and all other ſortes which declyne towardes a duſky or darke colour. In Mettalles he is chiefe maiſter of Tyn,<note place="margin">Tyn.</note> which (as <hi>Plynie</hi> ſayth) being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer layde on ſuch veſſels as are of Braſſe, maketh them ſauour more ſweetely, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth them from ruſting. All wholſome moyſture alſo proceedeth from him, which cauſe good increaſe or nouriſhment in the body. And as concerning the Elements he ruleth &amp; dealeth as him lyſteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ayre. Of Prouinces and Kingdomes,<note place="margin">Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treies ſubiect to Iupiter.</note> he is lord (as he is ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Sagittarius</hi>) ouer <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Celtica, Spayne,</hi> and the higher parte of <hi>Arabia.</hi> And as he partaketh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Piſces,</hi> hee holdeth <hi>Lycia, Lydia, Cylicia, Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylia, Paphlagonia, Naſomania,</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramantye,</hi> or <hi>Caramantica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee runneth ouer the Zodiacke, &amp; end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his courſe therein, in xii. yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Saturn" type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21445:67"/>
               <head>Of SATVRNE the ſeuenth Planet.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ATVRNE is a</hi> Planet cold and dry, maſculine, malicious and hurtfull in many ſuch Effectes as hee worketh: for when he Raygneth, lyghtlye thoſe that bee borne vnder him, either dye ſhortely, liuinge no longe time to accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of, or els if they liue any long time, they haue for the moſt part an heauy and hard fortune. Therevpon for this his pernitious condition of hurting &amp; deſtroying, hee was wont to be ſet out as a Mower or Harueſt man, hauing and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Sythe or Sickle in his hand, as one which by his owne will was fully bent and geuen to accelerate &amp; haſten the ruine and decay of all liuing things; and were it not but that <hi>Iupiter</hi> placed betwixt him &amp; vs, did temperate &amp; bridle him much in his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd heauy qualities, and condicions: nothing here beneath almoſt coulde eyther
<pb facs="tcp:21445:68"/>liue longe, or proſperouſly endure. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue to conſider the vnſpeakable and wonderfull wiſedome of the almighty that as in all other thinges, ſo in this hee hath moſt eſpecially and wiſely prouided: that, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy of life ſo erneſtly labouring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death and decay of all thinges, ſhoulde haue hys place appoynted him there ſo far of from the earth, where all creatures lyuing make their abode, that of all other Planettes he the cruelleſt ſhould be moſt remote &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt of. For how ſhould any creature ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuſtain, help, and defend it ſelf againſt the force of ſuch extreame cruelty: If thys mortall enemy of all were beſtowed &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced any thinge nighe: yea, or any nearer then he is now, to the earth here below, the place of our aboade: yea and how ſhoulde any thynge continue oute his appoynted and determinate Time, if this fearſe and furious harueſtman as it were, euery day labouring to downe with all, were not let and hyndered by other more friendly &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious powers, ſtaying him from ſuch hys force. See therefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of holy writ, and how truely it is there ſayde, God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e perfecte wiſedome hath diſpoſed all
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21445:68"/>things in their iuſt number, meaſure, and waighte. It is not therefore for his owne worthineſſe or dignity that <hi>Saturne</hi> hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt place amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Planets, for his deſerts deſerued: but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other effects &amp; occaſion: as that all things liuing might by that meanes be the further of from ſo frowning, froward, and fatall Foe. He is of a pale and wan co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and diſpoſeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Melancholicke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. This <hi>Saturne</hi> (as the Poets ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) was ſome to <hi>Coelus,</hi> and <hi>Veſta,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saturnus vvhoſe Sonne.</note> as alſo father to <hi>Iupiter, Iuno, Pluto, Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunus, Ceres, Chiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; <hi>Picus.</hi> Of <hi>Iupiter</hi> we haue ſayd befor: <hi>Iuno</hi> was both ſiſter,<note place="margin">His Sons.</note> and afterwards Wyfe to <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuno.</note> The ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſhe women were wont very ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to call vpon her in their time of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile &amp; labour of childe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of <hi>Iuno Lucina.</hi> This <hi>Iuno</hi> had to her Daughter, <hi>Hebe</hi> a luſty gallant, whom <hi>Iuno</hi> made af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwards Cupbearer to <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebe.</note> &amp; beinge very wanton on a time, &amp; forgetfull of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly modeſty, &amp; ſhamefaſtneſſe in a fall y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe had, vncouered her Secrecy, which ſo offended <hi>Iupiter,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iuno,</hi> that ſhe being by and by diſplaced, &amp; turned out of her office.
<pb facs="tcp:21445:69"/>
                  <hi>Ganimedes</hi> a beautifull youth was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to her roome.<note place="margin">Ganime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> 
                  <hi>Pluto</hi> they tearme the God of hel. And <hi>Neptunus</hi> another ſon of <hi>Saturnus,</hi> and <hi>Ops</hi> they make the God of the Sea: And <hi>Ceres</hi> they make the God of Corne,<note place="margin">Chiron.</note> or huſbandry. And <hi>Chiron</hi> the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taure</hi> they ſay was <hi>Saturnus</hi> his ſon alſo by <hi>Phylira</hi> a <hi>Nymphe,</hi> which <hi>Chiron</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came halfe a man, and halfe a horfe, who was brought vp in a den, and there he was taught and learned the arte of medecynes and the vertue of herbes: as alſo he practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed harpe muſicke. And <hi>Picus</hi> the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed ſonne of <hi>Saturne</hi> begat <hi>Faunus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Picus.</note> 
                  <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſhould ſeeme to make this <hi>Picus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to <hi>Circes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Circes.</note> whom by another name he calleth <hi>Martius:</hi> who ſaieth hee falling in loue with <hi>Pompona,</hi> and vſing her compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny greately, thys <hi>Cyrces</hi> his wife gelous ouer hym as ſhee tranſpoſed by incantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diuerſe other thynges ſo ofte as ſhee ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, ſo for anger and reuenge of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhee tourned her huſband <hi>Picus</hi> into a byrd of that name, whych wee commonly with vs vſe to call a <hi>Pye.</hi> The ſtar of thys <hi>Saturnꝰ</hi> in greeke is called <hi>Kronos</hi> which importeth an infinite or vnſpeakable time.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21445:69"/>This time therefore which meaſureth the length of our lyues is called of ſome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yard Wande or Meterod of all wordly doinges and affayres: Wherefore the Dayes, the Howres, the Nights, the Monethes, the Yeares:<note place="margin">Tyme his horſes.</note> all theſe are the Horſes that draw tyme forwarde, and continue time in hys courſe. The Howres being ſpente euen by litle, &amp; lytle, doe yet helpe forwarde tyme apace. Euery howre of the Day though of it ſelfe ſuppoſed but a ſhort time, is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtanding to bee employed to ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable vſe or exercyſe, that wee may ſay wee haue beſtowed not ſo much as one howre vnfruitefully. As in tymes paſte our auncyent Elders conſydering the loſſe of tyme, euen of an Howre: did therefore regarde howe they ſpente euery Howre moſt carefully and buſily. <hi>Martialis</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Romaynes</hi> aſſigned to euery hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the day aſeuerall kynde of exercyſe. The firſt to the ſeruice of God,<note place="margin">The day hovv ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the old Romaines</note> and to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: the ſeconde to ſalutation by bidding god morrowe, and vſing other friendly confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: the thyrde and fourth they addicted to the hearing and pleadyng of common wealth matters, the fyfth to bodily exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:21445:70"/>and laboures: the ſixt &amp; ſeuenth to take their former repaſt and eaſe: the eight they applyed to fence play, trying of Maſteries, and martial affayres: and after this the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſidue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day in his aſſigned howres was employed to the inuention or finding forth of ſuch profitable artes or wayes, as which furthered and enryched both the ſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, as alſo the caſe and condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euery priuate perſon.<note place="margin">The dayes accompt differeth.</note> But the dayes accoumpt is not a like in all places &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes: for ſome recken it to bee a day from ſunne riſing to ſunne riſing, as the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians:</hi> ſome from Sun ſet to Sunſet, as the <hi>Athenians:</hi> ſome from noone to noone, as the <hi>Vmbrians:</hi> ſome from the Sun ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Sun ſet, as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon People here with vs: ſome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Midnight to Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Aegyptians:</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dyall which declareth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cleare ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny day howe euery houre eſcapeth &amp; paſſeth away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, was firſt founde out by <hi>Anaximenes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dyall of vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt found out</note> Scholler to <hi>Anaximander,</hi> who was the firſte that ſhewed the Experience thereof in <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia:</hi> and <hi>Papyrius</hi> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt lykewiſe that broughte the ſame into <hi>Rome:</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21445:70"/>of this, being led hereto by occaſion of time. Some are in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> opinion, that this Planet <hi>Saturnus</hi> is ſo called, <hi>quaſiſe ſatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raret annis,</hi> for that in his courſe or circuit going, hee hath yeares and time fully. His houſe is in <hi>Capricornus,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius:</hi> And his Exaltation or Aſcendent is in the <hi>21.</hi> of <hi>Libra.</hi> Such as are borne vnder <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> commonly called <hi>Saturnyſtes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saturnyſts hovv diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</note> are lumpiſh, heauy, and ſad, dull witted, full of Melancholy, hard &amp; ſtraunge, a long time to receiue vnderſtandinge and learninge, but yet after they haue once with much a doe apprehended and taken the ſame, they after become faſt Keepers and Retayners thereof: whereupon there is this difference betwixt the <hi>Mercurialyſts</hi> and theſe, that as the firſt doe quickly and redely receiue and take, that whych is red and delyuered vnto them, but are on the other ſide ſoone forgetfull.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Saturnyſts</hi> are commonly hard to learne, but ſure in that which they haue once obtayned. As that Seale doth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Imprinte and keepe his Marke which Sealeth in Waxe, and ſo forth: then that
<pb facs="tcp:21445:71"/>which is beſtowed vpon Water, which ſoone receiueth the marke thereof, &amp; ſoone leeſeth the ſame. The greateſt deſire of the <hi>Saturniſtes</hi> alſo, is for the moſt part to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe them ſelues to become ſole or ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in theyr life,<note place="margin">Saturniſts gemen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olitarines</note> and to allow of the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eſtate or condition chyefly. Their Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomy is altogether blockiſh, their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce cruell and ſtronge, theyr head ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging downe, theyr eyes euer bent and caſte vpon the ground. Theyr property is ſuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be euer almoſt either muſing or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. And in their ſleepe they are much troubled: For they dreame oftentimes that they be buried aliue &amp; put into the earth quycke, or elſe they dreame of deade men, &amp; thynke they ſee ſuch ſights which make them aſtoniſhed, and to cry out in theyr ſleepe, as when they dreame of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils which they do often, and of hel, and hel fier, and of cruell perſecution and tyrannye and ſuch like.<note place="margin">Their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſpoſitions.</note> All which and far many moe horible cogitations, do often aſſault y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholike co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexioned men. The outward notes and ſignes of theſe men be, they bee for the moſt part of a browne colour, hard, heary &amp; rough ſkynned. Their faces leane,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21445:71"/>warped or wrynkled much: theyr vaynes greatly diſtented and puffed vp: they are al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo of hye browes thicke lyppes. And as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſpoſition of theyr minde, they be naturally gieuen to deceipte, to ſeduce &amp; to bryng the ſimple people into falſe belief: to feare and fray, and oftentimes to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and flea: to conſume and pine away within themſelues through wrath, ire and cancred malice: They are alſo very ready and prone to ciuill diſſention and diſcorde. They be alſo for the moſt part ſhorte lifed, becauſe the exceeding cold in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of their Dayes, as we ſee it cometh to paſſe in old men, which through coldnes of nature are chopte vp of a ſodaine: for olde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they grow on towards death becom very colde and dry, all heate and moyſture wyhch are the preſeruatiues of Lyfe then forſakyng them and bidding them farewel. Whereupon it followeth, that theſe qualy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Saturnus,</hi> that is colde and dryneſſe are the very hie wayes, Meſſengers, &amp; Har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bengours of death, and ennemies vnto life. Whereupon thys kinde of complexyoned men can not endure longe, which lacke the mayntenaunce and nurſerye of the vittayſe
<pb facs="tcp:21445:72"/>and lyfe qualities. The <hi>Saturniſtes</hi> alſo are gieuen to great ſadnes,<note place="margin">Their ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> becauſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withoute hope of good ſuceſſe: in ſuch thynges as they deſire, whych are lightely difficulte: they doe deſcende into a certayns kinde of deſperation thereof,<note place="margin">Their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne daunger. Clynias Achilles</note> wythin them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe lues. And they alſo are gieuen to bee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely moued and angred, as was <hi>Clyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> And <hi>Achilles,</hi> which both, to helpe themſelues of this ſore and ſickenes: vſed, before they would either eate or drink to expell and baniſh from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this inward ennemy of theyr ſoule or mynde, with gye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng theyr endeuours wholy to ſome kind of muſicke.<note place="margin">The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ende of life.</note> And ſolitarynes is a great part of their deſire, and the pryuate kind of life: as Experience gaue forth in the Dayes of <hi>Diocletianus</hi> and <hi>Maximinianus</hi> Noble Prynces or Emperours:<note place="margin">Diocletia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus and Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus.</note> which forſakying theyr royall roomes and publique, &amp; pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely preheminence: for to obtayne a quyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lyfe, which they hoped to haue in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empting themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worldly affaires, gaue ouer all.<note place="margin">Hiero. Amura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</note> So did <hi>Hiero</hi> the tyraunt of <hi>Syracula.</hi> So dyd <hi>Amurathes</hi> the Turke, and <hi>Otomanus</hi> the Father of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> whych won <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> reſigning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21445:72"/>hys ſome hys roome and charge. So did <hi>Lotarius</hi> nephewe to Charles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great,<note place="margin">Lotarius</note> and many <hi>Venetian</hi> Lordes and Dukes, So did <hi>Ierome, Petrus Diamanus, Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> forſaking the world, they betoke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to ſolitarynes of life. For by that meanes they imagined that they ſhoulde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more eaſely come to the quiet porte or Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of ſcience and ſpeculation. Such an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Timon</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Timon.</note> for ſolitarines of lyfe, but not to a like ende: for the other for deſyre onely of knowledge in heauenly thinges ſeparated themſelues from the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men, but this other through a way wardnes and crokednes of nature, abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſhunned all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s companies. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the field <hi>Atticus</hi> he got him a Den and was gladdeſt when he was furtheſt of from the ſight of al men. Inſomuch that on a time a very friende of his called <hi>Peantus</hi> brynging with him great prouiſion purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing to make merry with this <hi>Timon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Peantus</note> and ieſting with him, and queſtioning how hee fared, and how hee liked of that Banque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: Mary very well (quoth he) but I ſhoulde fare and like better if <hi>Pea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus</hi> were away.
<pb facs="tcp:21445:73"/>Then the which ſpeach, what coulde haue bene more hoggiſhly or ſwyniſhly:<note place="margin">Heraclitus</note> Such another was <hi>Heraclitus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Epheſian</hi> which miſliking mens company dwelled in caues of the earth, and in Mountaynes and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in Wilderneſſes, lyued with Rootes, Herbes &amp; Water. Such another alſo was <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who for his doggiſh conditions was called a <hi>Cynicke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note> hee abode alone in <hi>Cranium</hi> without <hi>Corynthe,</hi> harboured in a Tunne in ſteade of a houſe. In like ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rt did <hi>Theon</hi> &amp; <hi>Arſentus,</hi> but theſe two choſe out ſolitarye places to auoid much corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of lyfe,<note place="margin">Theon. Arſenius.</note> which they ſawe in thoſe daies abound euery where. But of theſe ſolitary perſons, Melancholicke men, and very <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turniſtes:</hi> we haue per aduenture ſaid ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, &amp; more then inough. We are nowe to reuerte to the other effectes of <hi>Saturne</hi> ſeene and experyenced, in the Inferiour &amp; baſer kyndes of Creatures. And to come nexte vnto bruite beaſtes, all ſuch kynds be proper vnto hym whych bee of lumpiſhe &amp; ſluggyſhe Nature, and ſlowe to dryue: As the Aſſe whych chyefely breedeth in <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and nowe alſo aboute <hi>Reate</hi> in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> as alſo in <hi>Betica</hi> and throughoute
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21445:73"/>all <hi>Lybia</hi> they goe to Plough onely with theſe,<note place="margin">Aſſe.</note> and vſe them to all other intentes of huſbandry. They refuſe no burdens bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whileſt their Backes breake. With y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mylke of the ſhe Aſſes, as <hi>Tranquillus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porteth <hi>Poppea, Neroes</hi> Wyfe made her ſkin very cleare and fayre: yet in <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania</hi> in the forreſts there are wield Aſſes called <hi>Onagri</hi> ſo ſwyft in ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning that they cannot bee catcht vntill they haue runned themſelues out of breath.<note place="margin">Onagri.</note> Hetherto alſo belongeth the Mule which breedeth in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> through the coniunction of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilde aſſe and Mare.<note place="margin">Mule.</note> Theſe be moſt what of browne colour, and very ſwift. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Monuments of the <hi>Athenians</hi> it is remembred that one of theſe lyued foure ſcore yeares. Under <hi>Saturnus</hi> is the Camell alſo,<note place="margin">Camell.</note> both that of <hi>Bactria,</hi> and the other of <hi>Arabia.</hi> The firſt ſorte hath two Kybes on his Backe, and this laſt hath but one. And as they haue ſuch like vpon their breaſtes, vpon which they reſt and ſtay theyr Bodies ſo often as they lye downe. The Females haue foure Teates euen as our Kyne here haue, and their Tayle is like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſſes tayle. They beate mortall &amp; deadly ſpight to the horſe.
<pb facs="tcp:21445:74"/>They neuer drinke but firſt they trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water before w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their feete. <hi>Aelianus</hi> ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are of this kinde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liue <hi>50.</hi> yeares. Theſe chiefly of all other foure footed bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes at ſuch times as they minde going to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, ſeeke firſt after ſome ſecret or hid corner or place wherethey cannot be ſeene. Vnder <hi>Saturnus</hi> alſo are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goates which as they waxe fat,<note place="margin">Goates.</note> ſo doe they leaue bearing and waxe barrayne. They goe with their younge <hi>5.</hi> monethes, as Ewes doe: &amp; they haue <hi>4.</hi> at once ſometimes, but ſeldome. Till they be <hi>3.</hi> yeare olde they beare not, &amp; likewiſe when they waxe olde, they waxe barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they breede till they be <hi>8.</hi> yeare old. They ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe ſee as clerely in the night as in the day time. Looke what trees they bark they die forthwith. And if they licke but vppon the Olyue tree they cauſe it to leaue bearing. Vnder <hi>Saturn</hi> alſo for her ſolitarines is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hare,<note place="margin">Hare.</note> aſwell thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breed about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Alpes</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; which bee cleane white, liuing as they report in the wyuter Moueths w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Snowe, as alſo oures which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue alone in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fieldes, chaunging their formes wherein they ſquat &amp; keepe, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they liſt. They ſleepe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their Eyes open, wanting Eye lids. They are ſtill &amp;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21445:74"/>ſet at reſt in the day time, &amp; ſtray abroade for their reliefe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night time. The fielde Hares are the ſmalleſt &amp; ſwifteſt of foote. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hill &amp; Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Hares are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt &amp; leſſe ſwift. The experience of their ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſheweth forth in then forefeete, which the leſſer &amp; ſmaller they be ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more do they exceede and excell in their pace. In theyr courſing they apply their eares faſt &amp; flat to their backes. They vſe to beguile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dogs oftentimes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> courſes in &amp; out, &amp; flex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous turning. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe hath yonge ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abroad &amp; hideth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places, thinking by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes to keepe and preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from finding out. If ſhee chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth at any time to happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for, ſhee ſtriueth to eſcape him by ſwift flight. But he matcheth her ſhift with ſubtilty &amp; flynes: For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe he giueth her ouer and reſteth himſelfe,<note place="margin">Foxe.</note> &amp; being freſh againe to follow after her, ſeketh after her foring, which bringeth him directly to her forme. The age of Hares is well coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by certayn ſundry poares or holes that they vſe to haue in their bodies as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to waxe olde. Among ſerpents <hi>Saturn</hi> poſſeſſet thoſe that bee of moſt deadly Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome,
<pb facs="tcp:21445:75"/>and Naturally gieuen to deſtroy: as the Adder,<note place="margin">Adder.</note> which as <hi>S. Ierome</hi> in his Epiſtles ſayth, is ſo full of poyſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when ſhe goeth any where to drinke, ſhe is fayne to lay aſide her poiſon till ſhe returneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, for feare of bruſting. So is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent <hi>Ichneumon</hi> which is continually at hatred with the Aſpe,<note place="margin">Ichneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> and laboureth day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to finde out the <hi>Aſpes</hi> Neſt to deſtroye her Egges, whereby ſhee knoweth howe greatly ſhe hindreth the Succeſſion or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of her deadly Ennemies. Amonge fowles hee chalengeth the <hi>Eſtriche</hi> which feedeth oftentimes vpon Iron: alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licane</hi> which lyueth ſolitarely &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,<note place="margin">Pellicane.</note> which reſorteth much to the Sea coſtes &amp; there catching ſhelfiſhes, after ſhe hath deuoured them ſhe per braketh them vp agayne to the entent ſhee may the more eaſly breake their Shelles &amp; come by the meate. The Swan alſo ſolitary in her life, and merry at her death,<note place="margin">Svvan.</note> ſo reioyſinge in hope to be ſhortly with her beloued <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> (as ſayth <hi>Plato</hi>) ſeemeth alſo to be one of this number. Amonge Trees <hi>Saturne</hi> holdeth the Mulbery tree which is longe ere it waxeth olde,<note place="margin">Mulbery tree.</note> and is counted of <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21445:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>the wiſeſt tree of all, for that hee laſt of all others putteth forth his Buds &amp; bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ewetree is of this number,<note place="margin">Evvetree.</note> whoſe leaſe is like the Fyrtree, and whoſe Barke is like the Cedar: If any Catrell bite of the rootes of the Ewe tree they die preſently. Among hear vs he holdeth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>try, which hath almoſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taſte of Time. And Heniwcke, with which, &amp; with fleſhe intermedled together, Hunters in diuerſe places deſtroy and kit Wolues.<note place="margin">Rhodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daphne.</note> And <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dodaphne,</hi> which beinge taken inwardly poyſoneth, and vſed onely outwardely is ſufferayne in many Medicines.<note place="margin">Plyn. lib. 36. cap. 17.</note> Amonge precious ſtones <hi>Saturne</hi> hath the ſtone cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sarcophagus</hi> which beinge put to the bodies of dead men and ſuffred to continue ſo but the ſpace of fourty dayes,<note place="margin">Sarcopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</note> it eateth vp all the whole Carkaſe, leauing nothing but the teeth onely. It ſhoulde ſeeme that there bee at this preſent in <hi>Lycia</hi> ſome of theſe kindes of ſtones, which being faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them that bee alyue, doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>awe and conſume away their fleſhe. Contrary to this is the ſtone <hi>Chernites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chernites</note> which is found in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and is a perpetuall preſeruer of the bodies of men whether they be aliue or
<pb facs="tcp:21445:76"/>deade. In ſuch a ſtone was the body of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> the king of <hi>Perſia</hi> ſapped and layed at his funerall, and buriall: which kept hys body ſafe from conſuming away many hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares. Heatherto alſo belongeth the <hi>Chalazy</hi> which is both of the colour, and figure of hayle.<note place="margin">Chalazye</note> And is the hardnes, of the Adamant: This being put neuer ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or long in the fier, waxeth neuer the warmer or whotter, but continueth ſtill as colde as yſe. Subiect alſo to <hi>Saturnus</hi> is the ſtone <hi>Galactites</hi> which is of a milkie coloure:<note place="margin">Galactites</note> this being beate into, powder and mixt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> water, and ſo app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to the noſthrilles of ſheepe fetcheth their mylke agayne after it is dryed vp.<note place="margin">Elaphoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratites.</note> So is <hi>Elaphoceratites</hi> which is like to Harts horne. This being ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt or beaten into Powder and intermedled with oyle, and ſo layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any part or place of the body which is become bare or balde, doth helpe in very ſhorte time to fetch the hayre againe.<note place="margin">Galazite</note> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> is the <hi>Galazite</hi> that dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth from the Ague: Alſo amonge Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals <hi>Saturne</hi> hath a do with Ledde which is of two kinds that is to ſay white ledde &amp; blacke:<note place="margin">Leadde.</note> one of them wil not be adglutina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted or ioyned to any other thinge, without
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21445:76"/>the commixture of another. Wherefore when they ſoder any thinges both theſe do concur together thereto. The white is the beſt. In Medicines y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of Lead is great: for it helpeth to repreſſe maimes, or ſcars, and being applied to the Loynes and nigh vnto the Kidneyes in thynne Plates, or Leafes, with his exceeding coldnes it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiteth (as <hi>Plynie</hi> ſaith) the burning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and immoderate luſt of <hi>Venus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 34. Cap. 18.</note> With ſuch kinde of prouiſion did <hi>Caluus</hi> the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator,<note place="margin">Caluus.</note> burninge greatly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire of Luſt and fleſhly Concupiſcence, aſſwage and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the rage of his intemperate deſire. And being vſed alſo in ſuch order as after thinne beaten Plates or Leafe wyſe, and put next the Breaſt it cleareth the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, and maketh it more apt to ſinge out clearely.<note place="margin">Nero.</note> And ſo did <hi>Nero</hi> vſe to doe to make his Voyce and Breaſt pleaſaunt. Amonge the Elementes <hi>Saturne</hi> hath moſt a doe with the Earth whoſe Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are alſo after the maner of <hi>Saturnus,</hi> that is moſt colde and drye:<note place="margin">Earth.</note> which Earth the Phyloſophers not wythoute greate cauſe called the Nourſe or Graunde Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all Lyuinge thinges here with vs,
<pb facs="tcp:21445:77"/>for that ſhe conceyued and brought forth ſo many diſtinct and diuers kindes of things as make nowe to the enriching and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the whole Worlde. And as the Earth ſerueth to bring forth ſuch variety of fruites and prouiſion, as wherewithall al thinges lyuing are richly ſuſtayned: ſo doe all other things in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Worlde by Gods ſpeciall apoyntment ſerue to the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and vſe of Mankinde, whom God hath made Lord and maiſter of all. So that the Fyre (as ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi>) which ſerueth to heate and to geue light:<note place="margin">Lib. de I ra Dei. cap. 13.</note> the Fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynes which out of the Earth and ſides of hylles gieue forth water: the floudes which wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our grounds: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hilles that bring forth Vynes &amp; other deliciouſe kindes of fruite: the Fennes, and Mariſhes, which bringe forth Reede &amp; Sedge: the ſea which both ſtoreth vs with variety of Fiſhes, as alſo ſerueth to the paſſage of Marchauntmen, and marchaundize: the Suu which altreth and chaungeth the times and ſeaſons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare: the Moone who is a Guide and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour in the darke night, and alſo a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſher of the yeare into ſeuerall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths: the ſtarres which ſerue greatly to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21445:77"/>the trauayling of the ſea faringe men: the windes which preſerueth the Ayre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: all theſe, as all thinges els which the Earth produceth of her ſelf any wayes beneficially (which are Infinite) ſerue all to the commodity, behofe, and vſe of Man. And yet is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earth (albeit it is ſo rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniſhed and great withall and vnmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable) any wayes as big in quantity,<note place="margin">Starres o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vvhat big<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> as is the leaſt ſtar in the firmament, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians</hi> be to be credited, for they ſay that the Earth is eighteene times leſſe then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt ſtar there.<note place="margin">The earth leſſe then the ſtarre hovv much.</note> To the deeper conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion whereof (becauſe this thing can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinke in our ſenſes) we are to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that after the mindes of <hi>Ptholomeus, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraganus,</hi> &amp; others expert <hi>Aſtronomers.</hi> The ſtars of the firmament are diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed into ſixe ſundry differences or degrees of Magnitude &amp; greatnes.<note place="margin">Stars are of ſixe degrees.</note> In the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of quantity or bigneſſe there are <hi>16.</hi> in number whereof euery one is bigger then the whole Earth <hi>107.</hi> times.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Of the ſecond ſyſe or bigneſſe are <hi>45.</hi> in number, whereof euery one is bigger then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth <hi>90.</hi> times.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third ſorte which exceede in quantity are <hi>208.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and they are all big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:21445:78"/>then the Earth by threeſcore &amp; twelue times.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Of the fourth ſyſe are <hi>264</hi> and all of them greater then the Earth by <hi>54.</hi> times. In the fifte degree of greatnes are <hi>217.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and euery one of them bigger then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earth <hi>35.</hi> times. In the ſixt degree of big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes are <hi>249.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſtars, and euery one of them greater then the Earth <hi>18.</hi> times. And all theſe are the leaſt that are ſeene and haue bene diligently obſerued &amp; marked of the <hi>Aſtrologians:</hi> Whereupon <hi>Alphraganus</hi> concludeth that the leaſt ſtar which we ſee is a great way bigger then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole earth. O miſerable men therefore that make ſo much of a Moate, of a Center, or Poynte, of a Pryſon: all which names y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth hath in reſpecte of the higher Heauens, and to care ſo litle for the Poſſeſſion of Heauen, where as is no circumſcription of Place, nor meaſure of Time, nor friuolous Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Ioy, but all places there infinite and Immenſurable, and conſuming tyme quite baniſhed, and the Pleaſures that bee there be endleſſe, and very glorious. The vertue of the Earth in all bodies compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is to fortifie them and to make them dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and faſt. Whereupon the ſolidity or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21445:78"/>ſoundnes of euery mixt thinge is deriued and fetched from this Element.<note place="margin">Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes vvhereof they come</note> Yea and Earthquakes alſo, which come vpon a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and force of ſome ſore windes pent vp and ſcanted, or denied of their free courſe within the Entrailes or body of the earth, by ſuch his ſounde or forcible reſiſtaunce, procure oftentimes greate diſtruction and decay to whole Cities, Townes, &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes. As in the time of <hi>Seneca</hi> a greate part of the Towne <hi>Herculana,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hercula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis &amp;c. Ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vven vvith Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</note> as alſo the City <hi>Neapolis,</hi> and certayne cities of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pania</hi> were ouerthrowen. In <hi>Lybia</hi> there was ſo ſore and horrible an Earthquake, that an hundred Cities at one time were decayed therewith.<note place="margin">Lib. de mirabili ſacrę ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turae. What a ſore earth quakevvas in Thracia and Bythi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nia at Chriſtes death. 13. Cities in Aſia de ſtroyed vvith one Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</note> And <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that at the very inſtant of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion there was ſuch a ſore Earthquake, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the ſame there were Eleuen whole Cities in <hi>Thracia</hi> ſubuerted. And in <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinia</hi> at the ſame time, almoſt all the hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes there were ouerthrowen. In the <hi>20.</hi> yeare next after <hi>Chriſts</hi> Paſſion there fell downe with an Earthquake <hi>13.</hi> famous ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>Aſia</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>Eplieſus, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſia, Ceſarea, Philadelphia, Sardis, Moſt hene, Megaethytra, Hymmolus, Themis, Myrrhina, Cumae, Apollonia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Diahir.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21445:79"/>In the <hi>66.</hi> yeare after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Chriſte, three other famous Cities were ſunke in <hi>Aſia</hi> by an Earthquake,<note place="margin">Cities ſunk here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith in the yeare-of Chtiſte 66. The yeare 79.107.</note> namely <hi>Laodicia, Hierapolis,</hi> and <hi>Coloſſa,</hi> and great wars afterwarde happened throughout all the countrey. In the <hi>79.</hi> yeare three Cyties in <hi>Cyprus.</hi> In the <hi>107.4.</hi> Cytyes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>Aſia, Elea, Myrrhina, Pytanae,</hi> &amp; Cume; and two in <hi>Greece, Opuntys,</hi> and <hi>Orita:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">116.</note> And in the <hi>116.</hi> yeare, almoſt all <hi>Antioche</hi> peariſhed with an Earthquake. In the <hi>373.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">373.</note> all <hi>Nicea</hi> almoſte was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen with the ſame. In the <hi>557.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">557.</note> yeare <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> whole <hi>10.</hi> dayes together was ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> horribly, inſomuch that a great deale of the buildinges there fell downe, &amp; much people was ſtayne. In the <hi>829.</hi> yere throughout <hi>Germany,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">8 29.</note> and <hi>Fraunce</hi> there happened ſuch an Earthquake, &amp; ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and ſore a Tempeſt withall, that it ouerthrew great and lofty trees, &amp; ſhooke and ouerturned very ſtronge and mighty buildinges.<note place="margin">Witzburg 841.</note> In the <hi>841.</hi> yeare, <hi>Witzburge</hi> trembled <hi>20.</hi> times one after another, and deſtroied many people and much building. In the <hi>855.</hi> yeare <hi>Moguntia</hi> tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled ſore,<note place="margin">855.</note> and a Church there of <hi>S. Vrbane</hi> with the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21445:79"/>terror and trembling thereof fell downe quite. At which time many Cyties alſo &amp; great Turrets, and Caſtels in <hi>Germany</hi> were likewiſe ouerthrowen. In the <hi>1120.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1120,</hi> Fyer bruſt out vvith an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</note> yeare there braſt forth out of the Earth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an Earthquake certaine flames or lightes of fyre, by which many were ſodenly ſlain. And what ſhall I ſay of <hi>Baſile?</hi> which how often it hath ben decayed by Earthquakes I cannot nowe ſtande to recite. And euer lightly before ſuch effects of Earthquakes there went before as tokens thereof great drowghts, or els continuall &amp; ſore rayne, dryings vp of Fountaynes, the light<note n="*" place="margin">Signes of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes to follovve.</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne in the Sommer time greately ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured by Blacke and darke Clowdes, or els with Clowdes of red and fyery colour, and whirle windes, and boyſterous rough windes rending trees a ſunder, or els tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their rootes vpward, &amp; fyery flames running alonge in the Element, &amp; ſtraung aſpect of ſtars, calme Ayre, and alſo great and groſſe exhalations, &amp; vapors breathing forth fulſomly from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, and the heauy aſpect of <hi>Saturne,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mars.</hi> Theſe ſignes haue bene alwayes, and are yet for the moſt parte Prognoſticators of
<pb facs="tcp:21445:80"/>Earthquakes to inſewe. The Places, or Countreys which are moſt ſubiect to theſe are ſuch as be nighe to the ſea, and chiefly where there hee many Fens, and hollowe ventes of running Waters, as likewiſe in hilly Countryes. For about the <hi>Alpes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Appenninum, Plynie</hi> himſelf is Witneſſe that he hath experienced and perceiued ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tremblings &amp; quakings of the Earth.<note place="margin">Times na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally apt for Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</note> The times which bee Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally meeteſt for Earthquakes is the Spring time &amp; Autumne, and very ſeldom or neuer in the Winter time. And when they happen it is oftner in the night, then in the day time: and the greateſt and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribleſt that ſo happeneth is in or about the night, and is not longe before the Sunſet, or els it happeneth a litle before the Sun ryſing.<note place="margin">Cap. 82.2. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral kindes of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</note> 
                  <hi>Plynie</hi> in his ſecond booke maketh two kindes, or differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of Earthquakes. One, which is the eaſieſt, and which doth leaſt hurt or harme: which is as it were a ſofty or right vp ſhaking,<note place="margin">This Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration happened in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Anno. Chriſti 1580. 6. A.</note> with the Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers called a <hi>Vibration</hi> which lyfteth lifteth vp buildinges and houſes bending, ſhaking, and bowing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his vpright force and trembling at their higheſt or top.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21445:80"/>And ſuch a kinde of Earthquake happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned here in <hi>England</hi> vppon Eaſter Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare of Chriſte <hi>1580.</hi> aboute vi. of the Clocke in the euening, <hi>Viz</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill:</hi> which heaued vp waters, hills, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Caſtels, with ſuch thinges as were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in them, ſo burſting forth &amp; break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out in ſuch fauorable ſorte, as that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry title harme (the Lord be thanked there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) happened within theſe Countreyes heere aboute vs. Which kinde of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake was a very <hi>Vybration</hi> or a ſhaking of Gods ſharpe and ſeuere Rod agaynſte vs for the rottenneſſe of our ſinnes: yet in ſuch mercifull order that vpon proofe, and tryall of our amendment hee ſpared vs at that time fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinking &amp; quite ſubuertinge vs, which thinge our wickedneſſe had tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly deſerued. God graunt the ſame clemency of our moſt merciful father may dryue and drawe vs now at the laſt to take heede to our ſelues, leaſt that greater ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaunce enſuing doth not ouertake vs. The ſecond kinde of Earthquake which is a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inous ruſhing together of all,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Succuſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Inclina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> and of <hi>Peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidonius</hi> called <hi>Succuſsio,</hi> or <hi>Inclinatio,</hi> is more perilous and daungerous.</p>
               <p>For in this Earthquake Howſes that
<pb facs="tcp:21445:81"/>be farre diſtant are toſt and caſt vp one to another, and one vpon another; and in the ſame, Walles, Houſes, Hilles, Caſtelles, Floudes, Ryuers, great parts and pieces of Countreyes are ſodaynely ſoopte away quite: yea, &amp; of this ſecond kinde of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake called a <hi>Concuſsion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A ſtraung Concuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge.</note> there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that property that runninge vp and downe within the Earthes incloſure, and there boyling like a ſeething Pot or ſeeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water, at the length it breaketh forth and doth wonderfull harme. As it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Fryburge</hi> in <hi>Briſgoia,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſte <hi>1509.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ann. 1509</note> Some called this kynde of <hi>Concuſsion Braſteis.</hi> There is another kinde of <hi>Concuſsion</hi> or daungerous earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake called <hi>Hiatus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Braſteis.</note> a gaſping, or gaping as when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forcible matter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in is driuen to part &amp; ſunder itſelf, with which kinde of Earthquake the Citty <hi>Cyllene</hi> (as ſayth <hi>Plutarch</hi>) was ſundred and rent a two in the dayes of <hi>Mydas</hi> the king: and ſo was the countrey <hi>Lyguſtus</hi> afterwards with the ſame. Alſo of this, there is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde called <hi>Ruptor</hi> a burſter,<note place="margin">Ruptor.</note> which burſteth the Earth in twaine, and ſwelleth the ſame, and puffeth it vp like a hill, with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21445:81"/>which the Ilande <hi>Hiera,</hi> as alſo the City <hi>Heraclea</hi> in <hi>Pontus</hi> was wonderfully toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and tumbled. Then is there another kinde of <hi>Concuſsion</hi> called <hi>Truſor</hi> a thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting earthquake which with violent force thruſteth vp all that is in his way as it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">Truſor</note> remoouing and bearinge all vp on the to ſide. Then is there another kinde called <hi>Mugitus</hi> which is after alowing Noyſe, which with his ſtronge lowing ſound ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Grounde:<note place="margin">Mugitus.</note> which ſometimes alſo ſoundeth without ſhaking, as when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof is more weake, but yet it ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and ſtrugleth within and laboureth to get out at the Earthes hollowneſſe. And theſe kindes of Earthquakes as they haue naturall cauſes, ſo haue they their names accordingly. But there haue bene other Earthquakes which beinge without ſuch cauſes, and onely and meerely procured &amp; cauſed by Gods mighty Prouidence very Miraculouſly,<note place="margin">Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</note> may worthely be called ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall &amp; miraculous. As was when <hi>Peter</hi> was deliuered out of Pryſon: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was moſt ſtraunge in deede:<note place="margin">Act. 16.</note> firſte by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the time, for it was at midnight: and the other are only in the euening and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:
<pb facs="tcp:21445:82"/>ſecondly they differ in forme or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: for this ſhooke the foundations only of the Pryſon houſe where <hi>Peter</hi> was ſhut vp in,<note place="margin">A miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quake at Peters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery out of Priſon.</note> and the other ſorts ſhake moſt of all at the higheſt partes or tops of houſes and Buildings. This alſo did but onely make away for <hi>Peters</hi> deliuery, and ſo cloſed vp the ſame agayne: the others where they once make any way thei quite deſtroy there for a full a doe, and neuer cloſe or ſhut vp the ſame agayne. Wherefore this was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a moſt ſpeciall and ſupernaturall kinde of Earthquake. But to return to <hi>Saturn.</hi> Hee hath vnder him theſe Prouinces and Countryes,<note place="margin">Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntries ſubiected to Saturn.</note> 
                  <hi>India, Aethiopia,</hi> and the leſſer <hi>Aſia.</hi> Hee alſo runneth his courſe ouer the zodiacke in <hi>30.</hi> yeares.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the iuriſdiction, proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etyes, effects, &amp; qualities of the ſeuen Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, as alſo of all other kindes here below ſubiected vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and this which I haue already ſayd, I thinke it enough and very ſufficient at this time. God graunt vs by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration thereof to condiſcend into a more deepe meditation &amp; contemplation of his moſt excellent and deuine Maieſty: which is all in all, and all to all, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poet ſaid well: who is to be bleſſed foreuermore.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF ALL SVCH Principall matters as is contayned <hi>in this Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Chylles. Fol. 63. b</item>
               <item>Adamant. Fol. 49. b</item>
               <item>Adder. Fol. 66. b</item>
               <item>Aeacus. Fol. 52. b</item>
               <item>Aelurus Fol. 15. a</item>
               <item>Aeolus. Fol. 53. a</item>
               <item>Athalis. Fol. 19. a</item>
               <item>Amurathes. Fol. 63. b</item>
               <item>Arſenius Fol. 64. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>BAlmetree. Fol. 40. b</item>
               <item>Beares. Fol. 47. b</item>
               <item>Bees. Fol. 14. b</item>
               <item>Beetels. Fol. 14. b</item>
               <item>Blaſing ſtars hovv inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. 35. a. The kindes therof. 35. a. the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt time for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 35. b. What they prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. 35. b. their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. Fol. 35. b</item>
               <item>Bull firſt baited. Fol. 47. b</item>
               <item>Bloudy bovves about the Sun vvhen appeared. Fol. 33. a</item>
               <item>Bucklers of fire ſeene in the Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fol. 9. b</item>
               <item>Burning lampes. Fol. 11. a</item>
               <item>Braſteis or the burninge kinde of Earthquake. Fol. 72. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>CAmell. Fol. 65. a</item>
               <item>Cameleon. Fol. 14. b</item>
               <item>Chancharus. Fol. 21. b</item>
               <item>Catte. Fol. 14. b</item>
               <item>Celeſtinus Fol. 64. a</item>
               <item>Cephalus. Fol. 49. a</item>
               <item>Circes. Fol. 60. b</item>
               <item>Chalazite. Fol. 67. b</item>
               <item>Chernites. Fol. 67. a</item>
               <item>Chiron. Fol. 60. b</item>
               <item>Clynias. Fol. 63. b</item>
               <item>Cocke. Fol. 39. a</item>
               <item>Cockatrice. Fol. 48. b</item>
               <item>Coloures ſeene in the ayre. Fol. 11 b</item>
               <item>Comets vvhat they prog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſticate Fol. 36. a</item>
               <item>Cormorant. Fol. 15. a</item>
               <item>Countryes ſubiect to lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. Fol. 16. a</item>
               <item>Cynamontree. Fol. 41. a</item>
               <item>Crabfishe. Fol. 40. b</item>
               <item>Cynocephalus. Fol. 14. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>DAnaé. Fol. 54. a</item>
               <item>Dactylus Fol. 39. b</item>
               <item>Day hovv ſpent in time
<pb facs="tcp:21445:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſt. Fol. 61. a</item>
               <item>Day hovv diuerſſy accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pted. Fol. 61. b</item>
               <item>Dictamus. Fol. 42. a</item>
               <item>Dolphin. Fol. 57. b</item>
               <item>Doues. 57. a. A Doue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a letter. Fol. 57. b</item>
               <item>Dragon Fol. 48. b</item>
               <item>Dyall of vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de out. Fol. 61. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Eagle. Fol. 21. b. 37. b</item>
               <item>Eatites. Fol. 37. b</item>
               <item>Echeneis Fol. 15. a</item>
               <item>Elaphoceratites Fol. 67. b</item>
               <item>Elephant &amp; dragon. Fol. 55. b</item>
               <item>Endymion. Fol. 8. b</item>
               <item>Europa. Fol. 54. a</item>
               <item>Evvetree. Fol. 67 a</item>
               <item>Earth Fol. 68. a</item>
               <item>Earth leſſe then the ſtars Fol. 69. a</item>
               <item>Earthquakes Fol. 70. a</item>
               <item>Earthquakes deſtroyinge vvhole Cities &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. 70. a. 100. Cyties at once deſtroied vvith an Earthquake in Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia. 70 a. differences &amp; ſundry kindes of Earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quakes. 71. b. A Vibra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion or gentle Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake happening here in England 1580. 6. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill. 71. b. A miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Earthquake at Peters deliuery. Fol. 73. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Foxe Fol. 66. a</item>
               <item>Fyer bruſting out of the earth vvith an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake. Fol. 71. a</item>
               <item>Fyer brands ſeene in the ayer. Fol. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. a</item>
               <item>Fyery flames ſeene in the ayer Fol. 9. b</item>
               <item>Flying ſtars Fol. 11. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>Galactites Fol. 67. b</item>
               <item>Galaxia or the milky vvhite vvay of the Ayer in the cleare nights Fol. 12. b</item>
               <item>Galazite Fol. 67. b</item>
               <item>Ganimedes Fol. 60. b</item>
               <item>Garland of the Moone. Fol. 12. a</item>
               <item>Garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of bloudy color Fol. 32. b</item>
               <item>Garlike Fol. 49. a</item>
               <item>Gaſpings, gapinges, and gulphes ſeene in the ayer. Fol. 11. b</item>
               <item>Glanis Fol. 4. a</item>
               <item>Goates Fol. 65. b</item>
               <item>Goshavvkes Fol. 30. a</item>
               <item>Gryffin Fol. 48. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Halo or Garlande of the Moone, and vvhat it prognoſticateth Fol. 33. a</item>
               <item>Halo of the Sun, &amp; ſtars vvhat it betokeneth. Fol. 12 b</item>
               <item>Hare Fol. 65. b</item>
               <item>Hebe Fol. 60. a</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21445:83"/>
               <item>Heliotropius Fol. 42. b</item>
               <item>Hermaphroditus. Fol. 19. a</item>
               <item>Hyatus. Fol. 72. b</item>
               <item>Hieraclitus. Fol. 64. b</item>
               <item>Hiero Fol. 63. b</item>
               <item>Horſe by vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oute. 45. a. A tryall of horſes Fol. 45. a</item>
               <item>Hovve to make Horſes Warlicke Fol. 46. a</item>
               <item>Hovv and vvhen horſes markes varye &amp; vveare avvay Fol. 46. a</item>
               <item>Hyacinthus Fol. 42. b</item>
               <item>Hyppodamus the ſvvyft runner. Fol. 44. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>Ichneumon Fol. 66. b</item>
               <item>Iuno. Fol. 60. a</item>
               <item>Iron. Fol. 50. a</item>
               <item>Iouialyſts hovv diſpoſed Fol. 55. a</item>
               <item>Iupiter Fol. 50. b</item>
               <item>Iupter Enhorcius. Fol. 54. b</item>
               <item>Iupiter Heterius idem</item>
               <item>Iupiter Homoginus. id.</item>
               <item>Iupiter Philius ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>Iupiter Zenius ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>Iupiter cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryes Fol. 58. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>Lapvving Fol. 48. b</item>
               <item>Lead. Fol. 67. b</item>
               <item>Lodeſtone. Fol. 49. b</item>
               <item>Lotarius. Fol. 64. a</item>
               <item>Long lack of the Sunne shine. Fol. 32. b</item>
               <item>Lote tree Fol. 41. b</item>
               <item>Luna hovv called. Fol. 6. b</item>
               <item>Lights in the nighte lyke the dayes light vvhen. Fol. 6. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Mars. Fol. 43. b</item>
               <item>Mars his countries, Fol. 50. a</item>
               <item>Mars and Sol hovv they differ Fol. 24. a</item>
               <item>Martialiſtes hovv diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Fol. 44. b</item>
               <item>Maximinianus Fol. 63. b</item>
               <item>Menalipus Fol. 44. a</item>
               <item>Mercury his diſpoſition. Fol. 16. b</item>
               <item>Mercurialiſts. Fol. 17. b</item>
               <item>Mercuries cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries. Fol. 18. b</item>
               <item>Minos. Fol. 52. b</item>
               <item>Moone. Fol. 6. a</item>
               <item>Moones Eclypſe. Fol. 8. a</item>
               <item>3. ſtates of the moone. 7. a 3. Moones appeared at once. 9. a. Courſe of the Moone. 7. b. Signes of prognoſtication in the Moone. Fol. 8. a</item>
               <item>Mule. Fol. 65. a</item>
               <item>Mulbery tree. Fol. 66. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>Nero Fol. 68. a</item>
               <item>Nightingale Fol. 38. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>OEnomaus. Fol. 44. a</item>
               <item>Onagri Fol. 65. a</item>
               <item>Orion Fol. 52. a</item>
               <item>Ovvles Fol. 48. a</item>
               <item>Oxe Fol. 47. a</item>
               <item>Oxen by vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt yoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Fol. 47. a</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:84"/>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Palmtree. Fol. 15. b</item>
               <item>Pantaure. Fol. 42. b</item>
               <item>Panthere. Fol. 14. a</item>
               <item>Partiche. Fol. 56. b</item>
               <item>Peantus Fol. 64. a</item>
               <item>Peacocke. Fol. 39. b</item>
               <item>Pellican. Fol. 66. b</item>
               <item>Peppertre. Fol. 41. a</item>
               <item>Phaeton. Fol. 12. b</item>
               <item>Phaenix. Fol. 37. a</item>
               <item>Picus. Fol. 60. b</item>
               <item>Pomes ſtone. Fol. 49. b</item>
               <item>Poppea Neroes Wyfe. Fol. 65. a</item>
               <item>Puttocke. Fol. 48. a</item>
               <item>Pye. Fol. 48. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>Rhododaphne. Fol. 67. a</item>
               <item>Rainbovve hovv ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. 33. a. the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovves three coloures vvhereof they come. Fol. 33. b</item>
               <item>Raynbovves vvhy there is often 2. or 3. at once 34. a. Coloures of the Raynbovv vvhat they be and vvhereof they come. Fol. 34. a</item>
               <item>Ruptor or the bruſtinge kind of earthquake. Fol. 72. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>SATVRNE. Fol. 59. a</item>
               <item>Saturne vvhoſe ſonne, &amp; his ſonnes. Fol. 60. a</item>
               <item>Saturniſts hovv diſpoſed Fol. 62. a</item>
               <item>Saturnes countries. Fol. 73. b</item>
               <item>Sarcophagus. Fol. 67. a</item>
               <item>Sea foxe. Fol. 40. a</item>
               <item>Scolopendra. Fol. 40. a</item>
               <item>Selenites. Fol. 15. b</item>
               <item>Seleno tropion. Fol. 15. b</item>
               <item>Spurg. Fol. 49. a</item>
               <item>Stars of vvhat bigneſſe. Fol. 69. a</item>
               <item>Stars hovv they differ in degree of magnitude Fol. 69. a</item>
               <item>Strombus. Fol. 40. a</item>
               <item>Succuſſion or the more daungerous kynde of Earthquake. Fol. 72. a</item>
               <item>Sol or the Sun vvhy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the midſt of the 7. Planets. Fol. 23. a</item>
               <item>Sol his Horſes. Fol. 25. a</item>
               <item>Sol his countries Fol. 43. a</item>
               <item>Sunne channging colour euery day Fol. 24. b</item>
               <item>Suns Eclypſe ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, &amp; ſome ſpecial. 26. a What kynd of eclypſe happened at Chriſtes death. Fol. 27. b</item>
               <item>Suns many appearing at once, as ſometimas 2. ſometimes 3. Fol. 30. b</item>
               <item>Suns &amp; Moones Eclypſe hovv they differ. Fol. 26. b</item>
               <item>Svvan. Fol. 66. b</item>
               <item>Syſiphus. Fol. 53. a</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:21445:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>Tantalus Fol. 53. a</item>
               <item>Tereus. Fol. 52. a</item>
               <item>Times horſes. Fol. 61. a</item>
               <item>Torpedo. Fol. 15. a</item>
               <item>Torches. Fol. 9. b</item>
               <item>Timon. Fol. 64, a</item>
               <item>Touchſtone. Fol. 49. b</item>
               <item>Trochus. Fol. 18. a</item>
               <item>Truſor or the thruſtinge kynd of earthquake. Fol. 73. a</item>
               <item>Tyger Fol. 55. b</item>
               <item>Tynne. Fol. 58. b</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>Venus. 19. b. her coloure 20, b. hovv she diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them that are borne vnder her. Fol. 20. b</item>
               <item>Vlyſses his ſubtelty. Fol. 53. b</item>
               <item>Vnicorne. Fol. 56. b</item>
               <item>Vulcanus. Fol. 51. a</item>
               <item>Vultures. Fol. 38. a</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>Whales. Fol. 58. a</item>
               <item>Wolfe. Fol. 46. b</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
